<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The First part of the history of England extending to the conquest of so much of Britain as was subjected by the Romans : with an introductory preface to the whole / written in the year 1666.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 233 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F978</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33319</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13228116</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13228116</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98589</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41341)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98589)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1550:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The First part of the history of England extending to the conquest of so much of Britain as was subjected by the Romans : with an introductory preface to the whole / written in the year 1666.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 35, [1], 63, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J.C. and are to be sold by William Grantham ... Henry Brome ... Thomas Basset ... Robert Horne ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College, Cambridge, Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  To 449.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98589:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98589:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FIRST PART OF THE HISTORY OF ENGLAND. EXTENDING To the Conqueſt of ſo much of <hi>Britain,</hi> as was Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by the <hi>Romans.</hi> With an Introductory Preface to the whole. Written in the YEAR, 1666.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. C.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>William Grantham</hi> in <hi>Weſtminster-Hall, Henry Brome</hi> at the <hi>Starr</hi> in <hi>Little Britain, Thomas Baſset</hi> under St. <hi>Dunſtans Church</hi> in <hi>Fleetstreet, Robert Horne</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> and <hi>Horn</hi> in the firſt Court in <hi>Greſham Colledge</hi> out of <hi>Biſhopsgate-Street,</hi> 1668.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98589:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98589:2"/>
            <head>AN INTRODUCTION to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving had opportunity and leiſure, for ſome time, during the late Revolutions, to obſerve ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral remarkable paſſages and the conſequences thereof, which have been fatal amongſt us here in <hi>England,</hi> ſuch perhaps as the World cannot overmatch, if equal, for variety and value: And taking notice further, that the root from which they ſprang was double pointed, the one part whereof conſiſting in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes, the other in deſigns, I thought I might not do an unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable Work to my Country, in endeavouring an Explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the one, and to lay open the other; and in committing Errors hope to be the rather pardoned, ſince what is here ſet down is not founded on any other bottom than that of a ſincere meaning.</p>
            <p>Hereupon I thought it good to write of the Actions of men, and confine the ſubject to thoſe of this Nation: wherein not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding having a large Field, we might as we paſs along take full liberty to obſerve and report what is conducible to the ſecond purpoſe; and in the beginning, by way of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction, diſcuſs certain Principles of great notice in the World, and not of different nature with the chief ſubject which may tend to unfold ſome miſapprehenſions, and alſo produce a general and beneficial Influence in our paſſage through the larger Work.</p>
            <p>The beginning muſt be low of ſome neceſsity, even upon the very firſt rudiments of Nature, though it ſeem at preſent diſtant and foreign to the purpoſe in hand. Neither can it well be otherwayes than ſomewhat large; but this is our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98589:3"/> confidence, though the proportion of the entrance to the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Edifice is not very juſt and ſuitable, eſpecially at this firſt impreſsion, when a very ſmall part only diſcovers it ſelf, yet they may hereafter, or it will at leaſt render the Fabrique more ſtable and capacious.</p>
            <p>Some Philoſophers hold that the Univerſe is an entire Maſs, infinite in reſpect of extent and diviſibility, that is as much as to ſay, without termination or bounds, and may be divided into parts alwayes diviſible, and but of one nature or diſpoſition: ſeeing then that there is motion in it, conſequentially it may follow, either that ſuch moving is <hi>ab aeterno</hi> (for it is a contradiction to ſay that ſome other thing moves it) or that the Univerſe has power of it ſelf to cauſe it's own motion; if the firſt were true, does it not follow likewiſe that there is no God in the World, which is againſt the light of reaſon, and the impreſsions in all mankind; and if the ſecond, that he is of the ſame nature with the other parts of the Maſs, as Earth or Water; and ſo of further conſequence, that every chip of Wood or Stone is part of the Godhead, which is abſurd. It may ſeem alſo inferreable of like neceſsity, that the faculties or powers of the Soul of Man, or other Animals, to know, to move, to be in pain, or to be pleaſed, are but the effects of the frame of thoſe bodies wherein they are, and ariſe from the figure and compoſition of part of the world, and unavoidably that Religion is but a craft whereby men are kept in awe; all which, in ſome parts appear inſenſible, in others contrary to the light of nature and of reaſon, to common ſenſe, the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal apprehenſion of ſober and wiſe men in all Ages, and would bring in with it a train of unſpeakable miſchiefs to a Commonwealth, and all Mankind, were it generally believed and admitted; and thereupon, contrary even to the nature of Truth, the fruits whereof are alwayes good.</p>
            <p>Other Philoſophers think that the univerſe is compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of a certain number of beings indiviſible in themſelves, though in reſpect of their quantity they may be Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically and Imaginarily divided, and that they are all of one nature, that their motion is not from any power within them, but either <hi>ab aeterno,</hi> or from the compoſition of ſome or all of them; the conſequences are much alike with thoſe of the foregoing Doctrine, and for the reaſons then mentioned are to be rejected.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98589:3"/>
            <p>A third there are who ſuppoſe ſeveral of divers na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſome whereof have a power to reſiſt penetration within the Sphere of their own beings, which is alſo a cauſe of their capacity to be moved, and are or may be called ſimple beings; others have withall further a faculty to know, to be in pain, to be pleaſed, to move, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and are or may be named Souls; ſome whereof, and not others, have alſo a power to reaſon, and are called rational Souls, (riſibilitie ſeems to flow from the faculty of reaſoning, and not to be one in it ſelf) they are likewiſe of opinion there may be other beings, ſuch as we call Spirits or Angels, and ſome paſt ſtories make mention of their appearances and actions; but of their nature, faculties, and buſineſs they preſume that we have ſcarce any knowledge, unleſs by revelation; but ſtrongly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, their employment is not to frighten and ſport with Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Children, and the weaker ſort of melancholick men; but rather that ſuch kind of inſtitutions were firſt promoted by certain Silver-Smiths, who making Shrines for the Temple of <hi>Diana,</hi> did thereby bring no ſmall gain unto the Crafts-men. They doubt not of a fifth, being different from the other four, who fram'd the World, and all things therein, and does ſtill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern it. Which Opinions are agreeable to thoſe of Wiſe men in all Ages, to the impreſſions in our Nature, the light of Reaſon, the benefit univerſally of Mankind, and upon which, neither inconvenience, nor abſurdity appears to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <p>I forbear to make a more particular entry into the firſt principles, or uſe other arguments to my intended purpoſe, becauſe this part would too much increaſe; and I chooſe rather for confirmation to any that ſhall doubt to refer him to the ſearches of his own reaſon, and the body of this Introductory Diſcourſe, from the congruity whereof, to the light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and of Reaſon, and the conſent within it ſelf, may ſome arguments perhaps flowe.</p>
            <p>2. Of thoſe beings before-mentioned in this place, we ſhall chiefly conſider <hi>Man,</hi> under which word is comprehended Male and Female, and either conſiſt of Soul and Body: The firſt is a ſingle being, the ſecond compound alſo, becauſe the one is not diviſible, as we think, and the other may be actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally divided.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98589:4"/>
            <p>Whether the parts of the Body, or the Soul it ſelf, had not a being <hi>ab aeterno,</hi> it may be is not penetrable by reaſon; and then we muſt have recourſe to revelation, and out of Holy Writ we are taught, that Almighty God created both.</p>
            <p>To proceed a little further, what is not conſtituted by ſome Agent, is ſo by chance now, by the many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand purpoſe that one may obſerve the parts of Man made for, it may well be concluded, it was in ſuch eſtate by contrivance, and not caſually. Further that there was a firſt man of every Family, becauſe men are born in time, and the Notions of time that are intelligible, have periods. That there was only one at firſt, or Male and Female, ſeems not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, in reſpect, that in all times the Actions generally of Men, much reſemble one another.</p>
            <p>In a Body is conſiderable, the Appetite, which is a propenſity ariſing from the conſtitution of the conſiſtent parts, and the quality of the fluid, without which, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, for want of Notions, and Fools and Madmen, from a defect in the parts of the Body, not being able ſufficiently to exerciſe the faculties of their Souls, could not ſubſiſt. They are many, ſome whereof are theſe; a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſity to eat and drink, which begins early, even from the birth, to live; and when we come to a full growth, and ſo not far from the beginning of our decay (which God deſigns alſo) to generate and propagate our ſpecies; and when they are born to nouriſh and defend them, not being capable of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing themſelves, and many other; which are all common to man, with other animals, From an exorbitant diſpoſition therein, proceeds generally the violence of one Animal upon another, and is in Man more extravagant uſually than in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but in him is a rational Soul to correct and regulate it.</p>
            <p>In the Soul is obſervable, a faculty to know; now knowledge ſeems to be an impreſſion on the mind, imprinted from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, by the conveyance of the Senſes: if it come through the Eye it is called a ſight, through the Ear a ſound, the Pallate a taſte, the Noſe a ſmell, and any other part of the Body a touch. Hence it follows, that of Bodies, which are fit objects of our ſenſes, we diſcourſe with ſome certainty; as of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, about quantities, called Mathematical, and not conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably improved ſince the antient time of <hi>Euclid;</hi> and our minds
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98589:4"/> not being infinite, but quantities limited, we have no intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible notions of infiniteneſs or aeternity. Hereupon further, that of what makes no impreſſion on the mind, we talk of but by gueſs, as we do of Spirits or Angels, and have no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them, unleſs revealed; and of ſuch things which are at ſo great a diſtance as we cannot receive well diſtinguiſht no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of them, we do but conjecture at too, as of thoſe of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomie; and of ſuch as are ſo little, that they come not into the mind, but imperfectly, or not at all, we likewiſe but gueſs at; as of the Elements of Nature in natural Philoſophy: yet in both theſe two laſt, greater knowledge hath come into the World by the improvement of the optick Science of late times, rendring, in effect, ſome things nearer, and others more large than the World wherein <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> lived, and many wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Philoſophers was acquainted with.</p>
            <p>The rational faculty ſeems to be a power to compare the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the mind, and that to be an Act of the Soul from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. If the compariſon be rightly and fully made, it is called right reaſoning; if but in part, and as yet no diſagreement found, we ſay it is probable, becauſe we find no difference, but do not conclude, becauſe we have not made a thorough ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. If there be a diſagreeing, we ſay it diſagrees from reaſon. Again what we can well compare, we can well rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of, as we may of the Notions of things large and near; what we can compare but in part, we can make but a probable conjectare of, and what not at all, we cannot reaſon of.</p>
            <p>Reaſoning ſeems thus to be done; Firſt the Soul applyes it ſelf to, or fancies, or calls to mind a notion of a thing we know well, and then makes application to another notion of a thing not ſo well known, and after, comparing them, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves how near they are alike in quantity, figure, colour, noiſe, ſmell, taſte, action, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and if we would perſwade another man to be of our opinion, we uſually goe ſome ſuch way as this to work: Firſt we affirm there is ſuch a thing, which we think to him is very well known, and that there are ſuch particulars about it, then we ſay the thing we would prove is the ſame with that in ſuch a reſpect, upon comparing has ſuch circumſtances, and therefore, in that conſideration, is the ſame thing: which ſeems likewiſe the foundation of Syllogiſmes and Logical Arguments. For example, by reaſoning, we find
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98589:5"/> there is a Deity who orders and diſpoſes all things in the world, for we thus argue. Concerning all the notions we have of things, we obſerve the figure and places of ſome, in a reſpect to others, have the marks of a Contriver, and there are them which have none: the firſt we ſay cannot be without deſign, the other come by chance, that is, without contrivance. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if we come to a Town, and find ſeveral things of certain figures in places, to an intended purpoſe, we conclude, and rightly, that they were contrived by the head, and acted by the hands of men; becauſe in comparing it with what we have heretofore ſeen, we never yet did obſerve ſuch things without contrivance, or made without hands; but if we ſee a heap of rubbiſh, we reſolve it might be in that ſhape by chance, for ſo we have formerly taken notice ſuch things have been. If we come to look into the admirable compoſition and figure of man, wherein, to a vaſt number of purpoſes, divers things are plac'd, and compare it with what we have ſeen and heard has been done by chance, or the power of men, or any other animate thing we converſe with, we ſhall preſently conclude they came neither by contingency, nor by the Art of any thing we have knowledge of, and therefore by ſome thing which we do not know, and give it the name of a Deity.</p>
            <p>We fetch another Argument, to this purpoſe, from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of motion, for we ſay, every thing we converſe with, has ſome cauſe to move it; and that nothing moves originally, where there is not a Soul or Spirit to ſtir it, and thence alſo, that the whole order of nature in motion proceeds from ſome Soul or Spirit, which we call likewiſe a Deity. But whether this be a ſingle perſon, or there be more than one, we cannot find out by reaſon, becauſe we have no particular and diſtinguiſhing notion of it, and ſo can make no compariſon to this purpoſe, and thereupon muſt have recourſe to revelation; and by Holy Writ we find, that there are three perſons, yet but one God; which does not diſagree from reaſon, for where is no defect in Judgement, nor violence of appetite, there may be no diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing in will. For the like reaſon we cannot diſcover the ſpecial place of reſidence, nor attributes of the Godhead; and therefore we do well when we ſay, that we know better what he is not, than what he is, or when leſs, and reſt in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98589:5"/>
            <p>When the mind is moved from without to the Soul in any particular notion, if we are awake, we ſay it comes into the mind, if aſleep, we call it a dream, and is without a motive force from the Soul, that is without our will, and with Man and Beaſts is alike; As to call to mind, or to reaſon, ſeems peculiar to the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Soul, and to be a motion from within. So little being known, is one cauſe there are ſo many Scepticks, Atheiſts, and variety of Phyloſophers. There may be a divine revelation different from the knowledge before mentioned; but it ſeldome comes, and is difficultly diſcovered, the world being full of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice and deceipt; but as we are capable enough to receive it, ſo doubtleſs God is powerfull ſufficiently to infuſe it.</p>
            <p>If it be asked what becomes of the Soul after diſſolution of the body, we muſt anſwer, we know not, that is, we can but conjecture probably; had we not a Revelation from holy writ that it enters a place of joy or torment, proportionably to the good or bad deeds acted in the time of its. conjunction with the body: which neither does diſagree from reaſon; for a being created may be continued, and what is from aeternity may be to aeternity: now if the Soul has a being when the body is diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as it may, and probably has, it is then ſomewhere, and being capable of pain and pleaſure before, it may be ſo on the diſſolution.</p>
            <p>Let us go a little further; we obſerve that ſome men who run an oblique courſe to the rule of reaſon, whom we call wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, are puniſh'd in this world in equal proportion to their offences, and others not; and again, they that walk regularly with great care and pains, are ſometimes rewarded here below, but not alwayes (which ha's been a ſtone whereat many have frequently ſtumbled) Now if there be not rewards and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments after this life, and there be alſo a God, he will then be unjuſt which is diſagreeing to reaſon; for we ſee even men of reaſon, if they are not overpowred by their appetites or paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, do juſt and reaſonable things, much more honourably ought we to think of the juſtice of Almighty God: And if there be no Deity, it will be incongruous to the general conſtitution of nature, and of the univerſal world which is regularly and juſtly framed: and thereupon we may inferr there is a Heaven and Hell: that is as much as to ſay, that Souls after this life have pains and delights according to their merit in this world, unleſs
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98589:6"/> where the ſpecial mercy of God on penitential applications does lighten if not extinguiſh the afflictions.</p>
            <p>Further, not much differing from the ſame purpoſe, it may be obſerv'd, that generally men of virtue, though for ſome time they may lye under ſcandals, and miſery, yet for the greateſt part of their years they proſper and are hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; but this is not alwayes ſo. And on the contrary, the wicked leading their lives according to their luſts, though they may have pleaſing dayes, yet have they many more miſerable; but it is not thus conſtantly. From hence it may be conjectur'd, that probably God Almighty hath uſually rewards for the virtuous in this world, as we often phraiſe it, and puniſhments on vitious perſons, to encourage the one, and diſcountenance the other; but not alwayes, to the intent they might not expect to ſet up their reſt here, but conclude upon a being hereafter; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and puniſhments according to the courſe of their lives.</p>
            <p>What the mind is, which I call that part of man where the Notions are treaſur'd up, is difficult to diſcover. This is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, that Notions will decay, and wear out, as men of Age diſcover; and the mind it ſelf ſeems to periſh in certain diſeaſes: from which a concluſion might be drawn, that it is of nature with the body, and little differing from that of other Animals, to the preſervation of whom it is neceſſary, but muſt ſay we think there may be a faculty in the Soul to receive them.</p>
            <p>3. FUrther, as to man in general, from the extent of his appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, in the particulars of his paſſions (that is to ſay) of luſt to meat, drink, or venery, of anger, and the like, and from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of his capacity to reaſon, proceeds the different diſpoſitions and tempers of mankind. Theſe two roots are well expreſs'd in the Poet <hi>video meliora proboque,</hi> which was the reſult of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; <hi>deteriora ſequor,</hi> which was the impulſe from the paſſion of revenge prevailing in <hi>Medea;</hi> the Spirit is willing, but the Fleſh is weak, ſaith the Scripture; and again there is a Law in our Members, warring againſt the Law of our minds.</p>
            <p>Theſe conſtitutious of men may be divided into many kinds with great difference; but I ſhall only take notice of ſome few particulars which make remarkable diſpoſitions. If the appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite be violent, and the reaſon weak, it renders that man giddy, inconſiderate and dangerous: I ſpeak not here of Fools or Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98589:6"/>
            <p>If a heady paſſion meet with an indifferent judgement, it makes thoſe who are the worſt men of the world: they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes making Diſturbances, heading of Factions, laying of Plots; they have a ſmattering of knowledge, and ſo preſume more than the foregoing ſort; and their outſide is for ſometime fair; but by their Ambition, Covetouſneſs, Luſt, and other Violencies, deſtroy afterward all that they with tollerable and formal reaſon did before diſcourſe of. They ſtudy the Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Princes, keep Factions alive to awe them with, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themſelves conſiderable; and commit a thouſand abſurdities in making out their Intereſts: If they are preferr'd to the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments of a Prince, by their vitions lives, they ſtain, and bring an evil report upon the beſt cauſes, and ſometimes ruine a Commonwealth, their Soveraign, and many honeſt men that adhere to his juſt Authority: if they are not advanc'd, they are the leading malecontents of a Nation, and oft thruſting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the head and diſguiſe of wel-meaning men, lead ſuch into errors before they are well aware of what theſe are within their boſomes. Of this kind was <hi>Caeſar Borgia Machiavells</hi> Prince, who never ſtaid at any Villany in order to the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his project, and in the end fail'd of all.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that have the moſt extended appetites, but ſtrongeſt reaſon, undertake great matters, and oft perform them to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but not without many Violencies, and much Injuſtice, by the praedominancy of their paſſions: ſuch was <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> the great.</p>
            <p>If the propenſity be in the loweſt extent, and meet with a judgement of the like low degree of capacity, the men with whom it is ſo, are generally free from offence, becauſe of the weakneſs of their appetites, and fooliſh for want of judgement, they are the Innocent ſoft men of the world. Of theſe it is meant when it is commonly ſaid <hi>probitas laudatur &amp; alget,</hi> plain dealing is good, but he that uſeth it ſhall die a Beggar. And for want of diſtinction, Proverbial Sayings of this nature, are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the occaſion of ſtaggering in the progreſſes of virtue.</p>
            <p>If the propenſity be weak, and the rational faculty indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, ſuch are the honeſt and good men of the world, in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral report.</p>
            <p>But if the provocations of nature are ſlow, and the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment exceeding good, which is very rare (for God Almighty
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98589:7"/> for the moſt part puts a quick reaſon where there are ſtrong paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions) then thoſe are the beſt men, ſome whereof have been called the Heroes of the World; and others, by the old Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens Canonized for Gods: And of this ſort in later times was <hi>Epaminondas</hi> among the <hi>Thebans,</hi> and <hi>Scipio Africanus</hi> among the <hi>Romans;</hi> before whom the World would not have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſtand, had they been Soveraign Princes of any conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Country: In adverſe fortune and in proſperity they are of equal temper, content and glory. The ſorting of theſe people make diverſities of factions and Religions; of whom one which is the laſt, is only ſafe for any Government to eſpouſe.</p>
            <p>But we muſt not conclude theſe obſervations without an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, where aeducation has been as it was in <hi>Alexander</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> a great Philoſopher, which had great influence on him; for during the ſtrength thereof, he lived virtuouſly, and with great renown; but after that began to wear out, and the force of Nature to return and prevail; the glory of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer life was ſhaded by his looſeneſs and debauchery. And the ſaying of another great Philoſopher to his Scholers, laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at a Phiſiognomer, who declared him by the outward view a vitious perſon, is not to be forgotten; <hi>So I am,</hi> ſays he, <hi>by Nature, but I have made a Conquest by Philoſophy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. IN the next place place we will conſider the actions of Men, now Law is the rule by which ſuch, or any other beings are governable.</p>
            <p>The Law of Nations is what is generally practiſed among Neighbour Countries, and has chiefly concernment in War and Peace. If it be univerſally uſed, it is ſaid to be the Law of Nations through the whole world, as we often call it, and ought not to vary from the Law of God, which is the Law of Reaſon: If they be made by Man, we call them humane Laws, from the Author: If they concern the conſtitution of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of a Nation, they are called Fundamental, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways not. With us in <hi>England,</hi> thoſe that relate to private Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations, or Places, or Perſons in ſome particular conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, are named Privileges, becauſe they are private Laws: ſuch which have reſpect to all in general, becauſe they are common to all, are called the common Law; if they be made by Act of Parliament, they may concern either Privileg'd men
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98589:7"/> or Places in particular, or the Community in general, having an extenſive power over all, and goe by the name of Statutes.</p>
            <p>The Laws of Nature, I take it, though ſome think otherwiſe, is that Rule whereby all things in the World which have not reaſon, or want the uſe of it, have their actions governed; and is ſolely managed by the Providence of God, and may be ſaid a neceſſity; ſo the motion of the Stars, the actions of Birds and Beaſts, and other Brute Animals are directed.</p>
            <p>By the Law of Nature all Animals follow and obſerve their Appetites, and to the preſervation of themſelves, eat what is proper food for them, where they can get it, and take from, and feed on one another as Birds and Beaſts of prey; and this by neceſſity, for without that, many could not live, and God has deſign'd it for a good end; for other wiſe ſome kinds would increaſe to an unfitting proportion for the Earth to ſuſtain: and what is done by this Law, is no ſin, in reſpect of the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity. Among the old, and ſome new Philoſophers, there are thoſe, who being too intent hereon, have held a fate in all things, and certain Chriſtians a too ſtrict praedeſtination.</p>
            <p>Were it not indeed for the ſpecial Providence of God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, that rational Souls have ſome freedom of will, and that the whole World will not be found in the ſame ſtate it now is, at ſuch time as the poſition of the Heavens will be thus again hereafter; perhaps it might not be abſurd to think of Platonick years; but thoſe things will alter the Scene.</p>
            <p>By the ſpecial Providence of God, I underſtand his extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary works, which are rare, and do therefore argue the excellency of the Artiſt, who has made a noble Engine with ſo much various curioſity as the World is; and yet for many thouſands of years it needs no correction or amendment that we can diſcover. But we cannot otherways ſuppoſe then that ſome men draw abſurd conſequences of Atheiſm herefrom; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing there is no Deity, becauſe we have not converſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with in ſpecial manner.</p>
            <p>The Law of Reaſon, which is ſometimes called the Law Moral, I underſtand, that by which animate things rational ought to be governed, and is alſo the Law of God, becauſe God directs it. We call it the Law of reaſon, becauſe we find it out by reaſoning; and conſiſts chiefly of two parts, in reſpect of a double relation, the one toward God, the other Man.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98589:8"/> That Law likewiſe which is revealed in Scripture, is called the Law of God, for the above mentioned cauſe, and of the Law of reaſon, is rather an explanation, than any wayes different, and ſeems ill interpreted where it diſſents.</p>
            <p>The Will is an Inclination of the Soul to do a thing; It is ſometimes diſpoſed by the body from it's paſſions, and at other times by the reſults of reaſon, and very rarely is a Will with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Motion from the one, or an Inclination from the other. As either predominates, ſo the Soul does generally Will, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the ſpecial direction of Almighty God, or a ſpontaneous Motion does vary it. Some likewiſe will urge a fatal neceſſity, having their minds chiefly intent upon the laſt reſult of reaſon, as others taking notice both of that, and the impulſe of nature; but the Will, though it is rarely known to act freely, yet one would think it might by this Inſtance. Put the caſe the Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite do diſpoſe a man to a vitious houſe, his Reaſoning to more ſober and convenient affairs: yet it ſeems not improbable he may Will, and in ſome caſes do an act diſtinct from, and not mov'd by either. Many diſputes concerning the freedome of the Will, have been the ſubject of great controverſie in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, and Profeſſors of Religion have brought it into queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Divinity, delighting rather in ſuch vain altercations, than to obſerve and promote the ſubſtance of Gods worſhip, in which the world does generally agree.</p>
            <p>Without reaſon it ſeems there could be no Sin, as there is not in irrational Animals, nor likewiſe virtue, for they both proceed from the comparing or reaſoning faculty of the Soul of man. Hereupon it follows, that to be chaſt by a diſpoſition of body, or to be temperate in Meat, Drink, or Venery, on the the ſame cauſe is not a virtue. To be valiant upon the warmth of wine, or by the natural heat of the brain, a weariſomeneſs of the world, upon greater skill in a weapon than another, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtrength of body, a bruitiſh nature, or an abſurd fear of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accounted Cowards if they refuſe to put their lives upon the chance of a Die, as many do with unmanly weapons, is not true Valour, nor oft accompanied with the courage of Nature, nor practiſed in well govern'd Commonwealths, or amongſt the truly Valiant and Victorious ſort of people; and is at this day in greater eſteem no where, than amongſt the moſt effeminate Men and Nations. Neither is it a virtue to be juſt and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98589:8"/> when the deſign is to purpoſes of ambition; but then are men ſaid to do an act of virtue, when they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect alone to the command of Almighty God, either revealed; or found out by reaſon.</p>
            <p>Hereupon likewiſe we do count Children, Fools, Madmen, and ſuch as are of non ſane memory by Sickneſs or Age, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from the Law of God, which is of reaſon, and generally through the whole world in humane Laws, they are not puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no more than Beaſts when they do miſchief, becauſe for the time they are deprived of their reaſon, they are in like condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with other Animals.</p>
            <p>If a man in a capacity to reaſon, do not reaſon aright, this ſeems no ſin in him, nor if he acts according to his reaſon; for no man can be expected but that he ſhould do according as he judges. But if a man ſhall reaſon aright, and not do according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to him it is ſin, and again to reaſon aright, and act from thence is a virtue, to reaſon wrong, and from thence do wrong, may be called a good meaning, or to reaſon wrong, and do dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently, may be ſaid an ill meaning; but enquire whether they be virtuous or ſinful actions.</p>
            <p>It follows further, that to puniſh men barely for their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is unjuſt and unreaſonable; but if they endeavour to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulge them (though they are conceited that ſo they ought to do) if that may prove miſchievous to a Commonwealth, they are to be reſtrained notwithſtanding; as one ought to take a ſword out of a Madmans hand, or as he that is infected with the Plague, ought not to be puniſh'd for having a Diſeaſe, yet if he will go abroad to endanger others, the Laws of this Land do reaſonably juſtifie the puniſhing of him, even in ſome caſes to death, upon this ground chiefly to prevent danger in others; and they that pretend an opinion, but are not thereof perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, deſigning under that colour to diſturb a Nation, and raiſe advantages to themſelves, ought to have inflicted on them heavy penalties.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, ſeeing by reaſon we find out that there is a God, by the like reaſon we are taught we ought not to ſpeak or act irreverently concerning him; or to ſet up any ſeigned God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head againſt, or equal with him; ſeeing he made the world, and continues it in a wonderful order; in caſe of evil, or miſchief happened or impending, he is, we may conclude, moſt able to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98589:9"/> relieve us. Hereupon it follows that we ought to deſire help of him, reaſon tells us he will ſuccour us the rather, for ſo doing, and that we ought to be humbly thankfull for what mercies he ſhews, which is our duty toward God.</p>
            <p>Come we then to what we owe toward Man. By the Law of Nature we do ſuppoſe that every man may have a right to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, but by the Law of reaſon no more than an equal right to all things: in the firſt caſe man may have what he can get, which is the ſtate common to other Animals; and in the ſecond, there ought to be an equal diviſion in convenient proportions, which is peculiar to rational creatures, and having been made, we ought to be content with our parts, and not either by ſtrong hand, or cunning circumventions, take from our Neighbours their ſhares.</p>
            <p>In ſome ſort alſo we have a duty toward other Animate Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; for by the Law of Nature we may make uſe of them, but to afflict them, eſpecially when we have no benefit thereby, as it is not agreeing with reaſon, but againſt it, ſo is it abominable even to the nature of man.</p>
            <p>5. ANother faculty of the Soul, is to be delighted, and pained, if they be not divers. The things which cauſe the firſt, are called good, and on the contrary, thoſe that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the other, evill, and in the abſtract good and evill, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their degrees are they ſaid to be more or leſs ſo. Now if the queſtion be asked what is the chiefeſt good, before we anſwer, we muſt diſtinguiſh and ſay, if it be meant of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal cauſe, doubtleſs God Almighty; if it be ſpoken to the means as to our own furtherance, we may reply, a virtuous life; if to the thing it ſelf, the greateſt pleaſure is that which is lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt in extent, duration, and freedome from evil, and is the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our deſigns, and end of our labours.</p>
            <p>But let our endeavours be never ſo capacious, without a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial providence of Almighty God, Virtue can rarely, if at all, make a happy man in this world, when fortune is wanting, which is the ſtate of a thing without deſign: and of all contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies, that is moſt conducible, when one lives amongſt a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py people: for an unfortunate Nation, like the rapid motion of the eighth Sphere, ſpoken of by ſome Philoſophers, forceth againſt their proper motion all Inferiour Orbes to a confuſion of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98589:9"/> them, and a neceſſary yeilding to that firſt great Circle. And a happy Country does much improve the Fruits of a virtuous life, to all that live therein.</p>
            <p>6. THat then in the concerns of a mans life, having ſo great a ſhare, in the next place let us enquire thereof. The ſtrength and happineſs of a Nation, ſeems chiefly to conſiſt in theſe things: that they have a good Government, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be many in number, and that they be conveniently provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of all neceſſaries.</p>
            <p>The Graecians having their eye eſpecially upon the chief men that governed the ſeveral Commonwealths in their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, which was divided into many; and obſerving ſome were directed by one man principally, others by many of better ſort, (that is to ſay) by the richer; and ſome by the people gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally; did call the firſt kind a Monarchy, the ſecond an Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſie, the third a Democraſie, for the reaſons expreſſed parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in the derivation of their ſeveral names; and thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominations have been brought through the Romane Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts to us at this day. But this ſeeming to be too general, there are them who do ſay, that there be alſo mixt Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>The way of diviſion we will chuſe, ſhall be this; All Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments are either of an abſolute Monarchy, an abſolute Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique, where the Authority is divided, or mixt. By an abſolute Monarchical Government, I mean, (and as I take it, it is the general acception of the word) ſuch as where the Legiſlative power, and the Executive, is Capitally or Originally all in one perſon, without aſſent of others; for if one man make Laws, and then Execute them; or Govern by the dictate of his own Will, or without Law, it ſeems not different in nature; and every Officer of inferiour degree, in ſome ſenſe, may be ſaid to be a Legiſlator. By an abſolute Republique, where a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor voice (which muſt be from three at leaſt, and may be to any number more) has the Legiſlative and Executive power. By a divided Government, when the Legiſlative is in the one entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the Executive in the other. By a mixt, when part of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or of both, is in the one, and the reſt in the other.</p>
            <p>An abſolute Monarchical Government, ſeems not ſo good for the Prince, nor the people; becauſe every one cannot well
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98589:10"/> execute the Legiſlative power at the laſt reſort, in reſpect he may want Judgement or regular affections: if he be himſelf, or leave his Succeſſor of corrupt nature, it does not oft fall out, that his Kingdom or his Life is not taken from him; for if he be vitious, which Sycophants will not only ſooth him in, but promote: and men are generally enclin'd to thoſe moſt, who cover their infirmities: having ſuch authority, he will hardly refrain that which men account their properties; and the abuſed to be revenged, and others, upon apprehenſions, to ſecure themſelves, will be apt to joyn in conſpiracy. If he want judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, deſigning men of greater wit will undermine and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him: All Ages are full of ſtories of this kind, and from ſo great a Latitude of power in one perſon abuſed; the word Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, which at firſt did bear the honourable name of a King, grew at laſt to import an Oppreſſor. <hi>Thales</hi> of <hi>Greece</hi> being asked on his return from certain Travails which he had made, what was the ſtrangeſt ſight he had ſeen in them, made this anſwer, <hi>A Tyrant that had lived long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it muſt not be denied when an abſolute Monarch proves a wiſe Prince that is judicious and moderate in his paſſions, he many times does admirable things, and ſettles ſuch Laws and Cuſtoms as continue ſome diſcents, which ſeems an objection to what is before mentioned, and has been heretofore obſerved by others; but for the former reaſons, and that an excellent Prince may perform more renowned actions in another kind of Government, it ſeems not to deſerve the preference.</p>
            <p>Neither is an abſolute Republique good, becauſe it cannot well perform the Executive part in the firſt of the ſource; for it muſt be done by one mind in reſpect of contrivance, ſecreſie, reſolution and expedition, in which they generally have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. It follows then in the third place, that if many men ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the executive part, or one man without conſent, the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative, or any part of each, it cannot always ſo well be done, for the reaſons before; but if the Legiſlative be executed by one upon the aſſent of many, and the Executive by one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; that this is the beſt Government, and by experience I think it has been found to have endured longer, and with more advantages than any other. But we may ſay of Governments as is ſaid of the Elements, that they are rarely found unwoven with one another, and that they take their names from the moſt predominate.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98589:10"/>
            <p>But becauſe ſome have doubted of this, and we would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly endeavour to give a reaſon of the known Laws of <hi>England,</hi> let us enter more particularly into the boſom of this ſubject. We are to remember that, as was ſaid before, every man by the Law of Reaſon has an equal right to every thing, (from which ſingle conſideration in a ſort of people with us lately in <hi>England,</hi> did proceed the Levelling humour) But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome things are not poſſibly to be divided, in reſpect of their nature amongſt Mankind, as the Air we breath; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers cannot be ſo well uſed in common, as Meat, Drink and Clothing; it follows that in reaſon there ought to be a diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe, and that thoſe remain entire; for in all Societies where Community is pretended, as laſt they come to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty when the Meat and Drink and Clothing is diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted.</p>
            <p>If it be asked in what proportion thoſe things which may be divided, are to be diſtributed, reaſon tells us according to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans neceſſity. If by what Rule or Law, for a Rule and Law is all one, doubtleſs by the Law of God, which is found out by reaſon, and thereto agreeable.</p>
            <p>If who ſhall declare what the Law of Reaſon is; one man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone may erre, but with aſſent of others, he is leſs lyable: a multitude have in them more oft the voice of Nature, <hi>Vox Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li Vox Dei</hi> in many caſes is the more true. Hereupon, though one man alone may be good, yet with aſſent of a Parliament, as it is conſtituted with us in <hi>England,</hi> of all ſorts of people, from all places, is ſurely generally better to ſuch a purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The laſt long Parliament one would think is an objection, ſithence many extravagant enormities ſell out. Though they cannot poſſibly be excus'd, yet this may be ſaid for them; A Parliament may be in the wrong until better conſideration, and to them at ſometimes it was the more excuſable, ſithence they had many voluntary and neceſſary excluſions; and we cannot tell what they would have done, when the heat which provok't them by the general noiſe of grievances blown up by facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men beyond a juſt report, had been a little ſlack't upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thoughts, if there had been no purgations. I ſuſpend my own thoughts, and chooſe rather to report the opinion of our late moſt pious and judicious Prince King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, and in his own words, which are theſe to his Son our preſent So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98589:11"/> 
               <hi>Nor would I have you to entertain any averſation or diſlike of Parliaments, which in their right constitution with free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and honour will never injure or diminiſh your greatneſs, but will rather be as interchangings of Love, Loyalty, and confidence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Prince and his People. Nor would the events of this black Parliament have been other than ſuch (however much biaſed by factious inelections) if it had been preſerved from the inſolencies of popular dictates, and tumultuary impreſſions, the ſad effects of which will no doubt make all Parliaments, after this, more cautious to preſerve that freedom and honour which belongs to ſuch Aſsem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies (when once they have ſhaken off this yoak of vulgar encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) ſince the publique intereſt conſiſts in the mutual and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good both of Prince and People. Nothing can be more happy for all, than in fair, grave and honourable ways to contribute their counſels in common, enacting all things by publique conſent, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Tyranny or Tumults, We muſt not ſtarve our ſelves becauſe ſome men have ſurfeited on wholſom food.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The inconſtancy of the Vulgar, noiſed in all Stories, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother objection. We muſt here again diſtinguiſh: If the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, I mean the common voice of men take upon them to judge of a perſon, they are oft miſtaken, for they do it by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance only; and Men upon deſigns, affecting popularity, put on Maſques and Diſguiſes, which is the ground of Vulgar error in theſe things; but if they take upon them to judge of what is reaſonable, the common voice has generally leſs er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror than that of particular men. When a man appears virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, they commend him; and when vitious, they decry him: ſo then the wavering proceeds not from the people, who are conſtant always to the commendations of virtue, but from the ſubject, who changes the courſe of his actions, and is himſelf variable in this life, or at leaſt has a different outward ſhape.</p>
            <p>Now as a good Goveenment may juſtly challenge the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence of the three neceſſaries before mentioned, ſo good Laws may bear the greateſt reputation therein. They will Execute themſelves, and the Executive part is uſually moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective. Laws diſpoſe men in their natures to good, or bad; are the cauſes of faelicity or miſery according as they are made, and alter the very form of mens manners.</p>
            <p>The Romans excelled herein, which I count was the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal foundation and durance of their Victories and Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98589:11"/> 
               <hi>Suetonius</hi> takes notice that <hi>Caeſar</hi> did eſpecially obſerve the ſtrength of body in the choice of his Souldiers, depending doubtleſs on the Roman Diſcipline (which was a branch of their Law) to encline their minds to Valour, and conduct. <hi>Alexander,</hi> being in this particular not altogether ſo happy, did chiefly inſiſt upon a good election, in reſpect of Judgement, regular Affections, and Experience.</p>
            <p>Being upon the point of Laws, let it not be thought amiſs to mention theſe few obſervations. In a Commonwealth there ought not to be too many Laws, becauſe they cannot then be well remembred by them to whom they are a Rule, nor thoſe who are to Judge by them. The Penalties ought to be equal to the Offence; if they be too little, it renders the Law frivolous, as are many of our Antient Paenal Statutes; by the riſe of the value of money in theſe later Ages, by the pleaſure of our Kings; but more conſiderably by the fall of the value of Silver, occaſioned by the plenty of it from the Weſtern World, not long ſince diſcovered: and ſome made of late are rendred uſeleſs upon a like reaſon. They are not to be too great, becauſe of the Infirmities of Mankind; but an error of this laſt nature is on the right hand.</p>
            <p>A juſt Action, is what is done by a Rule or Law, and Juſtice by way of excellency, is that which is done by the Rule or Law of Reaſon. Now the determination of controverſies, which is a doing of Juſtice, ought to be near the reſidence of the parties, and with ſmall, if any charge, to the concerned perſons, but what is voluntary; otherwiſe it will become a burden to the greater number, and intollerable to the poorer ſort, and in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of a ſmall value, to all.</p>
            <p>The common objection that the Law brought into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, would make it differ in many places, is idle; ſithence by experience in the Seſſions of Juſtices of the Peace, and Courts of Record, in Corporations through all <hi>England</hi> we find the contrary.</p>
            <p>To paſs on when the Laws are made, who ſhall compare the actions of men with theſe Rules or Laws, that is, ſhall be Judge of the breaches and obſervances of them. Many cannot well perform this part in a common courſe, becauſe there may be wanting a reſolution: one may be of opinion, by a certain fact, ſuch a Law, or a branch thereof, is tranſgreſs'd, another not, a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98589:12"/> third may differ from both; for the ſame fact may be thought Murder by one, Manſlaughter by another, and <hi>Se defendendo</hi> by a third: ſo to prevent a delay in Juſtice, it is generally well committed to a ſingle perſon, who may appoint ſubſtitutes with an appeal to himſelf.</p>
            <p>If the Laws are well made, and Judgement regularly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; yet without a Coercive power Men will not obey them: the placing thereof ought not to be in a major voice, becauſe they may be of ſo many ſeveral minds; and conſequently by delay, and want of reſolution, Juſtice may be imperfect: two have the ſame unaptneſs; therefore it is well repoſited in the hands of a ſingle perſon. Thus in <hi>England,</hi> the foundation of Judicature and power is in the King, and did appear more perſpicuouſly heretofore, when they ſate uſually on one of the Benches, and are both well plac'd in the ſame perſon, ſeeing no one of either can be ſo well executed alone; it is called with us the Executive power, as his other with the praevious aſſent of the Lords and Commons the Legiſlative.</p>
            <p>If inquiry be whether he ought to be elected, we anſwer no, for theſe reaſons: A major voice in the chooſers may not be; becauſe many men may be of various minds, and think of ſeveral perſons, and the common good thereby neglected, as is oft ſeen, for want of a Governour; if we ſay by Lot, the nominations may be ſo large, and chance ſo great; to which may be added in both, corruptions by Money, and other jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling devices, that men of worth are not like to be choſen, as is of frequent experience; and when an election is made, the Elected's natural affections to himſelf and Family will make a different Center to the intereſt of the publique.</p>
            <p>The next queſtion may be, whom, and out of what Family; that alſo muſt be determined by the Law of God, which is of Reaſon, or of Nature. The firſt cannot do it, becauſe God Almighty having made all Families equal, no reaſon can be given why one ſimply conſidered in it ſelf, ſhould be praefer'd before another: which conſideration taken alone has cauſed much miſchief in the World: But we muſt haſten off, and not ſtay here. Let us then have recourſe to the other branch of the Law of God, which is the Law of Nature; and there poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on gives a Title. So then, that Man or Family which has got poſſeſſion of the Crown, has a good title by the Law of God;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98589:12"/> and Reaſon tells us, the elder poſſeſſion is to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the younger, to prevent Contention, which is the Nurſe of War, and conſequently a deſtruction to Mankind: and if any ſhould now ſet on foot a ſuppoſed elder than the now King of <hi>Englands;</hi> a long and peaceable poſſeſſion is to be praefer'd before a more antient pretence; ſithence that is well known, and this can be but gueſs'd at, time having worn out a certain knowledge.</p>
            <p>It follows one would think, that he which has poſſeſſion of the Crown may diſpoſe it to whom he will; and ſo he might by the Law of Nature; but the Law of Reaſon comes now in again, and tells us that <hi>Salus Populi</hi> is <hi>Suprema Lex:</hi> therefore ſeeing the diſcovery of his mind in many caſes, eſpecially near his death, when his reaſon and ſenſes decay; ſome interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it one way, others in a different manner, would be diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to know which would deſtroy the people by diviſion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning men being ſubject likewiſe to ſuborn witneſſes; and uſe other arts to deceive: Thereupon it follows, that ſuch a one ought to be his Succeſſor, whom we may reaſonably think Parents would generally mean, and that is one of his own Children, which is alſo agreeable to nature, and of them the eldeſt, as being at the greateſt exerciſe of reaſon. The Love of a man enclines generally moſt to himſelf, in a ſecond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to his Children, and then to his Brothers and Siſters: ſo the Princes Children are to be praefer'd before his other Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. By this means the intereſt of the People is incorporated with that of the Crown, as it is (God be bleſſed) with us in <hi>England:</hi> and thereby the natural motions of a King, in favour to himſelf, his Children and Family, tend of neceſſity to the good of his Subjects; and Matrimony is a good determiner of which are his; being a publique act.</p>
            <p>The principal objections againſt an Haereditary Monarchy are theſe: The Prince may be fooliſh, of non ſane memory, a Child, he may dote, or be vitious: all which may happen to any ſingle perſon elected; though it be rare that a Child is cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen: and often it falls out, that the worſt men are in the beſt difguiſes. But to anſwer, If there be good Laws made (which are an eſſential part to the happineſs of a Nation) he can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit no general and conſiderable injury without Agents, who ought to be ſubject to the Law, the dread whereof will terrifie
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98589:13"/> them: Good men will be adviſing him, his near Relations, for the Love of him, and their Family will perſwade much, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors or Guardians, may be to them in ſome of the particular caſes before mentioned.</p>
            <p>This we may be ſure of by experience, that in all Elections, men generally of the beſt tempers are not choſen, they are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally but of the middle rank, and ſo is alwayes a race of Kings at worſt; for as there may be one extreamly bad, there may be another in diſcent as greatly good, ſo that though at periods there may be difference, yet take the line from firſt to laſt, it is of the common nature of mankind, which we the rather ought to be content with, becauſe in a train of Elections this is the beſt was ever found, and but rarely too, that they were of the general diſpoſition of humane nature, and this the diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that the conſideration of his Family, which muſt after return to a private life, will incline him to ſuch corruptions as there was alwayes, yet found men to prompt them to, as alſo their Electors.</p>
            <p>But to conclude this, God Almighty ſeems to have left ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what deſective herein, as in many other caſes, to the intent there may be an invitation and neceſſity on humane nature to ſeek after him, and implore his ſpecial providence for a virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince, and acknowledge it with humble gratitude, when we are bleſt with ſuch a one. For this kind of Government, appears in the Records of time, moſt practicable, durable, and of feweſt deficiencies; whereas other kinds, eſpecially abſolute Commonwealths, if there were any purely ſuch, have been ſo rarely fortunate, that they look like Anomola's of nature.</p>
            <p>The Coercive power may be divided into two parts, ariſing from the two wayes by which a Nation is governed, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, or compulſion, and are called the Eccleſiaſtical and Civil: both which are united in our Soveraign; and being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in ſome other Countries by their claſhings, are oft times of very fatal conſequence; the Churchmen perſwading one way, and the Civil Magiſtrate compelling another.</p>
            <p>Neither of thoſe two can be well managed without rewards, as well as puniſhments: rewards are either in opinion as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, of which the King with us is the fountain, or ſuch real good of the world, as men have need of, or affect, and in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract, anſwering all things, is money.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98589:13"/>
            <p>Becauſe there will be a perpetual want, there ought to be a conſtant Revenue ſufficient for the common and uſual defence of the people againſt Invadors, and Rebels, and upon extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary occaſions, a ſupplemental ayd by conſent in Parliament; for it is truly reported that money is the Sinews of Warr, and I may add alſo, of Peace.</p>
            <p>Hereupon it follows, that ſuch who abuſe a Prince, in his Revenue, do weaken his power according to the proportion of the wrong, and conſequently the ſecurity of the whole, and of all miſchiefs that can be done to a King or his Country; this is one of the greateſt imaginable, becauſe it deſtroys even the foundation of his power; and for the ſame reaſon the Laws ought to be very penal in this particular.</p>
            <p>To keep the Subjects in obedience will require the aſſiſtance of many Civil Officers, which in reſpect of command ought to be ſubordinate to one another, according to ſuch Rules as would be here taedious to mention.</p>
            <p>What kind of men ſhould be employed is eaſie to apprehend, No man doubts ſure but they ought to be of reaſon and regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of life, the fate and conſequence of employing ſuch as are of arrogant, but weak judgements; and eſpecially of violent and exorbitant paſſions, of luſt, ambition, covetouſneſs, cruelty, are negligent and idle; have cauſed many tragical Iſſues to thoſe Princes who have made uſe of them: they gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſtudy induſtriouſly the nature of their Soveraign; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving well underſtood that, in order their deſigns, attempt ſuch things as will not abide the Touchſtone of the Law, in preſumption upon his favour, then diſtruſting his affections may waver, they ſeek to ſecure themſelves on their own bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom: Now the foundation of power, as was before mentioned, conſiſts in money: Hereupon they endeavour to amaſs vaſt ſums together, whereby to fortifie themſelves; but this they conclude will not ſuffice, unleſs they ſuppreſs the power even of the Prince himſelf, and all meritorious perſons: the ways they take to the firſt purpoſe are generally theſe; they humour him in his vices if he have any that will raiſe an Odium, and ſo looſe him among the people; they weaken him in his Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, by countenancing publique frauds, wherein they have oft times a ſhare; in his Authority, by fomenting factions in Church and State, and when they have come to the utmoſt of their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98589:14"/> power, they dare even him to do any thing contrary to their own humour; but on the other ſide, the trueſt States-men are thoſe, who ſtudy the intereſt of their King and Country, are Honeſt and Judicious, and of profound Counſell in Warr and Peace.</p>
            <p>The duty of Subjects is not well underſtood till it be well conſidered, ſo not by Children and younger people, nor by them who have a deſect in judgement, that are taken up with the cares of the world, and other imployments which poſſeſs their minds: hereupon it is agreeable to reaſon, that ſome ſhould be ſet apart from other affairs, of the beſt judgements, to inſtruct the people in their duties, and perſwade them to it, and of good liſe to lead them by example, becauſe it is of great pains and time to underſtand what is fitting to be done, they ought to have no conſiderable other employment, to the intent they may throughly mind that: but they may miſtake, therefore it is convenient they ſhould have certain Articles of Doctrine, from which they may not vary in their inſtructions, which ought to be honeſt, and according to reaſon; for ſuch which have other foundations, make it doubtfull, and oft times pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce dangerous conſequences from credulous Churchmen. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are to be ſequeſtred from private trade and gains, it is fit they ſhould be publiquely maintained; and to the end they might be free from teaching to pleaſe the people, they ought to be independent on their Pariſh in their maintenance. If it be thought Homilies may ſerve this turn, it ought to be conſider'd, and may be well replyed, that they cannot be made ſo proper for every particular Congregation, and occaſion; nor are they ſo naturally and forcibly pronounced, as the Words and Notions which are of a mans own conception, though thoſe may be good alſo in their kind.</p>
            <p>For publique mercies received, reaſon tells us it is fit there ſhould be publique acknowledgement of gratitude, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure general bleſſings, general applications, and that ſuch men who beſt ſhould know the value of them, which are they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, are the moſt proper for theſe Sacrifices. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they ought to be ſubordinate to the Prince, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons before mentioned, and to one another, for the more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious conveying of orders, and inſpecting the people and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Clergie, by a diſtribution of that nature which is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98589:14"/> to right reaſon, and ſo to the Law of God, and of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence by Divine right; but (God knows) ſuch is the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs of mankind, that if a man looks through the world in divers Ages he may ſee too many have been choſen by favour, ſome in reſpect of intereſt; by money becauſe they will ſerve for little, and others, becauſe being of ill lives themſelves, they will the rather paſs by reprehenſion of thoſe perſons who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote them: and for this very reaſon, the perſonal vices of the Clergie, by men that do not diſtinguiſh the office from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, does endanger oft times the very order of Hierarchy; for ſuch as theſe, wanting the ſubſtance of their calling, which is good Preaching, and a Regular life, ſet up the formal and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonious part of Religion, inſinuating it for the ſubſtance, the better to blind and cover their own vitious lives, and ſo cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate many Hereticks, and Atheiſts; the firſt hunting for Truth in ſome other or new Religion, becauſe they find notorious er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in that they are taught; and the other ſuſpecting all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they perceive deceipts in ſome part of it.</p>
            <p>To conclude this, in memory to our Mother the Church of <hi>England;</hi> whoſe conſtitution is agreeable to what is before mentioned of this nature; it may be ſaid ſhe was a branch cut off from the body of the Romane Tree in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> and engrafted into the Royal Stock in the days of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of famous memory, and has flouriſh'd therein ever ſince (a late Chaſme excepted) with this Immortal Glory; that whereas other Churches have generally occaſioned fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent diſturbances to the Countries where they have been nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, and ſome bloody and dreadfull: this (ſeeming to have the peculiar mark of being Gods own) has never yet been the cauſe of any the leaſt diſquietneſs to us, ſince the very firſt Reformation, and at this hour, none appear to be proceeding from it, much leſs impending.</p>
            <p>If the Prince ought to have a conſiderable power to compel and perſwade the Subjects, it follows then that they ought to have but little to reſiſt him in the one or other, let the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be never ſo gawdy.</p>
            <p>Further, the Laws muſt have a time wherein to be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and we ſee, after many Ages, ſome are wanting ſtill; ſo then a queſtion may ariſe, by what Rule a Prince is to Govern when there is a deficiency; we ſay by the Law of Conſcience and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98589:15"/> Reaſon, and neceſſarily it muſt be left to the declarations of his own boſome, in caſes that require expedition, and thus it is in <hi>England;</hi> for Equity in it ſelf, is the Law of God agreeing to reaſon, and that which is in practice, is Gods, interpreted from the Princes breaſt, or from ſuch whom he does intruſt with his Conſcience: ſo our bills in Chancery do conclude that they pray Equitie, becauſe the Law has not provided an apt remedy, or to that purpoſe; and upon the ſame reaſon, the King in ſome caſes ſuſpends the Law it ſelf, as in Frauds, and Paenal Bonds, and Eſtates upon Condition forſeited, becauſe the Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> at preſent made, is herein defective, and comes not up fully to the Law of God; and in all caſes of evil, it is ſaid the King cannot licenſe <hi>malum in ſe,</hi> but he may <hi>malum prohibitum,</hi> though he can pardon either committed.</p>
            <p>Again, the firſt poſſeſſion of a man, is a good Title by the Law of Nature, until an elder, or the Law of Reaſon (which with mankind is to have a preference) otherwayes diſpoſes it, as is done in Taxes, and ſeveral other things; and all this, with much more, which for brevities ſake I purpoſely omit, is either founded on the Law of Nature or Reaſon, as is ſaid in our books of Law the Law of <hi>England</hi> is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus much of the Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>7. COme we now to the number of men requiſite in a happy Commonwealth. It is neceſſary they ſhould be many, and cannot be too great, if the proportion of proviſions be not too little; for though few men, well governed with neceſſaries convenient, may do, and heretofore have acted miraculous things; yet a greater number equally diſciplin'd, and of like proviſion, ſhall do more conſiderable and wonderfull things in tract of time: perhaps upon a contingent accident not well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood from whence it came; Fortune may now and then put an Argument to the contrary.</p>
            <p>To come to ſome Inſtances, which may ſerve as Arguments; <hi>Xenephon</hi> with a few men made a Retreat that has been of great glory to him through all times, even to this day, paſſing many vaſt Countries againſt a prodigious number of men; but then there was this in it. Firſt his Souldiers were provided with good Pikes, a ſort of Arms of the beſt uſe againſt Horſe in a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion Country, of which the Enemy conſiſted chiefly, and in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98589:15"/> encloſures they could do no conſiderable harm to Foot, which was an accident of Fortune. Then the General of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> in expectation of out-witting them by political contrivances, trifled out the time of burning the Country in their march, till they were ſo near the Confines, that they had ſufficient main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance for retreat out of their Dominions; after which they met with no conſiderable Nations, and for the moſt part, if not alwayes, with tumultuary forces, theſe being generally ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caeſar</hi> with ſmall forces, being well diſciplined and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, deſtroyed a great number of <hi>Helvetians</hi> in his Wars of <hi>Gallia,</hi> who had no good Diſcipline or Armes; but when he came to meet a greater number than his own forces, at leaſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually furniſh'd with neceſſaries, and almoſt as good Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin'd, he ſuſtain'd the loſs at <hi>Dyrrachuum,</hi> where if it had been well followed, a period had been ſet to his glories. But in the end, he overcame <hi>Pompey</hi> by the advantage of his cunning, in mixing certain cohorts of Foot with his Horſe, and then meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the confident precipitancy of the ungovernable Nobility of <hi>Rome,</hi> againſt whom he fought. <hi>Caeſar</hi> in <hi>Spain</hi> after, meeting with many Romanes of Diſcipline and Proviſion ſomewhat like his own Army, under <hi>Pompey</hi>'s Sons, he profeſſed he then fought for his life, whereas heretofore he had contended for honour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bajazett</hi> the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperour, with a great Army, excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Diſcipline, and well provided, made conſiderable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts; but when <hi>Tamberlaine</hi> with an Army greater, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and neceſſaries at leaſt equal, he was not long before he did encage him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scanderbegge</hi> did ſingular exploits with a few choice men; but it is obſervable he found the inconvenience of a ſmall Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as <hi>Epirus</hi> was, and in the cloze of his years, made it his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal care to fortifie himſelf with alliances, by way of Supply to that deficiency.</p>
            <p>We muſt not deny, that where the numbers are great, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good Diſcipline and ſtores, it breeds confuſion, and haſtens deſtruction: as on the other hand, an Army or Countrie never did exceed in number ſuch a proportion as was beyond the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of good Diſcipline; many great Monarchies of the World, and the March of <hi>Tamberlaine</hi> in exact order, are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt examples and arguments.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:98589:16"/>
            <p>8. PRoviſions are the next thing neceſſary to make a flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nation; they are ſuch as theſe, plenty of Fleſh, and Corn, Iron, Braſs, Wood for Fuel, Ship-ſides and Maſts, Hemp, Pitch, Tarr, the materials of Powder; if they are not all produceable from the ground, that they be not farr off, and that there be conveniency of Carriage for them, the chief where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is Water. Hence it is, that all great Governments have had their Capital Seats in Plentifull Countries which are well ſtored with convenient Proviſions, and for what they want, have the benefit of water for quick and eaſie Carriage.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romans</hi> were ſeated on a rich Soyle, and not far from the Mediterranean, and the Neighbouring Seas, places of the moſt convenient Navigation in this part of the World, at thoſe times, in reſpect of the extent thereof and quietneſs, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners Compaſs not being then invented. The <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Empire upon the ſame; the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> at this day, before them the <hi>Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> and <hi>Carthaginian,</hi> and few, if any, great Towns of note, are not upon or near good Rivers, or the Sea it ſelf. It is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, the ground the <hi>Romans</hi> conquered, was chiefly upon the skirts of thoſe Seas through which they could the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſly ſend and receive ſupplyes, and the Emperours were forc'd to withdraw firſt from the places moſt remote from the Seas.</p>
            <p>Since the invention of the Mariners Needle, there are other more commodious for Navigation, and a more proper ſeat than that is where the Winds and Tides are more ſtirring, ſince Seamen by the benefit of the Compaſs, can guide themſelves in the day without the ſight of the Sun or Land-marks, and in the Night without benefit of Stars or Fire, unleſs at ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial places and times.</p>
            <p>9. IF the People have a good government, are many in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and well provided; yet (eſpecially till there are good conſtitutions of Laws) if there be not a good election a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Officers, thoſe advantages for ſuch time will be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the leſs ſignificant.</p>
            <p>We ſhall find the ſame Nation ſometime victorious, and the World trembling under them; and one would think at firſt ſight it proceeded from the nature of the people, and in the turn of a hand, upon the alteration of a Prince, or his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98589:16"/> grow degenerate and effeminate, the Government, Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Stores ſtill the ſame, and <hi>e converſo,</hi> a ſluggiſh People, after a time victorious. Now ſeeing Princes act chiefly by their Miniſters and Officers, and that they have to do generally with all their Neighbours, for otherwiſe it might ariſe from the condition of ſome without, it cannot ariſe from any other more conſiderable cauſe, than the want of good choice. In the one, Men of Vertue appear uppermoſt, who give an univerſal reputation to their Country: in the other, theſe by degrees are thruſt down, and ſuch ſhew themſelves, who in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of buſineſs, bring an ignominious report upon the whole Nation. <hi>Edward</hi> the third, in his firſt time, and <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth of <hi>England,</hi> in his laſt, opur Chronicles make honourable mention of, with great admiration of their Valour and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts in <hi>France,</hi> and our happineſs then at home; and with as great ſorrow and reflections on their other times, and on both their Succeſſors.</p>
            <p>But if men of virtue are choſen, who are the ſpirit and life of a Commonwealth, yet we ſee Fortune now and then will be ſhewing her ſelf; but not oft, and ſo we may the better bear her inſolencies. But againſt the apprehenſions of men, God Almighty will, and does thoſe things oft times by his extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary providence, that ſeem to differ not only from the courſe of nature, but of reaſon; who of his mercy by devout applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, may, notwithſtanding be appeaſed.</p>
            <p>10. AT this day, in this part of the World, it may be there is not any Nation ſo near compleat, in many of the former particulars, as this of <hi>England.</hi> If we compare it with the Low Countries, the Crown of <hi>England</hi> has more Men, more Proviſions of ſome ſort of its Native production, and may have as many of any other; better ſeated, the Country of a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger extent; add to this, that here cannot eaſily be diverſions by a Land Invaſion.</p>
            <p>As to their Government, ſithence it has much of a repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, were it not that they fix their thoughts without upon fear of danger, the caement of republiques, it is likely they would divide, and ſettle on one another the uſual fate of ſuch governments, as it fell out to <hi>Rome,</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Scylla, Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Caeſar, &amp;c.</hi> for having overcome a great part of the World,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98589:17"/> and amongſt the reſt the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> a powerfull Neighbour, they fell to Civil Wars, as was foretold by a Senatour, and thereupon were adviſed not utterly to deſtroy, but to leave that Government as an awe upon their State, to prevent diviſions at home. War abroad, is the Intereſt of Republiques; the Low Countries, to the wonder of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes, thriving like Salamanders in the fire of contention.</p>
            <p>If we compare the King of <hi>England</hi> with the French, it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious; they have neither ſo convenient Ports, nor are ſo well ſeated, we lying betwixt them and the North, where the greateſt ſtores are for Naval employments; adde to this, that the form of their government and nature of the people indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes them to buſineſs on the Seas; Take this out of Sir <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Rawleigh,</hi> as <hi>Popaelynire</hi> well obſerveth: <hi>The Forces of Princes by Sea are marks of the greatneſs of an Eſtate; for whoſoever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the Sea, commands the Trade; whoſoever commands the Trade of the World, commands the Riches of the World, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the World it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If with any other, this being an Iſland in the midſt of Trade, betwixt the North and South, Eaſt and Weſt, a temperate Clime upon the great waters of the World; eſpecially ſince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief may be received and ſent with more certainty upon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the Needle, has manifeſt advantage.</p>
            <p>Some men in certain Nations it muſt be confeſſed, out of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, have in certain times abuſed the publique Revenue, as did the Officers of the Greek Emperour <hi>Constantine,</hi> when <hi>Mahomet</hi> beſieged <hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> Others out of envy to the glory of great and virtuous Commanders, have puzzled buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and obſtructed neceſſaries: as <hi>Hanno</hi> did to <hi>Hannibal</hi> in the courſe of his Victories againſt the Romans in <hi>Italy:</hi> Others have been traiterous, as was <hi>Beſſus</hi> to <hi>Darius</hi> his Maſter, in the time that <hi>Alexander</hi> invaded him. And it did fall out to that <hi>Hanno,</hi> the Ball was after toſs'd upon <hi>African</hi> ground, and conſumed the envious obſtructer, his Family and Country: to the Emperour, who having try'd, below his Imperial Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to ask money at the Doors of his Citizens, for the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary defence of him and them, through a perverſe and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate diſcontent at the former abuſes, though they had plenty within them, that he was refuſed, and ſo they periſhed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And to <hi>Beſſus,</hi> who depending on dealing with <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:98589:17"/> upon the ruine of his Prince, of whom he had the greateſt apprehenſions, did periſh in the deſign: And ſome heretofore out of arrogance and want of skill, have endangered their Country:</p>
            <p>But we muſt take great heed we be not too apt to think a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs of the actions of a Prince or his Officers, which Men are too prone to complain of: Firſt becauſe we cannot judge aright of them, ſithence they are at diſtance to moſt, and ſecret to all; the hearts of Kings are unſearchable. Secondly, We know not what they drive at, for they rowe one way oft times and look another, intending ſtill the publique good: Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they are but men, and may have their failings; and we ought to cover, and not divulge, much leſs expatiate on their Infirmities, as we would not men ſhould do ſo to us. They have their hands full of buſineſs, ſo that it is almoſt impoſſible but that deficiencies muſt be: Adde to this, that male contents do always magnifie the overſights of men in authority, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie their good deeds beyond a due proportion, and by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports they ſpread up and down, do give a diſcolouring to their actions: So that for this very reaſon we muſt always allow many grains; and if it were as bad as it may be ſometimes made, which without all diſpute it is not, as all men have their failings, ſo have they oft their poculiar periods wherein they commit them, ſometimes gaining ground by ſuch ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and make the more wary men, upon the benefit of their experience.</p>
            <p>11. THe gradations, means and manner how the Engliſh Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on came to ſuch a greatneſs, is the ſubject of the Hiſtory of <hi>England,</hi> of which the following Book is the firſt part, and this the Sum.</p>
            <p>At the diſcovery hereof by <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> it was divided into a multitude of petty governments, exceeding weak for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and more liable to the Roman Conqueſts.</p>
            <p>Under them it continued ſome hundreds of years, in that time deſigned in the nature of a Treaſury, out of which they might draw men and wealth for the purpoſes of the Roman intereſts.</p>
            <p>On their Exigencies in the Continent they left it weak, and ſubject to all Invaders, being diſabled by the policies and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98589:18"/> of their late Maſters; for what they had moſt apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of, they did moſt carefully endeavour to extinguiſh, which was the power and ſtrength of them, whom having ſubdued they had deſire to keep under.</p>
            <p>In this condition habituated alſo for ſeveral Ages to a Slav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh temper of mind, they were the more eaſily conquered by the <hi>Saxons,</hi> invited in to aſſiſt them upon the freſh affliction of their Northern Neighbours. Under them it continued a conſiderable time, divided into ſeven Nations, commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Saxon</hi> Heptarchy, being then in ſomewhat better plight to defend themſelves than formerly, becauſe they were redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to a fewer number of principalities, and were in no ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the <hi>Daniſh</hi> inroads and the conſequence thereof for ſome too conſiderable time excepted.</p>
            <p>After divers contentions, and great fluctuations, it all reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at laſt into one Monarchy, under a <hi>Weſt Saxon</hi> Prince, and then far more conſiderable. While it remained thus, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſereral of the Nobility, who had large poſſeſſions here, from the <hi>Roman</hi> policy, in granting large im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities to ſome who yeilded to them in their Conqueſts; &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently great intereſt did frequently perplex the Nation, with civil diffention, and by that very means principally it became a prey to the <hi>Norman</hi> Conquerour.</p>
            <p>The ſame cauſes remaining, the effects did not differ under the ſucceeding Kings; in ſomuch that thoſe victorious Attempts and Conqueſts that were made in ſeveral places, eſpecially in <hi>France,</hi> were frequently diſtracted, and at laſt utterly extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht by our contentions at home.</p>
            <p>In the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> The policy upon which great men kept and increaſed their eſtates beyond a moderate and competent bulk, by advantage of a Statute they had gained in the days of <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt, impowring them to Entayle all was fruſtrated by an invention at Law, which could not be effected before upon divers deſigns in Parliament; the iſſue of this was a bane to great poſſeſſions, and conſequently to ſuch powers and intereſts as did frequently mate the Kings, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the people of <hi>England,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>7th.</hi> followed the blow, acting ſeveral things le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled to the ſame purpoſe, and with benefit to them that in thoſe days did not generally think ſo, for by this means they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98589:18"/> were taken off from inclinations to a common miſchief, to which they were provok'd by their paſſions, and the urgings of vain and neceſſitous men, and in the calamity whereof they themſelves and their Families had the moſt deplorable ſhares.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> together with the Doctrine of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, had impreſs'd in the minds of men an opinion, that what is once given to the Church is Sacrilege to take away; by which means (it likewiſe having divers other arts to increaſe) they kept their eſtates, and became very formidable to the Kings of <hi>England;</hi> but being undertook by <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> he tore from them, with great ſeverity, thoſe large poſſeſſions which rendred them dangerous to his intereſts.</p>
            <p>Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his Daughter, by a long and prudent reign, did fix her ſelf, and marvellouſly improve the Intereſt of this Nation, wrapt up inſeparably with the trueſt of the Crown, And now did begin to appear the fruits of the Mariners Compaſs, not long before invented, the Trade and ſhiping of the world leaving the calmer, and and ſetling in our more active Seas. In her Reign the Nation was very potent, as may be obſerved by the notable enemies it withſtood, when the Princes round us were generall in deſign of our ruine, and yet with eternal honour were they all reſiſted, and ſome notably ſhattered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scotland</hi> was ſtill out, and capable of being a miſchievous diverſion on all occaſions, which immediately upon the Queens death was united in King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now one would have thought the Crown had been out of all danger at home, when on a ſudden did appear an intereſt in <hi>Scotland,</hi> which had its beginning in the Queens dayes, that by the neglect and abſence of King <hi>James,</hi> working it ſelf into the preſence of powerful Noblemen there, and after into the hearts of certain <hi>Engliſh</hi> here, from a cloud no bigger in ſhew than a mans hand, became in the dayes of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, a moſt good and pious Prince, the greateſt ſtorm, and of more terror than of many Ages had befallen, but is now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipated. And the Kingdom till of late by the abſence of the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Prince, was in perpetual danger of diviſion and confuſion; when it pleaſed God, at the point of deſpair, by the hand of the then General <hi>Moncke,</hi> and now Duke of <hi>Albemarle,</hi> a renowned and admirable Commander, to reſtore us one of excellent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98589:19"/> our undoubted Prince, all his enemies being bound hand and foot, and proſtrate before him, and to ſtabliſh him on the Throne of his Anceſtors, in a far more conſiderable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate than any of his Predeceſſors; this Parliament, to their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal honour, having repaired thoſe fortifications of a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, which ſome Princes heretofore in ſeveral Ages had ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to decay, the antient fundamental maxime, That the Crown-Lands could not be alienated, being evaded, and thoſe not now capable of being reſtored <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> without manifeſt and extraordinary injuſtice and danger.</p>
            <p>So that if one look upon this Kingdom, as once <hi>Florus</hi> did that of <hi>Rome,</hi> in a compariſon to the life of Man, we may up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the proſpect ſee it after many viciſſitudes and Ages, from a leſſer to a more ſignificant ſtature, to have at laſt come to a compleat ſtrength and vigour, ſuch as the laſt and this Summer, under the auſpicious Dominion of his Imperial Majeſty, ſingly of his own force, to a chaſe of their enemies the <hi>Dutch,</hi> after ſhort diſputes upon other equal tearms, notwithſtanding the aſſiſtance from <hi>France,</hi> and alliance with the <hi>Dane;</hi> a manifeſt argument of the apprehenſion of their own weaknes, compared with the ſtrength of his Majeſty; for I take the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacies which have been many, to import amongſt other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the opinion the world has of his power, ſeeing experience tells us, the weaker Princes and States unite againſt the potent. It is remarkable, that this laſt Victory was at a time the Engliſh were thought to be very low, the Peſtilence having ſwept away many, and a general decay of Trade, with ſome other conſiderations of uncomfortable memory, as if God Almighty would ſhew us what great bleſſings he has beſtowed on us, in enabling our Soveraign to deal with the United ſtrength of his Neighbours in a diſtracted condition; to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent we might have no reaſon to ſuſpect or fear when our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes are blooming.</p>
            <p>I Have forborn to fill up this Praefatory diſcourſe with the commendations of Hiſtory in generall, though much might be reported on the ſingular advantages which ariſe therefrom, to a Judicious Reader, eſpecially if it be of a Country where his concernments are great, and principally to perſons of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique buſineſs; much leſs need it be done in an Age, and among
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98589:19"/> people well acquainted with good Learning, and their true va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luations in divers particulars.</p>
            <p>Nor ſhall I blame the compilements of that concerning <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> though ſome of notable Judgement, and full Learning, have heretofore led the way; becauſe I would not ſeem to arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate that to my ſelf, which on my vaineſt thoughts, and beſt ſucceſſes, I think manifeſtly amiſs. But what I preſume to ſay, will be this, that if in the concernments of any mans affairs, any thing of notice in this part of the Story of <hi>England,</hi> a place of conſiderable regard, may have ſlipt either obſervation or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, being broken in time, and withall voluminous, and may be found more conciſely here, it is with good devotion offered; but principally to thoſe of the Engliſh Nation whom it more peculiarly concerns.</p>
            <p>But whether or no, and how farr my labours of this kind will become any improvement to the Intereſt of his Majeſty, the Royal Family, or the People ſubject to his Authority, whoſe direct Intereſts are inſeperably entwin'd and at all which I make my moſt ſpecial aime, muſt be recommended to the judgement and experience of the preſent and ſucceeding times, if they may be worthy to out-live a few dayes. However in this I ſet up my content, that my meaning is not amiſs; nor am I aware I have either fallen upon the extreams of ſervile flattery, or an unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming medling, where it ought not to be; and I hope in this part to give a reaſon of our Religion and Laws, will be farr from offending the true lovers of the Church and their Country.</p>
            <p>True it is, that he which takes upon him to diſcourſe of Vice and Virtue, with endeavours to ſuppreſs the firſt, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the other; it will not be, but that certain out of infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon general diſcourſes, will be jealous they themſelves are particularly pointed at, when the Vices they are ſubject to are only intended: nor am I deceived if ſome ſuch perſons be found to make reflections, or have an evil eye, ſithence it is no more than common expectation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98589:20"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98589:20"/>
            <head>THE FIRST PART OF THE HISTORY OF England.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat every Country had a time wherein it was firſt Planted, beſides what may be collected by Reaſon, ſeems true by Hiſtorical Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation alſo. A frequent increaſe there is of new Inventions, and ſuch as are of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable uſe, and extraordinary conſequence. <hi>The Marriners Compaſs</hi> grounded on the Magnetick virtue, is one, from which have proceeded more Alterations than can (without long time) be thought on, in Religion, Navigation, Diſeaſes, and other weighty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations: by the benefit thereof no leſs than a new World diſcovered in the conſequence, whereof has fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed a little World of new things. <hi>Gun-Powder</hi> is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98589:21"/> worthy of Notice, and has greatly altered the way of Military affairs; <hi>Printing</hi> might be added, and many more. And from theſe things I would inferre, that if Inventions (which more properly, for the moſt part, ought to have the name of Chances) are new every Age, and ſome of ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable uſe, that they are not like to be antiquated; it may ſeem, if the World had been <hi>ab aeterno,</hi> they would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have been found out long before now. If it be objected that ſeveral Arts are worn out of uſe; it may be anſwered, That he which ſhall read <hi>Pancirollus,</hi> a diligent enquirer into things of this nature, may obſerve that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably thoſe which are thought to be loſt, are either of fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous value, or it is uncertain whether they are not ſtill in being, under other Names, or ſomewhat varyed only, and at the moſt but worn out by more excellent Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: an Argument of it ſelf to the ſame purpoſe. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is, That Countries (eſpecially in this conſiderable part of the World) have Originals of their Hiſtory, and thoſe not farre diſtant in their time from one another. I am not ignorant what Stories are in ſome other parts of <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles,</hi> containing a ſtrange number of thouſands of years; but I can finde no reaſon why they ſhould be thought capable of continuing the Memory of things longer there than we here. It may be they have reckoned by <hi>Lunar</hi> years, perhaps out of affectation or miſtake they did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord erroneouſly, and it is not unlikely this very ſtory is fabulous, as to the extent they ſpeak of, though the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of a longer time may be truly more with them in ſome particulars than us. And till <hi>Aristotle,</hi> when the Creation was ſomewhat ſlipt out of memory, and traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on antiquated, the Philoſophers of the World have been ſaid to have held generally a beginning of it. I could enlarge upon this, but what is ſaid may ſuffice, hapily, to the intent, we might be induc'd to believe that every Country had a time when a People were firſt planted in it; But a Man may ſay of them, as is uſually ſpoken of ſome great Rivers, it is difficult to go up to their Spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, and more eſpecially of the <hi>Britains,</hi> who truſted too much to their memories in their firſt known Age to the <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98589:21"/>
               <head>Of the firſt Planters in Britany.</head>
               <p>THe Opinions of Learned Men concerning the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> extraction, are various; It may not be improbable that the <hi>Grecians,</hi> or a <hi>Greek</hi> Colony, or ſome Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours who ſpake the <hi>Greek</hi> Language, or a Dialect thereof, firſt Peopled this Country, for theſe Reaſons. It muſt be planted (in all likelihood) by Navigators, becauſe it is an Iſland. The <hi>Grecians,</hi> and thoſe who liv'd not far from them, about the firſt known time, were generally account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the beſt ſort. They ſetled divers Colonies on the Sea-ſide, quite through the <hi>Mediterranean;</hi> and paſſing the Streights, might no doubt fixe ſeveral on the Coaſts upon the <hi>Atlantick</hi> Ocea. The <hi>Greek</hi> Language, worn out of vulgar uſe among the People, was preſerved among the <hi>Druids,</hi> their Prieſts, upon the firſt Diſcovery by <hi>Caeſar;</hi> and it is not to be found out how they came by it, unleſs by ſome Plantation among them; no other common inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe having been heard of before. And another pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption is, The continuing of the Language has reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance to the practiſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy, in keeping up the old <hi>Latine</hi> Tongue at this day; amongſt whom are, as with theſe were, ſome intereſts and conſiderations of like nature. The <hi>Britains</hi> fought in Chariots, after the old manner about <hi>Greece,</hi> when they were firſt heard of in the <hi>Roman</hi> Territories, but a peculiar way then of the <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,</hi> except in <hi>Gallia</hi> abutting; which <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries tells as a Novelty, in a particular Deſcription of their way of Fight, to his Country-men. If we come to the firſt Name of the Iſland, we finde it called <hi>Albion,</hi> or <hi>Alebion;</hi> it ſeems to me to denote a derivation from <hi>Lybia,</hi> where <hi>Greek</hi> Colonies had ſet down. If we look upon the Conjectures of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> he declares his Opinion, that there were here in his dayes two ſorts of People, ſome whom he thought might come from <hi>Gallia,</hi> ſeated on thoſe Neighbouring Coaſts, upon ſome Conqueſts made; and a Nation within the Land of a more ancient ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Tacitus</hi> has much the ſame Conjectures, adding this, That he conceiv'd a third ſort came into the North
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98589:22"/> from the <hi>Germans,</hi> and founds his opinion on their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions. This does not diſagree with that of <hi>Cambden,</hi> who would have the <hi>Gauls</hi> to plant it; ſor it is not unlike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſome of them might come over into this Country, and yet another People might be here long before. And though I do not believe the reports of <hi>Brute</hi> in all points, concerning the <hi>Trojans,</hi> whom one may upon the matter call <hi>Grecians,</hi> in reſpect of their Founder, <hi>Dardanus</hi> a <hi>Grecian,</hi> and their near ſcituation to that Country; yet I may reaſonably ſuppoſe, that either it is true, in ſome parts, as the ſtory of King <hi>Arthur</hi> is; but ſo abſurd, by the many additions of fabulous and magnifying Writers, that the certainty thereof, is not only extinguiſh'd, for a great ſhare, but may be hereafter, as this of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> with many learned men, utterly doubted. Or elſe, the Hiſtorian, who firſt brought it to light, finding a great probability, that the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Extraction was chiefly <hi>Greekiſh,</hi> or ſo little diſtant, that it had great Reliſhes thereof; and withal, being taken with the ſame vanity, that ſome Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of thoſe times, and long before, did affect, to derive their Original from a <hi>Trojan</hi>-ſtock, did put this general truth into that particular ſhape, which would not bear the obſervations of learned men. I could add the conſonancy of the <hi>Greek</hi> Language, to the words of vulgar uſe amongſt us at this day, ſeeming to be the Primitives; and ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations on the credible report of an Altar, dedicated to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes,</hi> the famous <hi>Grecian,</hi> as appeared by an Inſcription found in the North, with ſome things more; but this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none of the moſt uſeful parts of an Hiſtory, I will add with <hi>Cambden,</hi> That the <hi>Gauls</hi> might be next in ſome places, and the <hi>Germans,</hi> with <hi>Tacitus,</hi> in others; and ſo paſs on to a Search, where they might firſt land; a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion more hardly to be reſolved, and I doubt, at the beſt, can be but conjectured at.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98589:22"/>
               <head>The Places, in which it may be ſuppoſed the Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters firſt ſate down: And of the Fortunate Iſlands.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am moved to gueſs, that they who were in their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regrination, might on their Landing fix on the Iſle of <hi>Man</hi> or <hi>Angleſey,</hi> or both: for theſe Reaſons. The <hi>Druids</hi> whoſe Name <hi>Druetes,</hi> a <hi>Grecian</hi> original, when this Iſland was firſt diſcovered to the more known parts of the World, were ſeated principally in theſe two, to <hi>Angleſey</hi> firſt, and not toward <hi>Scotland,</hi> a place of more remoteneſs, and probably of more ſecurity (were that the only Reaſon of their moving this way) as ſome have thought) the Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern <hi>Britains</hi> were ſtil made, as they gave way to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, a thing frequent among Colonies, to retire to their Original and Capital Seats, as being generally beſt fenced, and moſt affected; and at this day the <hi>Welſh-men</hi> affirm themſelves derived generally from the ancient <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> Stock. The worthy Biſhop of Saint <hi>Andrews</hi> in his Hiſtory of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> tells us thus of the Iſle of <hi>Man,</hi> and the Northern <hi>Britains</hi> his Country-men.</p>
               <p>Cratilinth <hi>coming to the Crown, in the Year 277, made it one of his firſt Works, to purge the Kingdom of Heathen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Superſtition, and expulſe the</hi> Druids, <hi>a ſort of Prieſts held in thoſe dayes in great reputation. Their manner was to Celebrate Sacrifices, and perform their other Rites in Groves, with Leaves and Branches of Oak; and thence, ſaith</hi> Pliny, <hi>they were called</hi> Druides, <hi>for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the Greek Language doth ſignify an Oak. It is likewiſe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified of them; that they were well learned in all natural Philoſophy, Men of moral Converſation; and for Religion not ſo groſly ignorant and ſuperſtitions, as other Heathen Prieſts: for they taught, There was one only God, and that it was not lawful to preſent Him in an Image. I ſuppoſe this muſt be meant of a ſupream God, for they held that the Souls of Men did not periſh with the Bodies; and that, after death, Men were rewarded according to the life they led on Earth. They lived likewiſe in great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect with all ſorts of People, and ruled their affairs very</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98589:23"/> 
                  <hi>politickly; for being governed by a Preſident, who kept his Reſidence in the Iſle of</hi> Man <hi>(which then was under the Dominion of the</hi> Scots) <hi>they did once every Year meet in that Place, to take Counſel together, for the Ordering of Affairs: and carried matters with ſuch Diſcretion, that</hi> Cratilinth <hi>found it difficult enough to expulſe them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the favour they had among the People. In this Iſle King</hi> Cratilinth <hi>(after their Expulſion) Erected a ſtately Church to the Honour of our Saviour, which he adorned with all neceſſary Ornaments, and called</hi> Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuſe fanum, <hi>that is, the Temple of our Saviour; hence it is that the Biſhops of the Iſles are ſtiled</hi> Sodoreuſes Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi: <hi>for ſo long as that Iſle remained in the Poſſeſſion of the</hi> Scots, <hi>the Biſhops of Iſles made that Church their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that I conclude, The <hi>Druids,</hi> who had ſuperintendency over the Southern <hi>Britains,</hi> reſided metropolitically in <hi>Angleſey;</hi> and in the Iſle of <hi>Man,</hi> thoſe who governed <hi>Scotland,</hi> upon ſome Diviſion at firſt; or elſe (upon the blow given thoſe by the <hi>Romans,</hi> and their Juriſdiction confin'd to the North) they removed their Seat to the Iſle of <hi>Man,</hi> one of the Places of their Original receipt being not Conquered. <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſpeaking of two kinds of People, here in the Southern Parts, to him only Diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, declares the more Novel to have liv'd neer the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Coaſts, and the more ancient upon the Weſtern: <hi>Tacitus</hi> to whom was more known of the North, and would have a third ſort Landed from the the <hi>Germans,</hi> as was ſaid before, did in the two firſt much agree with <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and among his Conjectures, ſuppoſes that by the more ſwarthy Complexions of the <hi>Silures,</hi> and their Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Hairs, ſome might come thither from <hi>Spain.</hi> There is to this day in thoſe Parts a Tradition, <hi>Mon mam Cumri,</hi> Man is the Mother of the <hi>Cumeri</hi> or <hi>Welſhmen:</hi> this is interpreted by them, who perhaps never thought of any other Reaſon, to the plenty of Corn or other Proviſions in the Iſland of <hi>Angleſey,</hi> in reſpect of other Parts of their Country, but thoſe that are acquainted with it, and the reſt alſo know, the aſſiſtance that comes to this purpoſe is not of ſo conſiderable notice. Now it is of frequent
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98589:23"/> Obſervation that the <hi>Cumeri</hi> were the moſt ancient Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern People, that Inhabited about <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Gallia.</hi> The two fortunate Iſlands ſo much talkt of, and celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ancient Poets, have been for many Ages laſt paſt, utterly loſt, and not to be diſcovered. Among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuppoſals, let us add ſome. They were two, and ſo are theſe of the Mans: they went both by one general Name, ſo did theſe; the one was called the bigger, the other the leſſer <hi>Mona;</hi> one the neerer, the other the more remote. The ancient Philoſophers and Poets were great Celebraters of viertue, and thereupon for encouragement to Men, did affirm there was a Place of Pleaſure or Reſt, whereto after life they were carried, who had lived Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly, and that Place was ſometimes called the <hi>Elizian-</hi>Fields, as at other the Fortunate Iſlands; they did further fancy, that though there were other delights, yet above all the pleaſure of converſe with the juſt, and a relaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from care, was moſt valuable. They might therefore conceit the better of theſe Iſlands above other Places, becauſe of the ſtrict life of the <hi>Druids,</hi> a Religious Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple here dwelling, ſequeſtred from the Cares of the World, and doubtleſs of a great Name for Virtue, at their firſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down, eſpecially (for beſides what was obſerved by the biſhop) <hi>Caeſar</hi> tells us, they became Judges of all Controverſies in <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Gallia,</hi> over which at laſt their Juriſdiction did extend. Their Name imports a Solitary Place, as Monaſtical among the Religious has the like ſignification from the <hi>Greek</hi> Language. The two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Iſlands were, in the Judgment of the beſt Writers, generally, by the Report of a noted <note n="‖" place="margin">N. C.</note> Mythologiſt, ſeated upon the Weſtern Coaſt of <hi>Britain:</hi> they were in the <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantick</hi> Ocean by common conſent, and theſe are there alſo; for in ancient time that Tract of Sea lying beyond the Coaſt of <hi>Africa</hi> and <hi>Europe</hi> to the Weſt, was called from the Mountain <hi>Atlas,</hi> (probably enough) the <hi>Atlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> Seas, the <hi>Streights,</hi> thereby being the out-let only to the <hi>Grecian</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Countreys, who ſucceſſibely Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it over this part of the World. The <hi>Elizian</hi>-Fields or Fortunate Iſlands, were ſaid to be full of Shades: the <hi>Druids</hi> here nouriſhed many Woods, to perform their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98589:24"/> Superſtitious Rites in. <hi>Angleſey</hi> was called <hi>Ynis Dowill,</hi> a dark or ſhadowy Iſland, from the Wood there growing. The <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> Poets anciently reckoned, the North their right hand, and the South their left, from their way of looking to the Weſt, toward the <hi>Elyzian</hi> Field. More might be ſaid to this intent, which I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely omit: I will add in the cloſe, the Opinion of ſome few of Note. <hi>Homer</hi> thought they were on the Coaſts of <hi>Britain. Iſacius Tzetzes,</hi> a Greek Author of account in <hi>Cambden</hi>'s opinion, reports they were with the <hi>Britains.</hi> And the Story of <hi>Plutarch,</hi> in the Life of <hi>Sertorius</hi> I will repeat; which me-thinks is not diſtant to what we are ſpeaking of. <hi>Sertorius,</hi> upon his retreat out of <hi>Spain,</hi> was forc'd to take the Sea, and being there in little quiet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, not allow'd to land peaceably on the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> or <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> Coaſts, (being then in the Mediterranean;) at laſt he paſſeth the <hi>Streights</hi> of <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> turning on the right hand toward the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Shore again, whereto came di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Sailers from the Fortunate Iſlands, ſeated not farre one from another, about 10000 Furlongs from the Coaſt of <hi>Africa. Sertorius</hi> hearing hereof, was ſo taken with a Reſolution of going to live there, retired from the Care of the Warres, that, had not the Pirates of <hi>Gilicia</hi> forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken him, upon hearing theſe his Determinations, it is likely he had attempted to go. The Iſlands of the <hi>Moni</hi> are much about the ſame diſtance. But if theſe be not they, I will give over my enquiry with <hi>Heylin;</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſearcht diligently for them, in all remarkable places of the World, ſeems at laſt to leave his hopes in the plain Field, as out of Expectation to finde out where they are: for I think not of any ſuch probable two, on our Coaſts, where it was in ancient time ſtrongly reported they were.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98589:24"/>
               <head>Of the Government, Laws and Cuſtomes of the Britains.</head>
               <p>SOmewhat ſhall be ſaid of the Government, Laws, and Cuſtomes of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> People. It is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, they had a double ſubjection: the one to the <hi>Druids,</hi> their Prieſts, which was Univerſal over the whole Iſland, and a great part of <hi>Gallia;</hi> the other to the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, which was divided into many Nations; in <hi>Kent</hi> alone, being four petty Kingdomes: ſo that we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, thoſe had the greateſt Power and Intereſt. The <hi>Druids</hi> of the South, had each over them a Primate, as alſo thoſe of the North; if they had not all one at firſt, they were choſen by Election, and ſometimes divers would ſtand in Competition for the Place, and Warres would thereon enſue. Their Conſtitution, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſayes, was reported to have had its Original in <hi>Britain,</hi> and not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, as we mentioned before in the Iſles of <hi>Man,</hi> their ancient Seats. They had in the greateſt eſteem the god <hi>Mercury,</hi> and much for this Reaſon, becauſe he was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to have had the care of Travellers, another Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Peregrination. After him, they had in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence the other gods, with the ſame conceits of their Power, as had the <hi>Grecian</hi> Nation. They wrote in <hi>Greek</hi> Characters, and in the <hi>Grecian</hi> Language; but their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting was not much: for as to their Doctrine, they taught the myſteries thereof to their own Order only, and never committed it to any other Record, than that of their own memories. The People, which we call the Laity, had general Notions taught them, of what they were to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve: Such as were of moſt conſiderable note were theſe, That the Souls of Men are immortal, and that rewards and puniſhments attend them after Death, according as they obſerv'd the <hi>Druids,</hi> in their Tenents, concerning Religion and Virtue. Sacrifices they had frequently, the common great advantages of the ancient Prieſts, and to cover the Art from firſt ſight, it is not unlikely they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore taught alſo, that the Sacrifice of Men was pleaſing to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98589:25"/> the gods: for ſeeing no other benefit might probably ariſe thereby to themſelves, they might ſeem to intimate, the gods were well pleaſed with the very ſmell of an Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and thereupon they did offer promiſcuouſly, Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Malefactors, and innocent Natives, whereby they had advantage over the People alſo, by a Power to determine who were the moſt fitting for ſuch a purpoſe, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently an Univerſal awe over them. They made eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial uſe of <hi>Miſſeltoe</hi> chiefly, that growing on an Oak, in their ſuperſtition cutting it down, with a Golden Bill, in very devout manner. They had in great uſe the Art. Magick, a peculiar attendant on the Doctrine of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. A Hare, Hen, and Gooſe, they forbad to eat, though for pleaſure they had many. The common People were kept in ignorance, which might ſerve to them as a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Devotion. The <hi>Druids</hi> were exempt from Taxes and the Warres, by which immunities, and other advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, many did covet to be of their Order. It is thought that the Chriſtian Religion, when firſt brought hither, was the eaſilier admitted, upon the apparent congruity to ſome of their Principles. They did excommunicate Offenders much in the ſame manner as it is done with us, excluding them the benefit of Law, all Men ſhunning their Society, and they had ſeveral other ways to puniſh Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of their Religion, and conſiderable rewards to the obedient. The Laity being divided into a great number of petty Governments, had thereupon, doubtleſs, various Laws and Cuſtomes, whereof we will mention a few, but cannot ſort them to the particular Nations. Some of their Money was in Braſs, other in Iron-Rings; one eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial ſort, had the Figure of a Shield emboſs't, and on that ſide a certain Image, the Device was within. It is ſaid, that in no other part of the World, but in ſome places belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Greece,</hi> this laſt ſort of Coin was uſed, another Argument of their <hi>Greekiſh</hi> extraction. For Warre they had Chariots, or Wagons, or both; armed ſome with Iron, in the faſhion of Sithes at the Axle-Tree, to do the more miſchief in their motion. In ſome places the principal Perſon guided the Horſe, in others they had a Chariot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier. In this laſt faſhion the Perſon of Condition would
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98589:25"/> alight as he ſaw occaſion, and fight on foot, retiring to the Chariot when he thought convenient. They were made of that faſhion, and the Horſes ſo train'd, that they would run very ſpeedily, ſtay, and turn dextrouſly, even upon the declivity of a Hill. Some ſought with ſmall Shields, and ſhort Pikes, with a Bell at the end thereof, to make a noiſe, whereby the Enemy might be daunted. They went for the moſt part naked, having a Sword girt to their Waſts by an Iron Chain, and ſome had Collars with Links of Iron about their Necks for Ornament. They did wear the Hair of their Heads and upper Lips long, and ſhav'd it off in all other parts. Some cover'd that which modeſty does direct us, others not. Their Bodies were painted with the ſhapes of Birds, and Beaſts, &amp;c. They lived upon Fleſh, Milk, and Roots, and ſome Corn; but of this laſt they planted not much. Few Towns there were, and but ill built Houſes: thoſe which they had were in places full of neighbouring Trees, and fenc'd with Wood cut down, and other materials in a groſs manner, wherin they lodg'd Themſelves and their Cattle. Theſe things one would think do denote a barbarous People, and, as ſome have ſaid, an ignorant Nation; and among our Hiſtorians, there are ſuch, who make formal Apologies for it. Though I cannot altogether excuſe it, yet, in my Opinion, ſuch ſeeming Barbariſms were for the moſt part practis'd on choice, and for good Reaſons. For it was with them then, as it is now with others, and like enough, will be always (when the Condition of a Country, is, or ſhall be, as theirs was) in no better nor civiller a plight, as they call it, though it may be ſomewhat various. It is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to, on all hands generally, that at the ſame time the <hi>Druids,</hi> who then ſpread over the whole Nation, were great Philoſophers, learned and civil in their Converſation; and no doubt, divers of the Laity alſo, though not very many, the <hi>Druid</hi>-Intereſt forbidding it. The Country be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divided into many petty Nations, of Conſequence it muſt fall out, that they had frequent Warrs, the Confines being ſmall: then to make common Plantations of Corn, and to expect to have a principal maintenance out of it, unleſs at ſome ſpecial times and places, would, in effect,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98589:26"/> be to ſubdue themſelves, for thereby they would be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the inroads of their Enemies, and, on a deſtruction thereof, to a Famine. As to their going naked, neceſſity compelled many of them, for if they kept many Sheep, out of which Men are uſually cloathed in cold Countrys, eſpecially of our Clime, ſuch kinde of Cattle are neither capable to be ſent readily out of the way from forragers, not protected from Beaſts of Prey, as Wolves, and Foxes in great ſtore, probably among the many Woods then in this Iſland. So then they were driven to live on wild Beaſts, and what might be had from Kine, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural productions of the Earth, which were in leſs degree ſubject to ſuch Inconveniencies, and the Hides were of great advantage for Coverings, and ſeveral other purpoſes. As to their dwelling Places, how vain would it be for any Man to ſpend a conſiderable part of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in building a Houſe, which would be immediatly ſubject to proſtitution, by irruptions of an Enemy, and Wood is ſo far from being an Argument of a barbarous People, in the ſenſe it is uſually receiv'd, that we may more truly ſay, it is a conſiderable and judicious protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for Men and Cattle in a ſmall Territory, a little Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, being apt to be over-run and ſpoyl'd in few days, where all things generally are uncovered, and with ſmall defence: But to come to the Hiſtory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Caeſar'<hi>s Deſign to invade Britany.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lius Caeſar</hi> abounding in the thoughts of Conqueſt and Glory, after he had made conſiderable atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in <hi>Gallia</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> about fifty years before the account uſed in <hi>England,</hi> fifty four ſome have ſaid, takes upon him a reſolution to Invade the <hi>Britains:</hi> moved to it upon expectation of Riches, by the plunder of a large and unexhauſted Country (Money being neceſſary in great Undertakings, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> had then in his mind ſuch as were of no ſmall dimenſion.) The Pearles of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98589:26"/> were in great report in thoſe days amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> whether by miſtake, or that there are none here in the latter Ages, equalling the former, is uncertain. But he gave out, that the <hi>Britains,</hi> in the Warres of <hi>Gallia,</hi> had aſſiſted the <hi>Galls,</hi> and made that the pretence of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion. The notice of <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s intentions, being come to the <hi>Britains,</hi> ſeveral of their States ſent Embaſſadors to him, with tender of ſubmiſſion to the <hi>Roman</hi> Authority, and offer Hoſtages for their ſecurity; to whom <hi>Caeſar</hi> was courteous, commending their reſolutions, and exhorted them to conſtancy therein, but would not deſiſt his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer deſigns, this notwithſtanding, but ſent them away with one <hi>Comius,</hi> whom he had made Prince of the <hi>Atre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batij,</hi> a Perſon of Judgment and Fidelity, with directions to him, to manage an Intereſt amongſt the States of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> according to certain Inſtructions, he had received from <hi>Caeſar.</hi> This did not pleaſe the <hi>Britains:</hi> ſo when they came to Land, it was reſolved to lay him in Irons, and effected accordingly, with an unanimous reſolution, contriving to defend themſelves like Men, againſt the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of thoſe, whoſe greedineſs and ambition, by ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, they could not ſatisfie. <hi>Caeſar</hi> could not get know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to any ſatisfaction, of the People, their ways of Fight, their Laws, Ports or Forces, only ſome ſuperficial Information he had, by certain Merchants; thereupon he ſends <hi>Caius Voluſenus</hi> in a Veſſel, to make ſome diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, who return'd, after five days diſquiſition, and gave <hi>Caeſar</hi> an account of what he had taken notice of; which could not be conſiderable, ſithence he did not dare to land, becauſe of the Enemy on the Coaſt prepared to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him. What with <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Warres on the Continent that Summer, which he had but newly paſs't over, and what with his preparing for an Invaſion by Sea, which muſt the rather ſpend him the more time, becauſe it was out of his cuſtomary way of fighting, it fell out, that he could not be ready to Ship his Men, till neer Winter, for this very reaſon, ſomewhat the more inconvenient to him, becauſe he was to paſs an Army of Southern Men, into a more Northern Climate, as alſo, becauſe of his return by Sea, for ſo he muſt, in reſpect of Winter Proviſion,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98589:27"/> which was not to be had, but in <hi>Gallia;</hi> the Seas being at the following Seaſon, more rough and unconſtant, which an Army is leſs able to endure, becauſe they are in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being diſperſt, the confuſion of many Naval de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of this nature: but notwithſtanding, <hi>Caeſar</hi> truſting to his wonted fortune, was reſolved to undertake it, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfies himſelf, with an apprehenſion, that, if he could but make a diſcovery, it might recompence his journey, by the advantage he might gain in his preparations, for another Summers expedition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His Preparations, Voyage, and Landing.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Galls</hi> and <hi>Germans,</hi> being but newly quieted, and apt on all occaſions, eſpecially the firſt, to expreſs their diſtaſte of that ſubjection, with which, as yet they had not well been acquainted, he thereupon left a great party in <hi>Gallia,</hi> where he had moſt ſuſpition, and in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whither he intended, at his return to arrive, and ſtrongly fortified the Port, called then <hi>Iccius,</hi> not farre from the now <hi>Callis,</hi> if not the ſame, from whence he did intend to ſet ſayl, as he had deſign'd likewiſe to come back to it. Two Legions of Foot, which might each contain about 5000 (for they were ſomewhat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain in their number) he reſolv'd to tranſport, and certain Horſe, which if they were the proportion, that was uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally with two Legions, might be about a 1000. The Foot lay at the Port before mentioned, with whom <hi>Caeſar</hi> was in Perſon, and eighty Ships of burden to carry them over, 18 more he intended for the Horſe, which to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, with that leſſer Fleet, were ſome few Leagues di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and by reaſon of contrary winds, could not come up to him, before he was in his paſſage to the Iſland, with the other part of the Navy. He had alſo with him ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Gallies, as we may call them, or Ships of War, to what number is not known.</p>
               <p>During his expectation of the Horſe, the Wind blowed fair, which opportunity, not willing to loſe, he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98589:27"/> thereupon ſhips his Foot, and weighing Anchor, ſets ſayl ſomewhat paſs't midnight, ſending to the Horſe commands to do the like, and follow, and comes himſelf with the beſt Sailors, within view of the Iſland, ſomewhat before Noon the next Day. The Coaſt where he arrived, was unfit to Land his Men on, the Rocks hanging over the Sea, and conſequently of more advantage to the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, than Aſſaylors, the rather, becauſe the <hi>Britains</hi> might make great uſe of their miſſive Weapons, ſo he caſts An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, and ſtays till the reſt of his Fleet, which ſet ſayl with him, came up, which was two or three hours after Noon; when they were neer, he ſends for his principal Officers aboard him, and acquaints them with what <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſenus</hi> had diſcovered, telling them further his Intentions to try for a more favourable Shoar, and gives them particular Inſtructions what they ſhould do, inculcating to them above all, the neceſſity of being exact in their duties on that unſtable Element of the Sea. The Wind and Tide ſerving Him, he weighs Anchor, and ſets Saile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and within a ſmall time, comes to a place not far diſtant, where was a plain and open Shore, proper to land his Men on, about <hi>Deale</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> as is ſuppoſed by ſeveral Circumſtances.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Britains,</hi> who attended <hi>Caeſar</hi> at his Anchor, obſerving his motion, ſend their Horſe and Chariots, being Lighter of march, before hand, and follow with their Infantry. <hi>Caeſar</hi> had the uſual difficulties to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with at his landing, eſpecially the diſorder of his Men diſperſt in ſeveral Ships, which did draw much Water and ſo of greater inconvenience. At firſt he made his attempt without any curious regard to the manner of doing it, not expecting any conſiderable reſiſtance from naked Men, but not long after finding it otherways, and being of quick apprehenſion, he ordered divers of thoſe Ships, which were not of burden to be manned with miſſive Weapons, and plac'd on the Flanks of the Enemy, others that did draw leſs Water to paſs up and down, and relieve ſuch, as at their Landing were oppreſt; which contrivance was of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent benefit to him.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Britains</hi> on the other ſide, notwithſtanding this,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98589:28"/> maintained the Battail with great courage and reſolution, inſomuch, that the <hi>Romans</hi> began to fail of their uſual forwardneſs. This was obſerved by <hi>Caeſar</hi> Himſelf, who did that day perform all the parts of an able General, making ſingular benefit of his ſmall ſhot, and was taken notice of alſo by many others, and particularly by a <hi>Roman</hi> Enſign, who carried the Eagle of the tenth Legion, he ſeeing the report of their peculiar Fame at ſtake, leaps out of his Ship, with the Eagle in his hand, and firſt praying to the gods, that what he was undertaking, might prove happy to the Legion, calls upon the daunted and lingering Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to follow him, unleſs they did intend to betray their Eagle to the Enemy; for his own part, he was reſolved to do his duty to his Country, and his General. Upon this, the Legion provok'd, upon the apprehenſions of diſhonour in the loſs thereof, began one after another to follow him, and the Fight being again renewed, which was at a ſtay before; when the <hi>Romans</hi> came at laſt to firm ground, it fell out, as might be feared, that the valiant, but unarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Britains,</hi> did retreat: their natural Skins (in a cloſe Fight eſpecially) being an unfitting match to the <hi>Romane,</hi> heavy Corſlets, at ſuch time chiefly, as they were to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter the moſt choice and victorious Souldiers, under the moſt able General, one of them, that ever the World had; I call it rather a Retreat, than Flight, though there were great diſorder in it, becauſe no chace was made, for want of Horſe, who were delay'd in their paſſage, by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral accidents.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Britains crave Peace; but on a Diſaſter to the <hi>Roman</hi> Fleet, take New Councils.</head>
               <p>UPon this apparent Diſcovery of the inequality in the match, betwixt the <hi>Roman,</hi> and <hi>Britain</hi> Arms, and Diſcipline, theſe, with a general conſent, reſolve to make their beſt terms, and ſubmit, and to that purpoſe ſend back <hi>Comius</hi> of <hi>Arras,</hi> before mentioned, with ſome of their own Country, as Embaſſadors, thinking by the one
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98589:28"/> to moderate <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s anger, and by the other, in conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to procure a Peace. At their coming, they excuſe their reſiſting Him, imputing it chiefly to the humour of the multitude; and tender Hoſtages, as a ſecurity of their Obedience for the future. <hi>Caeſar</hi> having firſt expoſtulated with them the breach of their promiſe, not to oppoſe him at his Landing, accepts of their Propoſitions, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, their Forces ſever, many going home, to their own Countries. Purſuant thereunto alſo, ſeveral Hoſtages from the Neighbour States, are brought into the Camp, the reſt being ſomewhat further off daily coming, and others ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, when on a ſudden, an accident fell out, which gave the <hi>Britains</hi> new and hopeful reſolutions.</p>
               <p>As it was obſerved before, the Horſe, by reaſon of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Winds, could not come up to Port <hi>Iccius,</hi> when <hi>Caeſar</hi> looſed Anchor, being ſome miles of, and not uſing a ſpeedy courſe to Embarque, and take opportunity of the ſame Wind, that he did, by delay, the Gale became weaker, and they had ſpent four days, before they were within view of the <hi>Romans</hi> in <hi>Britain,</hi> and then on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den aroſe a violent ſtorm, which diſperſt them; ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forc'd immediatly to return to the <hi>Gallique</hi> Coaſts, others endeavouring to Anchor on the <hi>Brittiſh,</hi> proving very leaky, were compelled to weigh again, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in the Night, for the Shoar, from whence they came; a time very dangerous then, eſpecially for Navigation. It fell out likewiſe, that thoſe Ships which were with <hi>Caeſar,</hi> part whereof were drawn on the Shoar, were extreamly broken with the Tempeſt, and ſome made utterly unſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable. Theſe things were to the <hi>Romans</hi> an occaſion of ſad thoughts, but to the <hi>Britains</hi> of comfortable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation; for it was apprehended on all hands, that if they ſhould Winter in <hi>Gallia,</hi> the Ships were wanting that ſhould tranſport them, and if in <hi>Britain,</hi> the Corn was not to be had, which might ſufficiently maintain them, and the Horſe, which would be very convenient, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt neceſſary, to the providing any conſiderable ſtores, was abſent. To this, the <hi>Britains</hi> had an opinion, that the <hi>Romans</hi> were fewer in number, than in truth they were, collecting it from the ſmallneſs of their Camp,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98589:29"/> which <hi>Caeſar</hi> had contracted, for the eaſe of his Souldiers to leſs then the uſual bounds, becauſe he had not ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Carriages, as Armies, did commonly march with. The <hi>Roman</hi> General on the one hand, having theſe things in his mind, and ſuſpecting what the <hi>Britains</hi> might do up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this grand alteration, eſpecially from the delay, was made, in ſending in the compleat number of Hoſtages, takes great care to provide againſt the danger, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon cauſes Corn to be daily brought in, from the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Fields, where ſome was ſtanding, and ſends for materials out of <hi>Gallia,</hi> to repair his Ships, which (by his great induſtry, and the laborious toile of his Souldiers, he brought to this effect, that all, but twelve, were made able to abide the Sea. On the other hand, the <hi>Britains</hi> reſolve to renew the War upon this accident, but judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly determine not to ſight the <hi>Romans</hi> in a ſet Battail, the experience of which they had had before, but to peece the Foxes Tayle to the Lions Skin, and draw the Warre out till Winter, to diſturb them as they did ſee occaſion, in their forraging, at ſome time or another, hoping to have a favourable opportunity to ruine them, ſuppreſs't they thought almoſt to their hand, by the want of neceſſaries, concluding, that if they could deſtroy theſe, it would be a great diſcouragement to all others, to make any further ſuch attempt upon them for the future: and hereupon they that were in <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Camp of the <hi>Britains,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew themſelves by degrees out of it.</p>
               <p>Not long after, the <hi>Roman</hi> Foot having reapt all the Corn of a Field, (except a ſmall piece, cloſe by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Wood ſides) the <hi>Britains</hi> gueſt they would come to it the next day; Whereupon, in the dead of the night before, they convey a great part of their Forces into the Covert, expecting the Enemy would appear and forrage, which accordingly fell out, as was imagined, for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Legion was ſent to cut it, and carry it away, and when they came; laying down their Arms, fell hard to their Harveſt, ſuſpecting not in the leaſt the Ambuſcado. The <hi>Britains</hi> having fortune in their lap, ariſe, and fall with great reſolution on them, in this their diſorder, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling many, drove the reſt into a heap, whom (having
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98589:29"/> ſnatch't up their Weapons in haſt, and not had time to place themſelves regularly, but by chance) the <hi>Britains</hi> oppreſſed ſorely with their Chariots and Darts. <hi>Caeſar</hi> had notice of this by accident, for thoſe Cohorts which were upon the Guard, before the Camp, taking notice of a great duſt ariſing that way, which the Legion had march't, gave intelligence thereof to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who immediatly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the danger, commanded thoſe to go along with him, ſome to ſucceed them in the Guard, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Forces to follow after. Haſtening to the Field, when he came, he found the Legion in great perplexity, and ſorely laid to, but by his preſence and recruits, he did much revive them, and ſtay the <hi>Britiſh</hi> fury, yet on the one hand, he thought good to ſtand ſtill for ſome time, without provoking the Enemy, ſuppoſing this not a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſeaſon, his Men having a terror on them, upon the late misfortune, and they would not attempt on him, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting greater Forces in the rear: So at laſt both with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew, <hi>Caeſar</hi> to his Camp, and the other up into the Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> Britains <hi>attempt</hi> Caeſar <hi>before his Camp, with ill ſucceſs, and</hi> Caeſar'<hi>s return.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe <hi>Britains</hi> being ſomewhat diſcouraged in their late thoughts of protracting the Warre, by the expedition and activeneſs of the <hi>Roman</hi> General, in the repair of his Ships, and not much hoping for ſuch another advantage, by the Diviſion of the Enemies Forces, they deſign, while their late ſucceſs was freſh in memory, to give one manly attempt more, for the recovery of their liberty, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the great diſadvantage on them, of Arms, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Union, in thoſe they were to ſight with. They had this other encouragement, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> could not follow his Chace far, for want of Horſe, if they ſhould looſe the day, and being Victors, as they ſpread it up and down they had been, in the laſt Skirmiſh, beſides the booty they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98589:30"/> might gain, and a fair expectation of delivering their Country; at this time they were not without confidence of fruſtrating future attempts, by the terror ſuch a fortune would bring on the <hi>Romans;</hi> to this may be added, that confederated Forces, are too apt to diſſolve on caſual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingencies, which the late ſmiles of fortune had kept to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and increaſt. Some few days they were on both ſides kept from action, by tempeſtuous weather, but this being blown over, they draw down a conſiderable force of Horſe and foot toward the <hi>Roman</hi> Camp. <hi>Caeſar</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives them with his Army, in good order before it, and without much time ſpent, puts them to flight, chaſing them with about thirty Horſe, which <hi>Comins</hi> had brought thither, upon his Embaſſie, before <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s landing; ſome ſlaughter was made, and in the cloſe, ſome Towns were fired that night by the <hi>Romans;</hi> after which they return to their Camp again. This attempt ſucceeding ſo ill, the <hi>Britains</hi> again reſolve to make conditions, and to that purpoſe, ſend Embaſſadors to treat of Peace; the Tearms are agreed on, and amongſt the reſt, that Hoſtages ſhould be ſent, for the ſecurity thereof, after <hi>Caeſar</hi> into <hi>Gallia,</hi> whether he had now thoughts to return, but with no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intent in him, then to come back the next ſeaſonable time into the Iſland, into whoſe weakneſs, by this his firſt voyage, he had too deep an inſight, and of which, they were not long after ſenſible.</p>
               <p>The Winter drawing on, for <hi>September</hi> was begun, <hi>Caeſar</hi> makes haſte back, ſuſpecting the danger of theſe Seas in ſuch time, to his crazie and ſhattered Fleet, and taking the opportunity of a fair Wind, weighs Anchor, and ſets ſayl, ſomewhat after midnight; arriving ſafely with all but eleven Ships of burden, upon the Continent, theſe not keeping their courſe, landed ſomewhat lower at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Port, and the Souldiers being few in number, the <hi>Morini,</hi> on whoſe Coaſts they happened to be, falling on them, would have cut them to pieces, but they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcued by <hi>Caeſar;</hi> and this was the firſt attempt made upon the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Coaſts, of which we have any ſufficient Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to ground an Hiſtory on.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:98589:30"/>
               <head>Caeſar'<hi>s ſecond Voyage.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CAEſar</hi> having made his return into <hi>Gallia,</hi> according to his cuſtomary way, paſſes into <hi>Italy</hi> for <hi>Rome,</hi> there to ſpend the Winter, in the management of his <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Intereſts, leaving behind him, to his principal Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, command to repair thoſe Veſſels, in which he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and to fit them according to particular directions he had left of building new ones. He ordered a very great number to be built; that they ſhould be flat bottomed, and lower, in the nature of Gallies, to the intent, they might uſe them with Oares, be fitter for ſhipping, and landing his Men, and wider to carry over the more Souldiers, and Proviſions for an Army. This was with great diligence and induſtry, effected according to their inſtructions, by the Legates, and other Officers left behind. What was want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Coaſts of <hi>Gallia,</hi> they cauſed according to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, to be brought from <hi>Spain,</hi> inſomuch that at <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s return, he found about ſix hundred Veſſels ſitted for this purpoſe. Obſerving this, he commended thoſe who were diligent in their care and truſt, and ſetling ſome diſorders that were ariſing in <hi>Gallia,</hi> upon the apprehenſion of his intended abſence; He prepares himſelf for his ſecond Voyage.</p>
               <p>Three Legions, and about two thouſand Horſe he left behind him, neer the Port <hi>Iccius,</hi> with Inſtructions to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide neceſſaries of War, and to ſecure his return; five Legions he deſignes to take with him, and two thouſand Horſe, and to carry over a large number out of the beſt Families of the <hi>Galls,</hi> which might be to him in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Hoſtages, cutting off a Prince of the greateſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and intereſt amongſt them, who had with-drawn himſelf privily, after he could not be excus'd by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> from going along with him, on ſeveral pretences of oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſtay. Being ready, not long after, it blew a fair gale, whereupon he ſhips his Men, ſetting ſayl at the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down of the Sun, with a gentle Wind, ſtanding for the Coaſts of <hi>Britany,</hi> but it left him about midnight fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98589:31"/> ſo the Tide prevailing by ſpring of day, he could perceive they had held a courſe, which brought them much upon the left hand of that part of the Iſland, where <hi>Caeſar</hi> had the laſt year landed his Men, and at what place again for his former good ſucceſs, and the knowledge of the ground, he did deſire to arrive. The Tide turning, and befriending them again; with the benefit of their Oares alſo, they came by noon the ſame day to the Coaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and landed without any diſturbance. The <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> having made a retreat, upon the apprehenſion of his Forces, which they concluded were very great, from the number of the Ships above 800 in all, many being added to carry Proviſions and ſome Officers, having divers for their private uſe. <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the firſt thing he did upon land, appointed out a place for a Camp, and cauſes it to be fortified, wherein he left the baggage, and a party of ten Cohorts, to ſecure both that and the Fleet, which was at Anchor hard by, and leaving <hi>Q. Atrius</hi> to command, he begins his march, to finde out the <hi>Britains,</hi> having been informed by certain Priſoners, which way they had made their retreat. When he had marcht about twelve miles, he found the <hi>Britains,</hi> with their Horſe and Chariots, to have made a ſtand at a River ſide, on a piece of ground of advantage, in reſpect of the height. <hi>Caeſar</hi> charges them, and they receive him valiantly, but being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matcht, and their apprehenſions preſſing on them, they make a further retreat into the Woods, to a fortification ſtrong by nature and Art, according to the faſhion of their own Country, and divers Trees being cut down and laid acroſs; (I ſuppoſe at diſtances without the Camp;) The <hi>Romane</hi> Order thereby was much impeaded in their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches. The <hi>Britains</hi> made frequent ſallies in ſmall parties, and did ſome miſchief to <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Army, but the Souldiers of the ſeventh Legion raiſing a Mount and a Teſtudo, entred their Fortreſs, and the <hi>Britains</hi> were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained again to diſlodge and flie, not much loſs being ſuffered on either ſide, in reſpect, the rather the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpent, and the Country unknown to him, he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to continue the Chaſe far, but did deſire to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy his Men in the fortifying another Camp for the lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98589:31"/> of his Souldiers that night; an excellent piece of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, whereby to ſecure and refreſh a wearied Army, and of great practiſe amongſt, and conducement to the <hi>Romans</hi> in all their Conqueſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Storm does miſchief to</hi> Caeſar'<hi>s Fleet.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe next day after, <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſent out three Parties of Horſe and Foot to finde out the <hi>Britains,</hi> and take ſome ſpoiles of the Country; but preſently upon it, news came to him from the Fleet, by certain Horſemen from <hi>Q. Atrius,</hi> that the night before, almoſt every Ship had ſome miſchief; divers were broken to pieces, and made utterly uncapable of ſervice, and moſt caſt upon the Shoar, by the violence of a Tempeſt which had been ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the night before the Anchors coming home, and the induſtry of the Sea-men little availing. Upon this news, <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſends for the Souldiers back again that were on their march, and returns to the Fleet, where he ſets him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf diligently to work to repair it. He ſends to <hi>Labi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enus,</hi> whom he had left Commander in chief of his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <hi>Gallia</hi> to ſend him ſhipwrights, and to build him as many new Veſſels as poſſibly he could; and out of his own Army, he cauſes divers to be drawn, and imployed in the reparing of his Veſſels. In which buſineſs he ſpent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ten Days, not reſting in the Night, and with admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable induſtry, brought it to this effect, that not above for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were utterly unſerviceable and loſt. Suſpecting the like accident might again happen in his abſence, he cauſes them to be haled on ſhoar by the Camp ſide, and encloſed both with one ſtrong Fortification; and then leaving the ſame party which was there before for a guard, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns with the Forces he brought back to the place where he had lately beaten the <hi>Britains.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:98589:32"/>
               <head>Caſſibelan <hi>Elected General, attempts</hi> Caeſar'<hi>s Forces ſeveral times.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the mean while, at a common Conſultation the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> diſcourſe their Condition, and the inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ariſing to them by the diverſity of Councels, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon with one conſent Elect <hi>Caſſibelanus</hi> Prince of the <hi>Trinobantes</hi> for their Generaliſſimo; a Perſon of excellent conduct and valour, hoping by the management of their affairs in ſuch a hand to ſucceed the better. His Royal Seat was at <hi>Verulam</hi> about a mile from the now St. <hi>Albanes,</hi> and his Country large, extending it ſelf on the one ſide to the River of <hi>Thames; Caſſibelanus</hi> being placed in this truſt, raiſes very great forces, and with his Horſe and Chariots, falls upon the Enemies cavalry in their march, and gave them, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> acknowledges, a ſharp charge, but was not able to maintain the Fight long, againſt his well-diſciplin'd, and well-experienc't Veterans: Being compell'd to make to places of advantage, upon Hills, and among Woods, the Enemies following after them, of whom many were cut off in the purſuit, going too far from their Eagles, and being too eager in the Chaſe. <hi>Caſſibelanus,</hi> upon the <hi>Romans</hi> retiring to encamp, returns, and lying upon the edge of the Woods, reſolves to obſerve whether any advantage might be taken on them by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, with whom he thought he had no equal match in a plain Field. It fell out according to his expectation, for the Army of <hi>Caeſar</hi> was generally diſordered in fortifying their Camp, there being a party only, not very conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, on the guard before it. Upon theſe he charges with great reſolution, and ſuch a fury, that had not <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſent ſpeedily two Cohorts for their reſcue, it is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely moſt had been cut off; for <hi>Q. Laberius Durus,</hi> a Tribune was that day killed, with many others. Theſe two Cohorts were ſome ſmall diſtance from each other, and it ſhould ſeem, by the report of <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries, that the Guard was ſurrounded, and thereupon being over-laid and terrified with an unuſual kind of fight,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98589:32"/> they broke through the Enemy, and either retreated, or plainly fled into the diſtance betwixt thoſe two Cohorts before mentioned for their ſecurity, but ſeveral more freſh ſupplies coming in; the <hi>Britains</hi> retire themſelves, either ſatisfied with what they had done, or that probably upon the Alarm, they could not do much more.</p>
               <p>The manner of this Fight was thus on <hi>Caſſibelan</hi>'s ſide: When he charged the Horſe, it was done in ſmall parties with great diſtances, (the rather it may be, becauſe of their Chariots, which muſt have compaſs to turn in) if any had the worſt, they retreated, and ſometimes in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy did it without any other cauſe, whom if a few of the <hi>Romans</hi> followed, they would deſcend out of their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, and fight the Horſe on foot, which <hi>Caeſar</hi> declares was not an equal match on the <hi>Roman</hi> ſide; and when they charg'd the Foot, if there were reaſon, they would retire in good Order, and avoid the Chaſe of the heavy armed Legionaries; if any of their own Parties were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid or wearied, through theſe ſpaces they ſent freſh men. Whether this was their cuſtomary way of fighting, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by <hi>Caſſibelan</hi> to match this kinde of Enemy, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, but doubtleſs it was advantageous to the <hi>Britains;</hi> and had they had as good defenſive Weapons as the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> it is like enough they might have given a good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of that Days work.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caſſibelan</hi> the next day after kept the Hills farre from the Camp, and appeared but little in Parties, in reſpect of what he had done before, until Noon; at what time <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſent out three Legions, and all the Horſe to forrage with <hi>C. Trebonius,</hi> a Legate, whom (encouraged by his former ſucceſs) he charges very reſolutely; but the <hi>Romans</hi> receiving him with a great force, and preventing the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> policy, by preſſing ſo hard upon them, that they could neither rally thoſe that were routed, nor relieve ſuch as were hard laid to, at laſt they were forced to flie, many of his Men being killed in the Battail and purſuit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:98589:33"/>
               <head>Caſſibelan'<hi>s ſecond thoughts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CAſſibelan,</hi> upon this, concluding with himſelf, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of advantage could be had upon the <hi>Romans</hi> in a cloſe fight on equal ground, comes in the next place to a reſolution of attending <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his march, with a ſmall number of his choice Forces, which accordingly he does, and taking with him about four thouſand Wagons. By the advantage he had in the knowledge of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, he thought to ſecure himſelf the better from being forced to fight, and to keep the <hi>Romans</hi> from doing much ſpoile in plundering and firing it; Withall, he conceived he might ſtarve them out at laſt, by cauſing all the Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to be driven into the Woods, where they apprehended the <hi>Romans</hi> would take their march; this was according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put in execution, not without hopes alſo, as occaſion ſerv'd, to cut ſome of them off who did ſtraggle, if they could not light upon an opportunity of advantage on the whole body of the <hi>Roman</hi> Army; a Counſel of good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivement and ſucceſs, for it fell out after, that divers who were ſpread up and down upon hope of plunder were killed, which occaſioned the <hi>Romans</hi> to march cloſe, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to ſome ſtreights for proviſion, and prevented thereby great miſchief to the Towns. <hi>Caeſar</hi> being in his march for the Country of the <hi>Trinobantes,</hi> intending to paſs over the River <hi>Thames,</hi> at a place fordable, but one thereabouts being known (about <hi>Oatlands</hi> ſuppoſed) by the Captives and Runagates, he underſtood that the Enemy lay with a good force on the other ſide, and that the Foard was knock't full of Piles of Wood, ſharpned at the upper end, and were all under Water out of ſight, to the intent they might annoy, and diſorder the <hi>Romans</hi> in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the River, being ignorant thereof, and ſo ſet upon them at landing in their confuſion; which being diſcover'd, did prevent the hoped for ſucceſs of <hi>Caſſibilan</hi>'s deſign; for <hi>Caeſar</hi> paſs't over with the greater care and expedition, readily provided to receive the <hi>Britains,</hi> ſending the Horſe firſt, and directing the Legions to follow cloſe after them,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98589:33"/> in whom he had greater confidence againſt this Enemy, then in the Cavalry, theſe being frequently in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> confeſſeth in their marches, when they were far from the Legions upon any occaſion. The <hi>Romane</hi> Foot having march't through the Water, which was up to their ſhoulders, and being come to the Bank-ſide, gave a charge upon the <hi>Britains,</hi> who not being able to ſuſtain it, gave way, after ſome conteſt, and at laſt fled. <hi>Caeſar</hi> from hence takes his march directly to <hi>Verulam,</hi> not far from the now St. <hi>Albanes,</hi> intending to force it, having underſtood it was a Town of ſome importance, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Seat of <hi>Caſſibelan,</hi> and full of Cattle driven in thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, upon apprehenſion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Army; this he aſſaults, and poſſeſſes himſelf of it, the People haſtening out, not being able to reſiſt him, many of whom were killed in the flight.</p>
               <p>All this while <hi>Caſſibelan</hi> waited on <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and out of the Woods, by paths unknown to the <hi>Romans,</hi> did skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh with them now and then, as he contriv'd or found advantage, eſpecially with the Horſe, and ſuch parties as were abroad for forrage and plunder, which did occaſion more ſafety to the <hi>Britains,</hi> and in a great part render <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s deſign of a ſpeedy conqueſt, and to enrich himſelf and his Souldiers with the ſpoile of the Country, fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs. Whereupon on the other hand the <hi>Roman</hi> General caſts about to ſave his honour, and to ſhift off a War like to be tedious and unprofitable. There was a faction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Caſſibelan,</hi> among the <hi>Trinobantes,</hi> who had ſent Commiſſioners at this time in the name of that State to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> deſiring that <hi>Mandubratius</hi> the Son of <hi>Immanuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> who was formerly Prince of their Country, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and kill'd by <hi>Caſſibelan,</hi> might be reſtored to them, and withall offer to ſubmit themſelves to the <hi>Roman</hi> Common-wealth, and to give Hoſtages for ſecurity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. This opportunity <hi>Caeſar</hi> gladly takes hold on, and accepts the tearmes, requiring forty Hoſtages, and certain Corn for his Army, which by the policy of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> General would not long have been out of want, had they not receiv'd theſe Proviſions, or gain'd the like by ſome other means, which would not have been ſo eaſie and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98589:34"/> Purſuant hereunto, <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſends <hi>Mandubratius,</hi> who had formerly fled to him out of <hi>Gallia,</hi> for the ſecurity of his life, to this people, according to their requeſt; and his Conditions on the other hand, they punctually and ſpeedily obſerve: <hi>Caeſar,</hi> deſirous to improve the fortune and contrivance, commanding his Souldiers to offer no violence to the <hi>Trinobantes,</hi> which was punctually obeyed; the conſequence whereof brought in five petty States more to <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s ſubmiſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> Britains <hi>ſubmit, and</hi> Caeſar <hi>leaves the Country.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CAſſibelanus,</hi> this while expecting the ſucceſs of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, he had laid, to fall upon the <hi>Romane</hi> Camp, in their ſecurity, by his Allies, where the ſhipping was in <hi>Kent,</hi> though he found a decay of his ſtrength, did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear as yet to treat: but that failing alſo, by a Sally made out of the Camp, the <hi>Romans</hi> beating them of <hi>Kent,</hi> who were to execute it, and one of their chief Nobility taken Priſoner, he comes at laſt to a Reſolution of ſubmitting; having performed to his eternal glory all the parts of an able General, with inconſiderable Forces, compared to thoſe of his Enemy, hoping for a better conjuncture of affairs hereafter, which <hi>Caeſar</hi> more willingly accepts, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting little other good to be done that Summer, and now ſtudying to return to affairs of better expectation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caſſibelan</hi> was a Prince of admirable conduct and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and inferiour to <hi>Caeſar</hi> only in the quality of his Forces, he commanded, as has appeared by the prudent courſes he took at all times in managing the War, and the reſolute attempts he made, his ground being won from him by the Inch, and not without puzling the brains of <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelf.</p>
               <p>It is manifeſt here was made but an inconſiderable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> yet in his Commentaries he declares he put down what tribute the <hi>Britains</hi> ſhould pay, as if he had made a compleat Conqueſt, when <hi>Tacitus</hi> and other <hi>Romane</hi> Authors conclude generally, he did little more
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98589:34"/> than ſhew, than the Country. We will receive it in a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable ſenſe, that he meant, he had made ſuch tearms with ſome part of them. <hi>Caeſar</hi> intending for the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and being fuller of baggage at his return than entry, (having many Priſoners alſo) becauſe he had loſt ſome of his Ships in the tempeſt, contrives to carry over his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers at twice, which accordingly he did, after ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, in exſpecting the return of certain of the firſt, that were diſperſt by contrary Winds: and landed them ſafe in <hi>Gallia,</hi> in a good paſſage thither.</p>
               <p>Theſe were the enterprizes of <hi>Caeſar</hi> in this Iſland: he was of an excellent contrivance, and bold in execution, wary, ſubtile and circumſpect, in all his martial affairs, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended almoſt conſtantly with ſucceſs; but was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out violencies of luſt and ambition in the proſecuting his deſigns, not ſhewing at all times that due reverence to the Power above, or reſpect to man-kinde, as became a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his endowments, from nature. After great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendings amongſt his Country-men, not without a large ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of blood and ſlaughter, being arrived at a high pitch of Power and fame, in the glory of the <hi>Roman</hi> ſtate the Senate Houſe, in the cloſe of all his labours and toiles, when he expected to have received ſome fruits of his ſweat and pains, he was murdered at the foot of his Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in-Law, <hi>Pompey</hi>'s Image, whom not long before he had ruined, with above twenty wounds, his neer relation <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> whom once he intended a great ſhare of his eſtate, being a principal contriver; and that <hi>Brutus</hi> the Son of <hi>Servilia,</hi> ſuppoſed to be his baſe Childe, giving him a mortal ſtab in the bottome of his belly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The State of</hi> Britain, <hi>during the time of</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus, Tiberius <hi>and</hi> Caligula.</head>
               <p>UPon the return of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> as was before mentioned, to the Continent, the civil Wars of <hi>Rome</hi> hapned, the principal of their Common-wealth falling out about di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98589:35"/> the plunder and riches, which in ſeveral Ages their Country-men had been acquiring; during which time, the <hi>Britains</hi> had reſpite from their Invaſions.</p>
               <p>Upon the death of <hi>Caeſar, Auguſtus</hi> after he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with <hi>M. Anthony,</hi> and became Superior, not only to him, but all of a contrary faction in <hi>Rome,</hi> did affect a quiet and peaceable life, ſuppoſing it not convenient, as he gave out, to enlarge the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire, big enough for management already, and thereupon the <hi>Britains</hi> had ſtil the greater ſecurity. But the tribute ſet down by <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar,</hi> being neglected to be paid, twice or thrice he intended an Invaſion, diſdaining to be baffled by a Country of little note in thoſe days; but being on his march in Perſon, was diverted by revolts on ſome other remote borders of his Dominions, and withall pacified by ſome <hi>Britiſh</hi> Embaſſadors, who renewed their conditions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tiberius</hi> who ſucceeded him, had the ſame reſolutions, but was on different reaſons moved to it, chooſing rather to attend his luſt and cruelties at home, than look abroad into forreign Countrys.</p>
               <p>Him followed <hi>Caligula</hi> in the ſupream Authority, a Prince diſſolute, and abounding in vain conceits, as do witneſs his ſolemn meſſage to the Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> of the Conqueſt of <hi>Britain,</hi> when neither he or any of his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ever ſet foot thereon. The colour was the receiving of <hi>Adminius,</hi> a fugitive <hi>Britain,</hi> the Son of <hi>Cunobeline,</hi> a Prince in this Iſland, who fled from his Fathers angel, and ſubmitted himſelf to <hi>Caligula.</hi> In his Raign nothing fell out worthy to be reported in the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Hiſtory, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs one ſhould remember his frivolous attempt upon the Ocean, at ſuch time as all Men did generally preſume, he intended to imbarque for <hi>Britain;</hi> the Story whereof take from <hi>Suetonius</hi> in his own words, thus tranſlated; Laſt of all, as if he were undertaking a War, marching with his Army on the Sea ſhoar, and placing his Engines of battery, no Man knowing or imagining what he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to do, on a ſudden commands them to fill their Helmets and their Laps with Shells, calling them the Spoils of the Ocean, of right a due to the Capitol and Palace; and as a Trophy of his Victory, erects a moſt high Tower,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98589:35"/> out of which, as from a Pharus, Fires might every night ſhine, to direct the courſe of Sea-men; and having decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a donative of a hundred donaries to every Man, as if he had exceeded all examples of liberality, bids them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part now joyfull, depart with plenty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder</hi> Claudius, <hi>by the conduct of</hi> A. Plautius.</head>
               <p>ALI this while it appears not to the contrary, but that the <hi>Britains,</hi> who paid their tribute, enjoyed, aſwell as the reſt of their Country-men, their Laws, Cuſtomes, and Liberties. During this long intermiſſion from diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, being divided into many petty Kingdomes and Nations, they were frequently among themſelves at War in one place or another; one Intereſt prevailing ſometimes, and at another a different, and upon Victory, many of the adverſe party either were baniſhed or fled of themſelves. And ſo it fell out, that <hi>Glaudius</hi> ſucceeding <hi>Caligula,</hi> one <hi>Berieus</hi> being a <hi>Britiſh</hi> fugitive, inſtigated him to make an attempt on the Iſland, which <hi>Glaudius</hi> did well like of, and thereupon ſent Orders to <hi>A. Plautius,</hi> to tranſport thoſe Souldiers, which he then commanded in <hi>Gallia,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Country; the Souldiery were very unwilling to go, and trifled away their time in a kinde of mutiny, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that <hi>Caeſar</hi> hearing thereof, ſent <hi>Narciſſus</hi> his freed man to haſten their imbarquing, which he accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly did, but not without diſdain in them, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of him, in reſpect of his former condition, having been once a Slave.</p>
               <p>The Army was divided into three bodies, intending thereby, that if they were obſtructed in one place, by the difficulty thereof, or the ſtrength of the Enemy, they might ſome of them land in another. Having put to Sea, they met with croſs Winds, and foul weather, which was the cauſe of great diſturbance, but a light darting toward the Iſland, from the place whence they put to Sea, certain who had good wiſhes for the journey, interpreted it as a direction from ſome God, that favoured their enterprize,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98589:36"/> and ſo encouraged the Fleet, which ſtrugling with the violence of the Tempeſt, they at laſt landed on the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Coaſts.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Britains</hi> not ſuſpecting their arrival, becauſe of the diſorder they heard was among the <hi>Roman</hi> Army in <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> which was before mentioned, did not oppoſe their landing; moreover their civil contentions being lately ſharp they could not ſuddenly make ſuch a confederacy, as might probably encounter with a good expectation, the force of the <hi>Romans</hi> at peace, and marvelouſly ſtrong in all parts: So they retired into places that were woody and full of bogs, expecting, as <hi>Dion</hi> ſays, to weary out the <hi>Romans,</hi> as <hi>Caſſibelan</hi> their former General had done heretofore with <hi>Julius Caeſar. Plautius</hi> beſtows great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in finding out their ſcattered Forces, and meets with ſome, to wit with <hi>Cataratacus,</hi> and <hi>Togodumnus,</hi> the two Sons of <hi>Cunobeline</hi> lately dead, whom he eaſily diſſipates, and withall practiſes to head ſome of their factions againſt the other, following the example of <hi>Julius Caeſar;</hi> a thing not difficult, in a Country divided into ſuch a multitude of Nations, as <hi>Britany</hi> then was: And he finds one proper for his purpoſe amongſt the <hi>Boduni,</hi> or <hi>Dobuni,</hi> ſeated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter</hi> ſhires, whom he receives into his protection, having been before ſubject to the <hi>Catuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lani,</hi> a Nation about <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and the Country of <hi>Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Leaving a Garriſon among them, he marches to a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, intending a paſſage over, to finde out certain other <hi>Britains,</hi> who lay in ſecurity beyond it, ſuſpecting like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe nothing, becauſe they thought the <hi>Romans</hi> could not get to the other ſide, being the Water was deep, and that there was no Bridge: but <hi>Plautius</hi> having <hi>Germans</hi> with him, who were accuſtomed to Swim through Rivers in Arms, he ſent them over firſt, who falling upon the <hi>Britains</hi> unexpectedly, did them much miſchief, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by wounding their Horſes that drew their Chariots, which in their encountrings they did chiefly aime at; <hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius Veſpaſian,</hi> and <hi>Sabinus</hi> alſo followed and kill'd ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, not apprehenſive thereof till it was too late. But this notwithſtanding, they rallied together, and by the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98589:36"/> of the night got into ſome order, and gave them Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail the next day with great courage; which was for ſome time doubtful: But the few and naked <hi>Britains,</hi> by their diviſions leſs able, did yield to the heavy Armed, united, and well diſciplined <hi>Romans;</hi> though like enough they were equal, if not ſuperiour to them in perſonal reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Upon their flight, they paſs over the River of <hi>Thames,</hi> being acquainted with it better than the <hi>Romans,</hi> at a place not far from that, where it delivers it ſelf into the Sea; The <hi>Romans</hi> followed, and the <hi>Germans</hi> again take the Water; others go over at a Bridge ſomewhat higher; and encompaſſing the <hi>Britains,</hi> give them a great ſlaughter; which was yet in ſome meaſure repaid by the <hi>Britains,</hi> who having kept their Courage, though they loſt the Battail, deſtroyed many of their Enemies, following the Chaſe too far among the Bogs; but <hi>Togodumnus</hi> was ſlain.</p>
               <p>But this is ſaid, rather to inflame, than abate the <hi>Britain</hi> reſolutions, for they now having got ſome time to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of their affairs, put themſelves, as is reported, ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to work, to defend their Liberties in a more formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable manner, than heretofore they had done; whereupon <hi>Plautius,</hi> according to his Inſtructions, if any thing of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhould happen, as <hi>Dion</hi> delivers it, endeavours the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of what he had got, and ſends to <hi>Claudius</hi> for his direction, in the danger approaching: He upon this news, puts the affairs he had at <hi>Rome</hi> in order, and comes part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Land, and a conſiderable way by Sea, where he was in great danger by Tempeſts, to his Army, expecting him at the River of <hi>Thames.</hi> Soon after he was with them, he paſſes the River, gives the <hi>Britains</hi> Battail, and vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, takes the City <hi>Camalodunum,</hi> ſuppoſed to be the now <hi>Maldon</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> the then regal Seat of <hi>Cunobeline,</hi> others upon their ſubmiſſion, he receives to mercy, diſarms many, and leaves <hi>Plautius</hi> to ſubdue more with theſe doubts alſo behind him to after Ages, whether he came thither upon a vanity, affecting a Tryumph, and other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories of honour, or that in truth <hi>Plautius</hi> was hard laid to, and withall no leſs diſputable, whether ſo much as any conſiderable Battail was fought the <hi>Britains,</hi> like enough,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98589:37"/> yielding upon the extraordinary preparations of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> and good tearms offered them; for the confiſcation of their goods was remitted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſtaid here about ſixteen days; what was done af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his return, by <hi>Plautius,</hi> is not much taken notice of; but I ſhould think the Conqueſt of the Weſt about <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall, Somerſetſhire,</hi> and <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> was now perfected, ſithence mention is made of his Inroads there toward the Iſle of <hi>Wight;</hi> and I remember not any particular other diſcourſe of their yielding. For the ſpoils and acquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons here taken, upon his return to <hi>Rome, Claudius</hi> did him publick honour. And now is the firſt time that the <hi>Romans</hi> may have been ſaid to have taken any poſſeſſion of this Country, which was about the Year of Grace 44, or 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>P. Oſtorius <hi>ſucceeds</hi> Plautius.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>OStorius</hi> was the next that ſucceeded <hi>A. Plautius,</hi> for ought we know of any account in authentick Hiſtory to the contrary. At his coming, he found thoſe <hi>Britains</hi> who had conſpired with the <hi>Romans,</hi> to the deſtruction of their Country, or had made any League or ſubmiſſion to them, over-run by ſuch who were faithful to their Native Soile, and had not ſubmitted, and much waſte made in their Fields, not being apprehenſive of the <hi>Roman</hi> Forces, the rather, becauſe their General was not acquainted as yet with his buſineſs, and in this colder Climate (Winter being begun) they ſuſpected not much action. <hi>Oſtorius</hi> obſerving this, takes with him certain Cohorts which were moſt expedite and ready for his purpoſe, and ſets upon the <hi>Britains</hi> unexpectedly, routing thoſe that reſiſt, and chaſing them that flie.</p>
               <p>It ſhould ſeem, that the <hi>Romans,</hi> from the former War, had confederacy with, or poſſeſſion of ſo much Land, as lay from the River <hi>Sabrine</hi> and <hi>Anton,</hi> with bounds from the Ocean to the Sea. Theſe two Rivers do almoſt meet, and within their compaſs Southward, lies a very wealthy and rich part of the Iſland. Now it appears <hi>Ostorius</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:98589:37"/> (intending to ſecure what was gain'd, rather than to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the <hi>Roman</hi> Conqueſts) deſigned to Fortifie, and cloſe them, as it were with Garriſons: The words of <hi>Tacitus</hi> are, <hi>Cinctoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> caſtris Antonam &amp; Sabrinam fluvids cohibere pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Sabrine</hi> is well known to be the River <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern,</hi> but this <hi>Anton</hi> is much doubted of. Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> would have it be the River <hi>Nen,</hi> and that in <hi>Tacitus</hi> it is tranſcribed amiſs, and ſhould be <hi>Aufonam,</hi> the <hi>Avon,</hi> upon a ſuppoſition that the <hi>Britains</hi> call all Rivers <hi>Avon;</hi> and ſo <hi>Northampton</hi> ſhould ſtand on the North of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>von;</hi> but I doubt thereof, becauſe it ſeems not much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, if that River had been ever us'd to have been call'd the <hi>Avon,</hi> as I finde not: and at this day Men, I fear, think not of ſuch a name; the word <hi>Northampton</hi> ſeeming ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to infer, that it is a Town on the North ſide of a <hi>Ham,</hi> or <hi>Hame;</hi> the word <hi>Ham</hi> ſignifying generally a hook, from <hi>Hamus,</hi> and applicable frequently to hooks of Water; ſo this Town ſtanding on the North ſide of a hook of water, may have thence its name, as <hi>Southampton</hi> from a hook of Water in the South of the Town. I take it, that by <hi>Anton</hi> is meant the River <hi>Trent,</hi> becauſe it is a more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable River, and fit to bear a name of note, without particular diſtinction, as did that of <hi>Severne:</hi> it is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the third River of <hi>England,</hi> and proper to joyn hands with the other, for a boundary to a <hi>Roman</hi> Province; as it was after upon the diviſion betwixt the North and South. Nor is the name now utterly loſt; for there is a River to this day flowing into the Head thereof, called <hi>Derwent;</hi> there is a Houſe of conſiderable regard, called <hi>Trentum,</hi> and ſeveral Towns upon it ending in <hi>Anton,</hi> and of a ſound little differing: now <hi>Dwr,</hi> or <hi>Dour,</hi> in <hi>Britiſh</hi> ſignifies Water; and ſo by vulgar contraction it might be <hi>Dwrent</hi> or <hi>Trent;</hi> that is, the Water of <hi>Ent</hi> for <hi>Anton.</hi> Theſe are but conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, and we may have miſtaken, becauſe the evidence is not perſpicuous; and I ſhould not have made ſo many words hereof, but for the former, &amp; ſome reaſons following; and that it agrees better likewiſe with the Hiſtory it ſelf of the tranſactions upon theſe parts. But I will purſue this no further, it being not very much material which it was.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98589:38"/>
               <p>The <hi>Iceni</hi> being within this Line, did doubtleſs ſuſpect they might be ſubjected at laſt after the <hi>Romans</hi> were at leaſure to conquer them, as well as they had the reſt, who were within that compaſs: To which purpoſe, thoſe Rivers and Fortifications might be of great diſadvantage, by hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering ſuccours that might come from the North to their Aide, being all equally concerned at the Bondage now putting on them. Upon this, they Arm, and oppoſe their Fortifying, exciting ſeveral of their Neighbours to joyn with them, and chooſe a place to Incamp in. Behind there was a rude defence, and a ſtrait paſſage was before it: But <hi>Oſtorius,</hi> with thoſe Cohorts only, the benefit of his Allies, and his Horſe, fell in on their fortified ſide, which being made in haſt, and without good direction, they eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pluck't down. Here the <hi>Britains</hi> alſo fought valiantly, but with ill ſucceſs; and this their loſs confirmed ſuch to the <hi>Roman</hi> Peace, which before ſtood doubtful.</p>
               <p>From theſe, he brings his Army to the <hi>Cangi;</hi> I gueſs they were a People that lived within the Line, and like enough were the Inhabitants betwixt the <hi>Iceni</hi> and the <hi>Humber;</hi> theſe he plunders and waſts their Fields: It is likely they had been aſſiſting to the <hi>Iceni,</hi> or had made former Inroads upon the <hi>Roman</hi> Quarters, and their Allies. Meeting no conſiderable oppoſition from them, he turns upon the back of the <hi>Severne</hi> toward the <hi>Silures,</hi> a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that Inhabited about South <hi>Wales,</hi> with whom he would fain have had a Peace, uſing all gentle and cruel means to that purpoſe: but they, partly truſting to the conduct of <hi>Caractacus,</hi> a Prince grown famous for his skill in martial affairs, and partly to their own courage, refuſed it. In his Marches, there appeared againſt him no conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable oppoſition; ſometimes in ſmall Parties the <hi>Britains</hi> would charge the Body, or ſome Wing of his Army; where loſs was on both ſides, but chiefly to the <hi>Britains.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He had not paſſed far, but the <hi>Brigantes,</hi> a People a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> and the North of <hi>Trent</hi> took Arms; upon which, ſuſpecting what Inconvenience might be, in lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an Enemy behind him in Arms, to diſturb him, or his new Conqueſts, he turns, and before they could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come conſiderable, ſome few that were up, being ſlain,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98589:38"/> the reſt (upon his willingneſs to remit the Commotion) laid down their Arms, and went to their Homes. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he proſecutes again his Journey to the <hi>Silures,</hi> ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the mean time to the Colony at <hi>Camalodunum</hi> to come to him; whom he planted amongſt the lately Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, to the intent to reſtrain the attempts of thoſe, and of ſuch as were confederated with him, whom he had reaſon notwithſtanding to ſuſpect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caractacus</hi> finding himſelf weak in the number of his Forces, compared to thoſe of the <hi>Romans;</hi> and knowing he was in his own Country, bounded on many ſides by the Sea, and <hi>Severne,</hi> and ſo conſequently leſs apt to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, if he ſhould be ſtraitned: while time ſerved, takes his March into North <hi>Wales,</hi> called then the Country of the <hi>Ordovices,</hi> a Place leſs ſubject to theſe Inconveniencies, in reſpect it had more ſpacious Room of retreat or flight in adverſe fortune; and more capacious, as the <hi>Roman</hi> Conqueſts then were, of joyning his Arms with thoſE of his Confederates, which accordingly afterwards he effected. <hi>Oſtorius</hi> follows him, and when he overtook him, found him reſolved, and prepared for Battail; having to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe choſen a ſpacious piece of Ground of advantage.</p>
               <p>The ſcite of the Place was a declining Hill; upon the Skirts thereof were Rocks, and unpaſſable places, with ſome open; at the bottom a River croſs't it: within this he drew his Army up in Battalia, ſtopping the Avennes on the ſides with Stones, in the nature of a Rampart, and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Line before it of the ſame Materials, and in like fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, ſuſpecting the Foard of the River. Before his main Battail, he places a Body of choice Men, in this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der expecting the Enemy. In the mean time, the chief Commanders of the ſeveral Nations paſs't up and down amongſt their Forces, ſetting before them the advantages of a Victory, the miſeries of a Battail loſt; leſſening the cauſes of fear, and encreaſing thoſe of hopes, beyond a juſt meaſure, to the intent their minds might be fortified againſt the apprehenſion of danger; and with other Arts, that Generals in the like caſes uſe. And <hi>Caractacus</hi> eſpecially paſſing with quick motion up and down the Army, did excellently perform that part of a General; being brief, but
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98589:39"/> very eloquent in his Language, and of undaunted reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. This he told them was the day, and this the Battail that muſt either recover or determine their Liberties; call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing frequently upon the names of their noble Progenitors, who had driven <hi>Caeſar</hi> their Dictator out of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; thereby delivering them in their Lives, their Eſtates, Wives and Children, from the violence of the <hi>Roman</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude. With theſe Speeches the Army was much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, and to teſtifie and encreaſe their reſolutions, they make ſolemn Vows and Oaths not to yield to wounds or Darts.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, the <hi>Roman</hi> General, by the report of <hi>Tacitus,</hi> was ſomewhat apprehenſive of the Scite of the place; to him of great diſadvantage, but the Souldiery and chief Officers knowing the difficulty, was greateſt in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the naked <hi>Britains,</hi> and that inconſiderable, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their rude fortifications, and a River fordable in many places; and thereupon quicking the General, they paſs the River by his Command, approaching to the fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: at which place the <hi>Britains</hi> had the advantage in the Fight at a diſtance, for the <hi>Romans</hi> throwing heavy Piles up the Hill, and thoſe lighter down, it might follow, that theſe had the greater ſlaughter, though their Bodies were exceeding well armed, eſpecially ſuch doubtleſs, who made the firſt aſſault. But the <hi>Romans</hi> making a Teſtudo, which was a defence of Tarquets, hanging over one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, like Tiles on a Houſe toward the Enemy; under the protection thereof, they approacht the works, and pluckt down the ill-built Wall, and ſo entred. And now the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> coming to fight hand to hand, having neither Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met nor Arms on their Bodies, were forc'd to retire, which they did upwards to the top of the Hill; but the <hi>Romans</hi> following, had alſo the better there; ſeveral flying away, and others being taken: amongſt which, was the Wife and Daughter of <hi>Caractacus,</hi> and his Brethren alſo yielded themſelves: but <hi>Caractacus</hi> himſelf eſcaped, and fled to <hi>Cartiſmandua</hi> Queen of the <hi>Brigantes,</hi> who afterwards betrayed him unworthily to the <hi>Romans,</hi> who frequently made uſe of ſuch treacherous dealings: and <hi>Tacitus</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, though in advantageous language to the <hi>Roman</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98589:39"/> does acknowledge by this kinde of means, and by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperating and provoking one Prince againſt another, they had no ſmall advantage of theſe Nations. Whereas if they had been unanimous in their Councels, had choſen the right way of managing this War, under a prudent General; which was that which the famous <hi>Caſſibelan</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, on his experience with a flying Army; to which their way of living on Cattle was advantageous, they might have rendered the <hi>Roman</hi> Conqueſts vain: But it fell out other ways, as it might reaſonably be expected from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted Counſels; for truſting to the nature of the ground, and the weaker fortifications, their great ſtrength, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted courage came to nothing. <hi>Caractacus,</hi> with his Wife, Daughters and Brothers were ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with many more, and ſeveral of the ſpoils taken. And to the intent <hi>Claudius</hi> might have the greater glory him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, being the Author and Maintainer of this War, as he had alſo been the Actor in it ſome time, they were pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly brought before him, ſitting in great State, his Wife <hi>Agripina</hi> being formally placed by him; and contrivement on all hands to magnifie the Victory to pleaſe the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caractacus</hi> at his preſentment before the Tribunal, with an undaunted mind in this his Adverſity, ſpake to this effect. <hi>If I had carried my ſelf with a moderation in my Proſperity, equal to the Quality of my Birth and Fortune, I might rather now have come to this City as a Friend than Captive; neither would You have thought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily of a Peace made with one deſcended of ancient and Royal blood, and commanding many Nations. My preſent Condition is to Me unhappy, to You glorious. I had Horſes, Men, Arms, and Wealth; no wonder if I was unwilling to loſe them: If You will command all things, it follows that all muſt obey. If I had preſently ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, neither My Fortune, nor Your Glory had been ſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, and My Afflictions had quickly been Forgotten: but if You ſhew Me Mercy, I ſhall live to the Eternal Memory of Thy Clemency. Caeſar</hi> being taken with his behaviour, pardons him, his Wife and Brothers, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes their Irons to be taken off: upon which they reverence
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98589:40"/> the Emperor and Empreſs, with many praiſes and grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful acknowledgments; Men commending the ſhew, and comparing it to what was ſeen, when <hi>Scipio</hi> ſhew'd <hi>Syphax</hi> and <hi>L. Paulus Perſes</hi> to the <hi>Roman</hi> People, did declare it an equal Spectacle: and to <hi>P. Oſtorins</hi> the Ornaments of a Triumph were directed.</p>
               <p>The ſucceſs of this Battail had a various event, for it begat careleſneſs in the <hi>Romans,</hi> and in the <hi>Britains,</hi> as it did cloſer Counſels, ſo alſo a more eager mind of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge; to which was added a report bruited up and down, ſaid to be ſpoken by the <hi>Roman</hi> General, that as in times paſt, the <hi>Sugambri</hi> were expelled their Country, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into <hi>Gallia;</hi> ſo the very name of the <hi>Silures</hi> ſhould be utterly extinguiſh't. But being at laſt well aware of the inequality of their defenſive Arms, they reſolve to try no more the event of a ſet Battail, but to take thoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, which they had of the knowledge of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and with their active motion, to ſeize on ſuch oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, as offered themſelves from the <hi>Roman</hi> care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs.</p>
               <p>The firſt that happened was this, the Camp-maſter (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing left behind, with a few Cohorts to fortifie certain places in the Country of the <hi>Silures)</hi> they fall upon, and encloſe them; and had not ſuccour come from the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Towns and Garriſons, they had been all utterly cut off. The Camp-maſter notwithſtanding, and eight Centurions, (of the quality of Captains now with us) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the moſt forward Souldiers were ſlain. Not long after this, they ſet upon the forragers, and together with them, put certain Horſemen, ſent to their reſcue, to flight. <hi>Oſtorius</hi> ſends before hand ſeveral of his Foot, lightly armed, to ſtay the purſuit, whom the <hi>Britains</hi> alſo beat and chaſe, until the more heavy Armed came up: upon that remarkable diſadvantage, the <hi>Britains</hi> firſt ſtay, and then retreat with ſmall loſs, the rather, becauſe the Day was almoſt ſpent. This way of fighting ſucceeding well, they continue it, making frequent Sallies out of the Woods and Bogs, (in thoſe Days here being very many) as opportunity ſerved. Encouraged with booty and ſucceſs, and inflamed with rage to ſee their Native Soyl a Prey to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98589:40"/> greedy and unjuſt Uſurpers: doing much miſchief to their Enemies, confirming their friends, and gaining freſh; which they procured by Spoils and Captives, frequently ſent as Preſents.</p>
               <p>The third conſiderable blow they gave the <hi>Romans,</hi> was upon two Cohorts; they were Auxiliaries, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted; forraging too greedily and careleſly by the avarice of their Commanders; but paid dear for it. Theſe occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, together with the care of the War, if they did not break the heart of <hi>Oſtorius,</hi> yet they did at leaſt the more ſpeedily end his Days: at which the <hi>Britains</hi> did pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as being a Commander not to be contemned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A. Didius <hi>ſucceeds.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DIdius</hi> was ſent by <hi>Caeſar</hi> to ſupply his place, a Man aged, and careful of his reputation. When he came, he underſtood of another diſaſter befell a <hi>Roman</hi> Legion in the late Interval which <hi>Maulius Valens</hi> commanded: This was magnified by the <hi>Britains,</hi> to the intent they might encourage their Friends, and diſcountenance their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. And <hi>Didius</hi> did not endeavour to ſilence the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, ſuppoſing that which way ſo ever the chance fell, it might be to him of advantage: If he conquered, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour was the greater; if not, the diſgrace the leſs, and the danger alſo, under a Prince full of unconſtant and violent humours.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Silures</hi> all this while making great depredations, where the <hi>Romans</hi> had an Intreſt; after the taking of <hi>Garactacus; Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutius, e Ingantum civitate,</hi> ſays <hi>Tacitus,</hi> commanded in chief (unleſs it ſhould be meant the <hi>Brigantes</hi> Country, which I ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect I am at a loſs to gueſs where his birth was; but I doubt that, becauſe there muſt be too great error in the tranſcribers, perhaps it might be ſome petty State, not remembred at this day) having married <hi>Cartiſmandua,</hi> the Q. of the <hi>Brigantes,</hi> the Traytoreſs to her Country, he continued, while affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was betwixt them, obſequious to the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſhe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving allied her ſelf ſtrictly with them: but unkindneſſes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98589:41"/> ariſing, by reaſon of her want of Faith to his Bed; at firſt they fell out betwixt themſelves only; in which conteſt, by craft ſhe had ſubtilly intercepted the Brother, and neer relations of <hi>Venutius,</hi> having aſſumed <hi>Velocatus</hi> his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour-bearer to her embraces. Her Husband being the more inflamed at this, gathers a conſiderable Force, and intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to give her Battail, the <hi>Romans</hi> ſend her relief. The conteſt was ſharp and doubtful for a while, but at laſt did encline to <hi>Cartiſmandua. Caeſius Naſica</hi> commanding a Legion, at another time and place had alſo in another fight ſomewhat the better: but <hi>Didius</hi> could do no more than juſt keep what he had got, and that not without great diſturbance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Veranius <hi>ſucceeds: and him</hi> Paulinus Suetonius, <hi>with ſome few others.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VEranius</hi> came after him in equal command and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and dyed immediatly upon it. And him <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus Suetonius</hi> ſucceeded. The Iſle <hi>Mona,</hi> now called <hi>Angleſey,</hi> was a Capital place amongſt the <hi>Ordovices,</hi> as being the Seat of the <hi>Druids,</hi> and ſtored with wealth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many had fled thither with a great part of their ſubſtance, as to a Place of ſecurity, being made an Iſland by an Arm of the Sea, and not eaſily paſſable: he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon deſigns to Invade it; for his Foot, he prepares flat bottomed Boats, in which he tranſported them, depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt upon the ſtability of the Legionaries: the Horſe followed, ſometimes foarding it, and ſometimes ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Shoar. The <hi>Britains</hi> had placed their Battail, and were numerous; the Women, their Hair hanging looſe, with Fire-brands in their Hands, paſſing up and down, and the <hi>Druids</hi> with their Hands lifted up to Heaven, did pour forth many bitter execrations. At this Novelty, the <hi>Roman</hi> Souldiery at firſt ſeemed to have had ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation, but after a while, the Commander in Chief en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging them, and they alſo animating one another, with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98589:41"/> Exhortations to this purpoſe. That they ſhould not be daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the ſight of Women, and Phanatick Men, they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc't and charged the <hi>Britains:</hi> who not appointed with an equal advantage to reſiſt them, ſuddenly fled; of whom they threw divers into certain Fires made hard by. This done, he plants Garriſons amongſt them, and to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, they might be leſs ſubject to ſudden Incurſions, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes their Woods to be cut down.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Suetonius</hi> was in the Iſland about ſetling his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, there was News brought to him of a revolt of the Province; the occaſion that then offered it ſelf was this: <hi>Praſutagus,</hi> Prince of the <hi>Iceni</hi> dyed, leaving behind him great ſtore of wealth, and intending to ſecure his Houſe, makes <hi>Caeſar</hi> his heir, with his two daughters: But this would not prevent the barbarous Luſt and Covetouſneſs of the <hi>Romans,</hi> for they plundered his Houſe, raviſhed his two Daughters, whipt his Wife <hi>Boadicia:</hi> The chiefeſt of the Nobility were turned out of their Inheritances, and the Royal Family accounted as Slaves. Theſe Villanies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in a Licentious and Inſolent manner, did move very much, not only the <hi>Iceni,</hi> but their Neighbours the <hi>Trinobantes,</hi> as yet not having loſt their ancient courage, though they had been reduc't into the form of a Province, and thereupon they hold ſecret Counſels, with an intent to revenge themſelves, and if it were poſſible, to put off that Yoak, which the greedy <hi>Romans</hi> had Impoſed. Their hatred was moſt bitter againſt the <hi>Veterans</hi> at <hi>Camalodu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> in the Colony there, (this <hi>Camalodunum</hi> was the now <hi>Maldon</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> as is ſuppoſed) becauſe they had thruſt the ancient Inhabitants out of their Houſes and Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, calling them Captives and Slaves.</p>
               <p>There was a Temple built, and dedicated therein to <hi>Claudius:</hi> to the Solemn Rites belonging thereunto, were divers Prieſts appointed, who under Colour of Religion, did moſt greedily devour the Subſtance of the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring <hi>Britains:</hi> to their Aggravations was added an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune Seaſon, (to wit) the <hi>Roman</hi> General was abſent, with a conſiderable part of the Army, and the Town was but ill fortified, by the careleſneſs of the <hi>Roman</hi> Officers. Theſe accidents fell out a little before the Attempt: the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98589:42"/> Image of Victory at <hi>Camalodunum</hi> fell down, and turned backwards; Women did ſing of Deſtruction, as if they had been Inſpired; Howling and Noiſes were heard in the Theatre and Court; in the Arm of the Sea, not far diſtant, was ſeen a ſtrange Apparition, and upon the ebbe, the Bodies of dead Men on the Shoar, which occaſioned a great terror to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and comfortable expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the <hi>Britains.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Veterans,</hi> becauſe <hi>Suetonius</hi> was far abſent, ſent to <hi>C. Decianus,</hi> a Procurator for Ayde, but he furniſh't them with only two hundred, and thoſe ill appointed: So there being not many Souldiers in the Town, the Chief of their dependance was on the ſtrength of their Temple. In this their diſtraction, <hi>Boadicia</hi> Commander in Chief of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, valiantly ſets upon them, repaying their cruelty in a juſt retribution of fury and revenge. Moſt of the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery were got into the Temple, where for two Days they continue, and then it was forced with great Slaughter. The <hi>Britains</hi> in the current of their Succeſs, march out, and meet <hi>P. Cerealis,</hi> with the ninth Legion, and certain Horſe coming to the Succour of the <hi>Veterans,</hi> and fight them, routing all, and deſtroying the Foot; but the Horſe fly with <hi>Cerealis</hi> into the Camp, and there ſecure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves within the Fortifications. <hi>Catus</hi> a Procurator hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Slaughter, and his Avarice in the Province, which had cauſed him to be hated, coming freſh into his mind, he thought it convenient for himſelf to fly, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly paſs't into <hi>Gallia,</hi> as a Place of greater ſafety for ſuch a hatefull memory as he had.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Suetonius</hi> hearing of theſe things, haſtens his return, and with an honourable reſolution, Marches through the <hi>Britain</hi> Quarters to <hi>London;</hi> a Place then famous for Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and plenty of Proviſions. Here he conſults, whether it were good for him to make that the Seat of War, or not: but conſidering among other Reaſons, his Number was not great, he reſolved to march out, and could not be perſwaded to ſtay, by the Importunacy, Cries and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of ſuch, as either Age, or Weakneſs of Sex, or a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to the Place had urged to a ſtay; reſolving rather to adventure this Town, though of Concernment, then to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98589:42"/> put a general hazard on the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Intereſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he marches out, ſeveral going with him, the reſt ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing behind, who without mercy were after by the Enemy put to the Sword. The ſame fate fell upon <hi>Verulam,</hi> a Town favoured by the <hi>Romans,</hi> in their Liberties; in this heat of revenge, they deſtroyed in the places before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and thereabouts, at the leaſt ſeventy thouſand <hi>Romans,</hi> and their Confederates, giving no quarter, but executing them with various deaths, giving a full draught of vengeance for their barbarous covetouſneſs, and ſavage Luſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Suetonius</hi> having with him about ten thouſand Men, which conſiſted of Legionaries, Auxiliaries and Horſe, and obſerving the Reſolutions of the Enemy, and that he could not long avoid a Battail, if they would force him to it, very prudently takes in good time the advantage of an excellent place to his purpoſe, and waits the coming of the <hi>Britains.</hi> In the entrance it was ſtrait, and encompaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with Woods, and he knew the Enemy was before, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Plain, where they could lay no Embaſcodo. His Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionaries upon expectation of a Battail, were cloſe ſet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; on each Wing were the Horſe, and the light Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with miſſive Weapons placed round about. The <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> tranſported with their late ſucceſs, and not enough aware of the diſadvantage of a ſet-Battail, though they had formerly, and their Anceſtors ſad experience of it, would notwithſtanding fight them upon theſe unequal tearms; for too great joy, and a paſſion of revenge, do equally, as well as fear, betray the Reaſon. <hi>Suetonius,</hi> as was ſaid, had choſen an excellent Place, and put his Men in admirable Order, conſidering the quality of his own Souldiers, and thoſe of the <hi>Britains;</hi> for the Legionaries being cloſe plac'd, uncapable of being ſurrounded, could meet with no more Enemies at one time, then they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were in number; and then being well Armed, the other naked, without ſome extraordinary contingency, theſe muſt yield: nor could a Victory be expected other ways to the <hi>Britains,</hi> then either by ſome Stratagem, great Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror by the <hi>Romans,</hi> or having a vaſt number of Men, by ſuch an oppoſition and ſlaughter of themſelves, as can
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98589:43"/> hardly be imagined any Men can endure.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Boadicia</hi> did appear in the Head of a vaſt Army with great confidence, but without good Diſcipline; ſuch was their vanity alſo, that many of their Wives were brought and plac'd in a kind of Coaches on the Skirts of the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail, in confidence to ſee the Slaughter of the <hi>Romans.</hi> The Queen her ſelf paſſing up and down with her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in a Chariot, amongſt the Forces, diſcourſing to them to this purpoſe: that now ſhe did not contend for a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Wealth, but as one of the meaneſt, to recover and defend their Liberties, to revenge the barbarous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries committed upon her Body, and the chaſtity of her Daughters. That the <hi>Roman</hi> Luſt was grown to ſuch a pitch, that they neither ſpared Virgins nor Matrons; that the Gods who were Revengers of ſuch horrible Impieties were preſent; the Legion that durſt give Battail was ſlain, the others are either hid, or ſecure themſelves in Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: ſhe puts them in mind alſo of their number, and of the cauſe of the War, and concludes with an Exhortation to die with honour, rather than live in Slavery: for her own part, this was the Reſolution of a Woman, the Men might live, if they pleaſed, in the condition of Slaves.</p>
               <p>On the other hand <hi>Suetonius</hi> uſes all Art, and mixes Exhortations with his good Conduct: he puts them in mind, that the Victory in moſt Battails, takes its riſe from a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few, and therefore they ſhould not be daunted at the apprehenſion of the ſmallneſs of their number, compared to that of the <hi>Britains;</hi> their glory would be the greater in a Victory, by the mention of that odds; but indeed many of the great number were Women; and above all, puts them in mind, how well they were Armed, how naked the <hi>Britains</hi> were, and what their ſucceſs had been heretofore upon ſuch advantage; deſiring them firſt to throw their Piles, which was a kind of heavy Dart, peculiar to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> and carryed by the Legionaries; and then to follow their work, with their Swords and their Pikes in their Shields, not regarding the Spoyl, till the danger was over, for where it falls, there it will be found by them after the Victory.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Britains</hi> could not forbear, but muſt charge them raſhly in this place of diſadvantage, which the Enemy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98589:43"/> without motion, while they were ſpending their miſſive Weapons; but immediatly after they Sallied out, and coming to a cloſe Fight, eaſily made the naked People give way and fly. Their Battail was ſurrounded with Waggons, ſo that they had great hinderance in the Flight, whereby the Slaughter was encreaſt; the inſolent and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous among the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſpared neither Sex nor Age, Man nor Beaſt, deſtroying neer eighty thouſand People. <hi>Boadicia,</hi> upon the fight hereof, with a courage mixt with the ſenſe of a Calamity already come, and to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, put a period to her days by poyſon, and prevented the future <hi>Roman</hi> Cruelties.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Paenius Poſthumus,</hi> Camp-maſter of the ſecond Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, hearing of this Victory, and being conſcious to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he had not done well in refuſing to obey the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals Order of being here at this Battail with that Legion, fell upon his Sword and dyed.</p>
               <p>After this, the Army kept the Field, and <hi>Nero,</hi> who was now Emperour, ſent them as a recruit, two thouſand Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionary Souldiers out of <hi>Germany,</hi> eight Cohorts of Aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iliaries, and one thouſand Horſe: The Nations which were either doubtful or Enemies, were waſted with Fire and Sword, but nothing did more afflict this diſtreſſed People than Famine, the <hi>Romans</hi> having ſecured all that they could get, and burnt and deſtroyed the reſt. <hi>Julius Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicianus</hi> was ſent to ſupply the Office of <hi>Cato,</hi> with whom <hi>Suctonius</hi> had ſome claſhes, and that did ſomewhat ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the Intendments of ſeveral Nations to ſubmit to a Peace; for he gave it out, that a new Governor was to be ſent, who would treat the People with more moderation, and ſent word to <hi>Rome,</hi> that nothing could be expected of good to the <hi>Roman</hi> affairs in <hi>Britain,</hi> until a new Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant was ſent, laying all the fault of ill ſucceſs on the frowardneſs of <hi>Suetonius,</hi> and all the good on the <hi>Roman</hi> fortune; thereupon <hi>Polycletus</hi> a freed Man, was ſent into <hi>Britain</hi> from <hi>Rome,</hi> to have an Inſpection into affairs; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon a great expectation from <hi>Nero,</hi> that he would not only reconcile the diſcords among the <hi>Romans,</hi> but alſo diſpoſe the <hi>Britains</hi> to a Peace. He came over with a great Army, but it ſeemed very ridiculous to the <hi>Britains</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:98589:44"/> that a Slave ſhould command thoſe that had made ſo great a Conqueſt.</p>
               <p>Not long after <hi>Suetonius</hi> was recall'd, upon an accident of ſome loſs at Sea which he had ſuſtained, and <hi>Petroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Turpulianus</hi> ſent in his room, a Man of an unactive ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and in whoſe time, all the care was to continue and encreaſe that peace, which <hi>Suetonius</hi> had left the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in.</p>
               <p>Him <hi>Trebellius Maximus</hi> ſucceeded, unexpert for War and unfit for action: it fell out in the time of Peace, after the late great Slaughter, the <hi>Britains</hi> having a deep ſenſe of it, that the <hi>Romans</hi> in <hi>Britany</hi> being without an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, whereof they might be afraid, began to diſagree one with another. <hi>Roſcius Caelius</hi> Lieutenant of the Twenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Legion, quarrelled with the Governor, objecting to him his Covetouſneſs, and the other to him his Faction, and by theſe Accidents, the Legions grew mutinous, and ſiding with <hi>Roſcius Caelius,</hi> drove <hi>Trebellius</hi> out of the Country, and for ſome time the under Officers governed the Army, wherein <hi>R. Caelius</hi> had the chiefeſt Intereſt, as being of the boldeſt nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vectius Bolanus</hi> was by <hi>Vitellius</hi> the Emperor ſent ſome time after to ſucceed him, a Man of whom it might be ſaid, that he was not hated for any Crime, and being withall good natured, he did procure to himſelf, rather Love than Obedience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Petilius Cerealis</hi> came next, a Man of a more warlike diſpoſition, who gave a conſiderable diſturbance to the Nation of the <hi>Brigantes,</hi> and made ſome Conqueſts upon them. <hi>Julius Frontinus</hi> did ſomething of the like naure upon the <hi>Silures,</hi> and him ſucceeded <hi>Agricola.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:98589:44"/>
               <head>Agricola'<hi>s <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakings and Conqueſts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A <hi>Gricola</hi> paſt the Seas, and came into <hi>Britain</hi> in the midſt of <hi>Summer;</hi> when he was here, he found the <hi>Ordovices</hi> had lately cut almoſt wholly to peeces a party quartered in their Country: Whereupon he ſummons in many of the Legionaries, and ſome Auxiliaries ſcattered in their Quarters, through the whole Province, (the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> not before ſuppoſing there would be any Action that <hi>Summer,</hi> the <hi>Winter</hi> drawing on) and with a conſiderable Body, marches into the Country of the <hi>Ordovices:</hi> here he made great ſpoil, revenging the Cruelty lately done up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Romans,</hi> with an extraordinary and <hi>Brutiſh</hi> ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to the greateſt part of the Nation, (which <hi>Tacitus</hi> his Son in Law does not poſitively deny: and I fear me not upon the valiant (for they were unwilling to deſcend out of the Woods and Faſtneſſes, into places where they were to Fight the <hi>Romans,</hi> upon ſo great tearms of diſadvantage, as they had lately another freſh experiment) but upon the Women, Children, and more tender People.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paulinus,</hi> as was ſaid before, was recall'd out of <hi>Mona</hi> the Iſle of <hi>Angleſey,</hi> and it ſhould ſeem, had not there ſo perfected his buſineſs, but that <hi>Agricola</hi> thought it might be matter of profit to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and honour to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to confirm the Conqueſt; whereupon he marches next way thither, and wanting Ships, upon ſo ſuddain a Reſolution, he contrives to Swim and Foard over that nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Water, which makes an Iſland of it, diſtinct from the other Country of <hi>Wales,</hi> with his Auxiliaries accuſtomed to ſuch Services. The People remembring their former miſery, and how that if they could not withſtand the <hi>Romans,</hi> when they had a leſs apprehenſion of them, they were not likely when they had enlarged their Province; without diſputing ſo much as their paſſage, Surrendred the Iſland to the mercy of thoſe, that they could not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably reſiſt, with hopes of ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Winter</hi> following, he contrives to ſecure what was gained, and among other of his Reſolutions, two he did
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98589:45"/> take of eſpecial benefit to the <hi>Roman</hi> Peace; the one was in the Tributes and Exactions upon the <hi>Britains:</hi> he took care that there ſhould be an equality, and corrected all thoſe petty Oppreſſions, in the collecting them, which uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally are more grievous, than the burden it ſelf: and as to the <hi>Roman</hi> Army, he made Election of Officers, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Merit, and not by Bribes, and affection, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation, whereby he rendred it very conſiderable for the next Expedition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Summer</hi> being come, he aſſembles them together, and firſt in diſcourſes, intermixing commendations and chidings, as they had done well or ill, takes afterwards his march, from one Country to another, up and down thoſe Places, which were either not as yet Conquered, or would not willingly ſubmit to Conditions; making great deſtruction. When the <hi>Summer</hi> was almoſt ſpent, he courts them with good words, and forbearance of Acts of Hoſtility, into tearms of Peace, which they willingly at laſt accepted; the Game inclining altogether on the <hi>Roman</hi> ſide: So a Peace is made with them, Hoſtages are given on the <hi>Britains</hi> part, for the ſecurity thereof, and ſeveral Garriſons plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on their Borders, with great Judgment, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a ſtrait and ſharp bridle to the <hi>Britains.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Winter</hi> following, he made a greater Conqueſt, then he had done the <hi>Summer</hi> before, but it was of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent nature. The <hi>Britains</hi> divided into petty Nations, had frequent Wars one upon another. So that Houſes of value to have been built, would have been ridiculous, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the frequency of their Wars, they could not have long ſtood free from Fire; and thereupon many other blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhments, as of Gardens, and Orchards, &amp;c. were negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted likewiſe. Their thoughts being active, and not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with theſe things, would be with ſomewhat elſe, and nothing was more obvious than the matter of War, whereto they gave their minds upon ſome neceſſity alſo, and in that Military Diſcipline, which was proper for pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Nations, in Woody and Boggy Countrys, as this then was; They were excellent in Art, and well fitted with ſtrong, reſolute and hardy Bodies. <hi>Agricola</hi> did not much fear an open Invaſion, from a People weak by their Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:98589:45"/> and naked; and amongſt whom there were many Trayterous to their Country, even Princes themſelves cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by the <hi>Romans:</hi> yet he might expect great diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance in parties out of the Woods, which would much obſtruct the quiet of the Country, and might deſtroy the Fruits of the Land.</p>
               <p>Hereupon he gets together about him many of the chief Nobility, commending to them the pleaſure and delight of a civil life in fine Buildings, neat Cloaths, Comptneſs of Language; which ſome affecting naturally, and others the rather to pleaſe the General, do obſerve and follow. Some diſtaſt theſe things, whom he diſgraces and villifies; but the other he commends, and gives them encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by granting aſſiſtance thereunto. By theſe means he ſoftned the Nation, and made them more lyable to the Impreſſions of the <hi>Roman</hi> ſteel upon all diſturbances; And of Conſequence, rendred their Province more ſecure.</p>
               <p>The next <hi>Summer</hi> he ſpent in a March Northwardly, Conquering ſeveral Nations, (that is to ſay) deſtroying their Country, and killing many where he met them, or they would attempt to ſet upon either his Army, or a party thereof, but this was ſparingly done; for whether the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> were terrified at the apprehenſions of the <hi>Romans,</hi> or this ſo great an Army, or that they had experimented a plain Field ſufficiently to their ſorrow already, or that they hoped to protract the War till <hi>Winter,</hi> expecting then to make uſe of the advantage they had, by their light Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; or for ſome, or all theſe Reaſons, they never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to joyn their Forces, and to give Battail, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in Woods, and Bogs, and places inacceſſable; make now and then ſome Incurſions on the <hi>Romans,</hi> but with no conſiderable effect: and he foreſeeing their thoughts prevented their attempts deſigned for <hi>Winter,</hi> by fortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divers Caſtles among them; which was done with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Judgment, as to the choice of the ſcite of the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and great Art as to the Model, and ſtored them with a twelve Months Proviſion before hand: ſo that what he gained by a ſtrong hand, he kept by prudent Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. In this Expedition, he paſs't beyond the Borders of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that now is, to a Water called <hi>Taus,</hi> beyond
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98589:46"/> 
                  <hi>Bodotria.</hi> The next <hi>Winter</hi> the <hi>Britains</hi> aſſaulted ſeveral of theſe Caſtles, and made ſome Incurſions into the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Quarters; but little miſchief was done.</p>
               <p>The fourth <hi>Summer</hi> was ſpent in ſecuring what was gained, and more eſpecially that narrow entrance into the further part of <hi>Scotland,</hi> lying between <hi>Glota</hi> and <hi>Bodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria,</hi> two Arms of the oppoſite Seas, they are now called <hi>Dun Britten</hi> and <hi>Edenburgh</hi> friths, which he did with Caſtles and Forts, as if having enlarged the Province, he deſired to make it the bounds of the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire that way.</p>
               <p>But the fifth <hi>Summer</hi> he paſs't beyond it, turning on his left hand, making ſeveral Conqueſts of Copuntrys border<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on <hi>Ireland,</hi> and placed many Souldiers therein, affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting a Conqueſt of that Iſland alſo: receiving to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Prince of that Country, come out upon private diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions then amongſt themſelves; to whom he was cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, with an intent to make ſuch uſe of him, as the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> had done with ſeveral others in <hi>Britain</hi> heretofore, (that is to ſay) to betray their Native Countries, to the pride and Luxury of the <hi>Romans;</hi> for at this time they were fallen from their ancient Virtue, though <hi>Agricola</hi> himſelf had ſome more than ordinary ſparks left.</p>
               <p>But the ſixth <hi>Summer,</hi> his thoughts were taken up by a diverſion on his right hand; for the <hi>Britains</hi> beyond <hi>Bodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria</hi> intending to aſſault the Garriſons, and divert his courſe, had already begun to make ſome attempts, by ſeizing the Paſſes, and aſſailing certain Caſtles. <hi>Agricola</hi> for his further ſecurity mann'd that <hi>Summer</hi> a conſiderable Fleet, which was of great uſe to him in his paſſage into the Country; for his March was by the Sea ſide, and his ſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not far from the Land. So that frequently the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers both of the Navy and Army met, and were in many reſpects very uſeful the one to the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Agricola</hi> ſuſpecting the <hi>Britains</hi> might have advantage upon him in number, divided his Army into three Parts, making his March with ſome Conſiderable diſtances, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thinking to prevent his being encompaſſed with a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude: a manifeſt errour doubtleſs againſt a new Enemy, whoſe valour he had not yet try'd, as appeared by the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98589:46"/> Conſequence, though he might gueſs ſhewdly at them, by what he had found in the reſt; for which <hi>Tacitus</hi> makes an excuſe that he had heard the <hi>Britains</hi> were divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Parties, and did intend ſo to ſet upon him. They ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this advantage in the dead of the Night, ſet upon the Ninth Legion, being ſomewhat weak of it ſelf, and with good ſucceſs; for they kill the Watch, enter the Camp, and therein Fight it manfully with the <hi>Romans;</hi> and had in all probability cut them off, if <hi>Agricola</hi> having notice of this accidentally by his Scouts, had not ſent the lighter-Armed with all expedition before hand to their ſuccour, and followed himſelf with the Legions. When the Battail was at laſt before and behind, the <hi>Britains,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a bloody Fight in the entrance of the Camp, the Day appearing, and the Legions alſo fled into the Woods. <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> tells us that, at the beginning of the <hi>Summer,</hi> ſeveral of his Officers upon a report of the Power of the Enemy, did adviſe him to retreat within the bounds of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly intended Province for his ſecurity, ſuſpecting very much the danger; but after this Victory, the very ſame did chiefly arrogate to themſelves the glory of that battle; an infirmity common to many Men of that diſpoſition to this day.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Britains</hi> with a noble reſolution did attribute the loſs of this day, not to the valour, but craft and fortune of the <hi>Roman</hi> General. With this conceit they make very much greater Preparations, confederate themſelves by So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Rites, and convey their Wives and Children into places of ſafety, intending in a Field to try their fortune again with their new-rais'd Forces.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Britains</hi> had thirty thouſand Men deſigned for the main Battail, beſides many young and old Voluntiers, who out of an honourable reſolution came to partake in the fortune of a Day; over whom, <hi>Galgacus</hi> of great deſcent and virtue, to be mentioned not without honour to his name, commanded in Chief. They took up their ground upon the declining of the Hill <hi>Grampius,</hi> now <hi>Grantz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bain;</hi> the firſt Battalion ſtood upon the Plain, the Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots and Horſe paſſing up and down with great noiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Battail, expecting the <hi>Romans.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:98589:47"/>
               <p>The <hi>Romans</hi> having ſent their Fleet before, by frequent and uncertain Landings, as they did ſome other miſchief, ſo they could not but make ſome diſtraction upon the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains:</hi> but at laſt <hi>Agricola</hi> takes his March directly to them that were prepar'd to receive him, having with him certain of the Country, whoſe faith and courage was a long time known to be truer to the <hi>Romans,</hi> than to their own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. His Battail he orders thus, eight thouſand Auxilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries were placed in a Body, and in the Van; on each Wing three thouſand Horſe were divided, in the Rear his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionaries were; the whole Front being extended beyond a juſt and uſual proportion: <hi>Agricola</hi> thinking thereby to prevent ſurrounding by the Enemy which over-numbered him.</p>
               <p>The Speech of <hi>Galgacus,</hi> as it is delivered by <hi>Tacitus,</hi> is to this purpoſe. When I conſider the cauſe of this War, and our neceſſary, I am greatly confident, this day, and this your conſent will give a happy beginning to the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the whole Iſland. We all have hitherto lived in Liberty; and moreover, no Land remaineth beyond, and no Sea for our ſafety, the <hi>Roman</hi> Navy, thus as you ſee, hanging on our Coaſts; So that Arms, which Men of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue deſire for honour, the faint-hearted muſt alſo uſe for his ſecurity. The former Battails, which have with divers events been fought againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> had their hope and reſerves in our hands: For we, the choice of the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Nobility, and ſeated in the furthermoſt receſſes, never yet had view of the enſlaved ſhoares, nor were our eyes offended with the ſight of ſubjection. This inward bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome hath defended us, the boundary of Land and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty for this Day of Glory. Now the uttermoſt point of the Country is laid open, and things, the leſs they have been within knowledge, the greater the glory is to atchieve them. What Nation is there now beyond us, what elſe but Water and Rocks, and the <hi>Romans</hi> Lords of all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; whoſe intollerable pride, in vain ſhall you ſeek to avoid by ſervice or ſubmiſs demeanour; Robbers of the World, that having now left no Land to plunder, ſearch alſo the Sea it ſelf. If the Enemy be rich, they are greedy of his wealth; if poor, they covet glory: whom not the Eaſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98589:47"/> nor Weſt have ſatisfied: they only of all Men, with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual luſt affecting riches and vanity. To rob, kill, and commit rapine, falſly they terme Empire; and when they have brought deſolation to a Country, they call it Peace. Children, and neer Relations, every Man by nature hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth moſt dear, and thoſe are preſſed for Souldiers, and carryed away to ſerve in a ſlaviſh condition: Siſters and Wives, though they may eſcape an open raviſhment, are notwithſtanding frequently proſtituted when they come as Gueſts, and pretend friendſhip. The goods and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Conquered they exhauſt with Tributes, and rob them of their Corn to ſupply their Garriſons, weary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out their Hands and Bodies in preparing Woods and Fenny places for their purpoſes, with a thouſand ſtripes and indignities. Slaves which are born to bondage when they are once ſold, are after maintained at their Maſters expences: but <hi>Britain</hi> daily buyeth her own bondage, and is at the charge of continuing it. Now as in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate retinue, the freſh man and laſt comer is moſt abuſed by his very fellow-ſervants: So in this old ſervitude of the World, our deſtruction is ſought being the lateſt, and is moſt vile in account. We have no Fields to manure, no Mines to be digged, no Ports to trade in, and to what purpoſe then ſhould they reſerve us alive? Moreover the man-hood and fierce courage of the Subject pleaſeth not much the jealous Soveraign: and this corner being ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and out of the way, the more ſecurity it yieldeth to us, in them it works the greater ſuſpicion. So ſeeing all hope of pardon is paſt, at length all of you take courage, as well theſe to whom ſafety, as ſuch to whom glory is in greateſt eſteem. The <hi>Britains</hi> led by a Woman, fired the Colony, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Caſtles; and if ſuch a lucky beginning had not ended in ſloath and ſecurity, they might have with eaſe ſhak't off the Yoak. We as yet never touched, never ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued; and born to be free, not to be Slaves to the <hi>Romans:</hi> let us ſhew ſtreight in the firſt joyning what manner of Men <hi>Caledonia</hi> reſerved in ſtore for her ſelf. Or, do you think the <hi>Romans</hi> to be as valiant in War, as they are wanton in Peace? No, not by their virtue, but by our diſcords they are grown into fame: and the faults of their Enemies they
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98589:48"/> abuſe, to the glory of their own Army, compoſed of moſt divers Nations: and therefore as by the preſent proſperity holden together, ſo if fortune do frown, it doubtleſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolveth them; unleſs you ſuppoſe the <hi>Galls</hi> and <hi>Germans,</hi> and to our ſhame be it ſpoken, many of our own Nation, which now lend their lives to eſtabliſh forreign Uſurpation; yet have been Enemies longer than Servants, to be led and induced with any true faith and affection. No, it is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and fear, weak procurers of love, which if you remove, thoſe which ſhall have ceaſed to be afraid, will ſtrait be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to hate. All things that do incite to the Victory are on our ſide. No Wife to encourage the <hi>Romans,</hi> no Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to upbraid them if they flee; moſt have either no Country at all, or ſome other: a few fearfull Perſons trembling, and gazing at the ſtrangeneſs of the Heaven it ſelf, the Sea, and the Woods; whom the Gods have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, mewed up, and as it were fettered into our hands. Let not the vain ſhew, and glittering of Gold and Silver terrify us: which neither defends nor offendeth amongſt the Enemies. We ſhall finde aſſiſtance on our ſide: The <hi>Britains</hi> will own their own cauſe, the <hi>Galls</hi> will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their former freedome, the reſt of the <hi>Germans</hi> will leave and forſake them, as of late the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſipians</hi> did. And what elſe have we then to fear? The Caſtles are empty, the Colonies peopled with Aged and impotent Perſons, the free Cities diſcontent, and in factions, whilſt thoſe which are under obey, with ill-will; and they which do Govern, rule againſt right. Here is the General, and here the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; there Tributes and Mines, and other miſeries inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably following them, who live under ſubjection of others: which whether we are to continue for ever, or ſtraight to revenge it, lyeth this day in this Field. Wherefore go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Battail, bear in your minds, I beſeech you, both your Anceſtors, and your Poſterity.</p>
               <p>Which whether it be the Production only of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors brain, or that much of it was ſaid, it matters not; however, I think the memory of it is not remembred here amiſs. The Speech was received by a various noiſe of Songs and Acclamations.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:98589:48"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Agricola</hi>'s is thus delivered: fellow Souldiers and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions in Arms, your ſervice and diligence theſe eight years ſo painfully ſhew'd, by the virtue and fortune of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire hath Conquered <hi>Britain.</hi> In ſo many Battails we had of neceſſity to ſhew our ſelves either valiant againſt the Enemy, or patient and laborious almoſt againſt Nature it ſelf. In which exploits we have born us both hitherto, ſo that neither did I deſire better Souldiers, nor you other Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. We have exceeded the limits, I of my Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and you likewiſe of yours. The end of <hi>Britain</hi> is found, not by fame and report, but we are with our Arms and Pavilions really inveſted thereof, <hi>Britany</hi> is found and ſubdued. In Marching, when the paſſing of Boggs or Mountains, and Rivers troubled and tired you out, how oft have I heard the valiant Souldier ſay? When will the Enemy ſhew himſelf, when ſhall we Fight? ſee now they are before you, you have here your wiſhes, and a place for your virtue to be ſhewn in, and all things to follow in an eaſie and expedite courſe if you win; if you looſe, all againſt you. For as to have gone ſo much ground, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped the Woods, paſſed over the Firthes, is honourable forward; ſo if we do flee the vantages, we have this day will become our chief hurt. For we are not skilled ſo well in the Countrys, we have not the like ſtore of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, but Hands we have and Weapons, and therein all things included. For my part, I have been long ſince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, that to ſhew their backs, is neither ſafety for Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier nor General: and therefore a commendable death is better, than life with reproach; and ſurety and honour are commonly dwelling together: or if ought ſhould miſhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, even this will be a glory, to have died in the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt end of the World and nature. If new Nations and Souldiers unknown were in the Field, I would by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of other Arms put you in courage: now recount you your own victorious exploits, and ask your own eyes. Theſe are the ſame Men which the laſt year aſſailed one Legion by ſtealth in the night, and were with ſmall work overthrown: Theſe of all other <hi>Britains</hi> have been the moſt nimble in running away, and therefore have eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98589:49"/> the longeſt alive. For as in Forreſts and Woods the ſtrongeſt Beaſts are chaſed away by main force, the cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly and fearfull are frighted by the noiſe of the Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. So the valiant of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Nation we have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy diſpatched, the timerous and moſt inconſiderable on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remain; whom at length you have found, not as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving intended to ſtay and make Head, but at laſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, and by extream paſſion of fear ſtanding as ſtocks preſenting occaſion to us in this place of a worthy and memorable Victory. Make an end therfore of your war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, and to fifty years travels, let this day impoſe a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious concluſion: approve to your Country that the Army could never juſtly be charged either with protracting the War, or pretences for not accompliſhing the Conqueſt. This was received with great Alacrity.</p>
               <p>The Battail it ſelf alſo, becauſe it does conſummate the Conqueſt of this Iſland, and is by <hi>Tacitus</hi> not only excellently, but very indifferently deſcribed, take alſo from him. <hi>Agricola</hi> leaving his Horſe, advanced himſelf before the Enſigns of Foot: In the firſt encounter, before joyning, both ſides diſcharged, and threw their miſſive Weapons: wherein the <hi>Britains</hi> employing both Art and Valour, with their great Swords and little Targets avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our throws, or ſhook them off, darting withall great ſtore of theirs againſt us: till at length <hi>Agricola</hi> ſpying his advantage, exhorted three Batavian Cohorts, and two of the Tungrians to preſs forward, and bring the matter to a cloſe Fight, (a thing which they in reſpect of long ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice were able readily to perform, and contrarily to the Enemies prejudicial) and hurtful by reaſon of their little Bucklers and huge Swords; for the Swords of the <hi>Britains</hi> being blunt pointed, were no way fit for cloſe or open Fight. Now as the <hi>Batavians</hi> began to ſtrike with their Swords, and thruſt with the Pikes of their Bucklers, to mangle their Faces, and (having over-born in the Plain all that reſiſted them,) to March up the Mountains, the reſt of the Cohorts gathering courage, upon emulation, violently beat down all about them, and many half dead, or wholly untouched, were left, for haſt of winning the Field. In the mean time the Chariots mingled themſelves with the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98589:49"/> Battel of the Footmen, and the Troops of the Horſemen began to flee: who, albeit they had lately terrified others, were now diſtreſſed themſelves by the unevenneſs of the ground, and thick Forces of their Enemies. Neither was the form of the Fight like a looſe Skirmiſh of Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to and fro, but ſtanding ſtill, and maintaining their places, they ſought by main weight of Horſes to break and bear down one another. The wandring Waggons alſo, and maſterleſs Horſes, afrighted as it hapned them by fear to be guided, overbare many which met them, or thwarted their way. Now the <hi>Britains</hi> which ſtood a loof from the Battel, on the height of the Hi'ls, and at their good leaſure diſdaining our fewneſs, began to come down by little and little, and to compaſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the backs of our men, which were now in probable expectation of winning the Field. But <hi>Agricola,</hi> ſuſpecting, as much, oppoſed againſt them four Wings of Horſemen, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely retained about him for ſudden diſpatches &amp; chances of War, and repulſed them back as ſharply, as fiercely they ran to aſſail. So the Counſel of the <hi>Britains</hi> turned upon their own heads: and the Wings were commanded to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Battel, and follow the flight. Then might you have ſeen in the open fields a great &amp; horrid ſpectacle; purſuing, wounding, taking, and killing of them which were taken, when others came in the way. Now whole Regiments of the Enemies, according to their ſeveral diſpoſitions, though Armed, and more in number, turned their backs to the fewer others unarmed, and ſought their own death, offering themſelves voluntarily to the ſlaughter. Every where Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons lay ſcattered, and Bodies, and mangled Limbs; the Ground every where imbrued with Blood, and ſometimes, even in them which were overcome, appeared now at their end both Anger and Valour. When they approached the Woods, uniting themſelves, they entraped unawares ſome of the foremoſt of our men, which unadviſedly followed, not knowing the Countrey: And unleſs <hi>Agricola</hi> had with his preſence every where aſſiſted at need, ſetting about them of his braveſt and moſt ready foot-men, as it were in form of a Toyl, and commanding ſome of his Cavalry to leave their Horſes, where the paſſages were narrow, and others
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98589:50"/> where the Woods were thin, to ride up and down moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; no doubt, ſayes he, we had taken ſome blow by our overmuch boldneſs. But after they did ſee our men again in ſtrong array to follow the chaſe in good order, they fled, (not in Troops as before, and attending each other, but ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly disbanded, and ſingle, eſchewing all company) toward the Deſart, and far diſtant places. The night, and our fulneſs of blood, made an end of the chaſe. Of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſide, Ten thouſand were ſlain: Three hundred and forty of ours, amongſt whom was <hi>Aulus Atticus,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief of a Cohort, upon a youthful heat, and through the fierceneſs of Horſe, being carried into the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of his Enemies.</p>
               <p>That night the Winners, for their parts, ſolaced them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the Victory and Spoil: and the <hi>Britains</hi> being utterly broken, crying out, and howling; men and women together take and draw with them their hurt perſons, call not hurt, forſake their own Houſes, and in deſpite alſo ſet them on fire themſelves; chooſe out Holes for to lurk in, and ſtreightwayes forſook them; communicate ſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels together, and then have ſome glimmering of hope: ſometimes at the ſight of their deareſt beloved they are moved to pitty, more often ſtirred to rage: and certain it is, that ſome, as by way of compaſſion and mercy, ſlew their own Children and Wives. The day following, diſcovered more plainly the greatneſs of the Victory; every where de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation and ſilence; no ſtirring in the Mountains; the Houſes fired and ſmoaking far off: no man to meet with our Scouts: who being ſent abroad into all the Quarters, found by their footſteps the flight was uncertain, and that they were no where in Companies together.</p>
               <p>Hereupon <hi>Agricola,</hi> becauſe the Summer was ſpent, and the War could not conveniently be divided, bringing his Army into the Borders of the <hi>Horreſtians,</hi> ſuppoſed in <hi>Esk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi> where receiving Hoſtages, he commanded the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral of the Navie to Sail about <hi>Britain,</hi> lending him Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and ſtrength for that purpoſe, and the terror of the <hi>Roman</hi> Name was gone before already; and he with eaſie and gentle Journeys, to terrifie the new conquered Nations, with the very ſtay of his paſſage, diſpoſed his Footmen and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98589:50"/> Horſemen into their Wintering Places: and withall, the Navy with proſperous Wind and ſucceſs, arrived at the Port <hi>Trutulenſis,</hi> from whence it departed; and coaſting along the neereſt ſide of <hi>Britain,</hi> returned thither again, having invaded in its paſſage the Iſles of <hi>Orkney.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this, <hi>Domitian</hi> the Emperor, envying his Glory, ſent for him home, when he had compleated the Conqueſt of ſo much of <hi>Britain,</hi> as was formed into a <hi>Roman</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, from the two Arms of <hi>Glota</hi> and <hi>Bodotria</hi> before mentioned, to the Southward, incluſive of that part of the Iſland; more doubtleſs he did deſign to invade and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs, and like enough he had effected it upon all the North, and Ireland alſo, if <hi>Domitian</hi>'s apprehenſions had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call'd and prevented him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Concluſion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Conqueſts in this Iſland.</head>
               <p>THus all on the Southern part of <hi>Glota</hi> and <hi>Bodotria,</hi> about the year of Grace, eighty ſix, was by degrees brought under ſubjection to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and formed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Province, or rather three; the <hi>Trent</hi> and <hi>Severne</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Diviſions; that part next <hi>Rome,</hi> being called <hi>Britania prima;</hi> the Capital place <hi>London:</hi> from which <hi>Canterbury</hi> took after the dignity of the Seat, to the Arch-Biſhop of that Province; for the Diviſions of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Juriſdiction, did follow thoſe of the Temporal in their firſt appointments. That which was beyond <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne</hi> was called <hi>Secunda: Caer Leon</hi> upon <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ske</hi> in <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouthſhire,</hi> being then the principal place, and Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Seat. <hi>Maxima Caeſarienſis</hi> was that, beyond <hi>Trent; York</hi> being the chief Reſidence and See.</p>
               <p>Hence it might be, that when <hi>Wales</hi> was in the Princes of their Country, and diſunited; that which remained in <hi>England,</hi> was divided betwixt the Juſtices in <hi>Eyre,</hi> by the River <hi>Trent,</hi> in affairs concerning the Forreſt; and the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralds in their proper buſineſs. Hence it might be, that in the piece of Money, expos'd to view by Mr. <hi>Cambden,</hi> where on one ſide, was this Inſcription, <hi>Hadrianus Aug. Conſul</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:98589:51"/> 
                  <hi>iij. Pater Patriae,</hi> and on the other, <hi>Exercitus Britanicus;</hi> three Souldiers being Pourtrayed on this, and the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors Effigies on the other ſide, (which the ſame Author would have to ſignify the three Legions, that ſerved here about his time; that is to ſay, <hi>Secunda Auguſta, Sexta Victrix,</hi> and <hi>Viceſſima Victrix:)</hi> like enough it is, they had particular Relation to the three ſeveral Provinces. And hence it might be that <hi>Geoffry</hi> of <hi>Monmouth</hi> did feigne the Diviſion of the Country into <hi>Loegria Cambria</hi> and <hi>Albania,</hi> to come from the three Sons of <hi>Brute, Locrine, Camber</hi> and <hi>Albanact;</hi> becauſe he thought it neceſſary to deliver Fathers to the ſeveral Diviſions of the Country he found here.</p>
               <p>The Provinces continued for ſome hundreds of years under the <hi>Roman</hi> Juriſdiction, the Limits a little varyed and drawn back, and ſome Diſturbances falling out, but neither very conſiderable.</p>
               <p>And now was founded that Government, as I take it, here in <hi>England,</hi> which has continued in the bulk and groſs thereof through many Ages, to this day, or at leaſt not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh't at any time, though not without certain addings and ſubſtraction, and now and then ſomekind of interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but yet did they never ſo far proceed, as utterly to diſcontinue that Series, which had its root even in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time of <hi>Romulus,</hi> at the Foundation of <hi>Rome.</hi> And upon the coming in of the <hi>Romans,</hi> here was alſo introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced one other form of Government, which having its Riſe in the dayes of <hi>Moſes</hi> among the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> with a fortune not unlike the other; firſt inſinuating it ſelf into the <hi>Roman</hi> Veins, upon the Conqueſt of <hi>Jury,</hi> and then ſpreading into all the parts thereof, came hither alſo, being a Member of it, and did ſo incorporate into that Body, varying fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in outward appearance, by divers Factions; but continuing in a great part the ſame to this day among us: both being alike, cut off from the main Body; the firſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ages agoe, the laſt in the dayes of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, and united in the Perſon of one ſingle Monarch: both ſtill retaining a great Portion of the ſame Nature they had ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally, though in ſome particulars altered as in ſuch anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent things it cannot be otherwiſe expected. But becauſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:98589:51"/> much of this many do not think of, and our Hiſtoriogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers do generally give a much later Original to certain Laws, and Cuſtoms, and Diviſions of our Countrey in the Civil Government; yet reprehended ſome of them in the times they are poſitive in, by my Lord <hi>Cook,</hi> Mr. <hi>Camden,</hi> Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> Sir <hi>H. Spelman,</hi> and other eminent Antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: We will leave this Argument at preſent, and cloſe with certain words of Doctor <hi>HEYLIN,</hi> an Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and Judicious Geographer, of the like Nature. He having Diſcourſed ſome time of <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ROPE</hi> upon the whole, comes at laſt to begin his particular Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in theſe words. And this ſhall ſerve for Europe in the general Notion: Deſcend we now to the particular King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Regions &amp; Iſlands of it, beginning firſt of all with <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> contrary to the uſage of moſt Geographers, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly begin with <hi>Spain</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> as being the fartheſt Countreys Weſtward, and conſequently neareſt to the firſt Meridian, from whence the Longitude was reckoned. Which we ſhall do by reaſon of that great influence which the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> had in moſt parts of Europe, and many parts of the World beſides, in matters as well Civil as Eccleſiaſtical, which much depended on the Power of that Empire for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, and on the uſurpation of that Church in the latter dayes.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:98589:52"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98589:52"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEſides ſome Errors in pointing, you are deſired to Correct theſe underwritten, which have eſcaped the Preſs by reaſon of the Authors abſence.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Introduction.</head>
               <p>PAge 26 Line 32 adde <hi>in.</hi> P. 32. L. 18. for <hi>ſereral</hi> r. <hi>ſeveral.</hi> P. 33. L. 31. for <hi>preſence</hi> r. <hi>Boſome.</hi> P. 35. L. 27. r. <hi>to him who.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the History.</head>
               <p>P. 3. L. 17. after the word <hi>and</hi> r. <hi>is.</hi> P. 5. L. 6. for <hi>druids</hi> r. <hi>denotes.</hi> L. 12. Leave out the word <hi>(was)</hi> P. 8. L. 25. for <hi>Moni</hi> r. <hi>Mons.</hi> P. 20. L. 5. before the word <hi>confederated</hi> r. <hi>their.</hi> P. 31. L. 3. for <hi>Donaries</hi> r. <hi>Denaries.</hi> P. 34. L. 33. r. <hi>with other bounds at the Sea.</hi> P. 42. L. 28. for <hi>upon</hi> r. <hi>up to.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
